This video is going to be very difficult to make and it's going to be very difficult for you to understand
Because I'm going to be talking about
Mathematical formulas and I'm going to be talking a lot about mathematics. So if you don't understand mathematics
Don't watch this video
Okay next but hey, how about the Earth's magnetic field this is hilarious
There's magnetic field has been measured since 1835 and it's growing weaker, which means it used to be
Stronger you guys are on the ball. Okay. Here's the problem. The evolutionists have though folks if we extrapolate backwards
Just as 20,000 years ago how long 20,000 years ago 20 million not 20 minutes would be billion 20 billion 20,000 years ago
The heat produced by the magnetic field would have liquefied the earth
20,000 years ago and a million years ago folks if this the magnetic field would have been so strong
It would have vaporized our planet vaporize the planet
Now I had to think long and hard about this because even for a creationist theory
This is nuts. How would the Earth's magnetic field melt anything?
The first thing I did was to figure out exactly how much heat it would take to melt the Earth's crust
over 30 trillion trillion kilojoules
I'm sure the heating engineers watching this will tell you my calculation is dodgy and to be honest
I haven't really checked it but still we need a staggering amount of heat to liquefy the earth
Even Crohn's fellow creationists would tell him this sounds nuts
So here's what I think happened Billy was sitting at the breakfast table one morning reading a book by Thomas Barnes a
Creationist who argued that because the Earth's magnetic field is decaying it must have been excessively high in the past
Working his way through a bowl of sugar-frosted sugar loops Crohn thought very high magnetic field Wow like those energy fields in Star Wars and stuff
Maybe it would like heat up the planet or something. Hey wait vaporize the entire planet
But the Earth's magnetic field doesn't even melt ice at the poles where it interacts with the Earth's surface
So it's not going to melt any rocks firstly Barnes made a crucial error
He assumed that the magnetic field was generated by an electrical circuit within the earth
Which is an old idea long discarded as the energy runs down thought Barnes the electrical circuit weakens and the magnetic field dies
So extrapolate back and the magnetic field would have been much stronger in the past now his reasoning would mean
That the electrical current needed to produce such a huge magnetic field would have required a huge amount of energy
Yes enough energy to melt every rock on the planet
Unable to climb down from the chair on which he was dancing
Crohn mistook the high amount of energy required to generate the magnetic field to mean that the magnetic field itself
generated energy since Barnes wrote that book in 1973
Researchers have discovered that it's not free electrons that generate the magnetic field but the movement of molten rock that acts as a kind of dynamo
thermodynamic currents are caused by heating and cooling just as happens in the world's oceans and
Just as oceans circulate because of the motion of the earth so does molten rock under the surface
The magnetic field strengthens and weakens according to the dynamics of this circulation
Okay, Billy what else now folks here's the problem with the evolutionary time scale runs in the major problems starting with just one couple
Hey people not eight people just one couple just 41,000 years ago. Did you say a million not a million two million?
Not two million just 41,000 years ago taking into wars and all that stuff the population on earth by now folks would be two to
Ten to the 89th power. How great is that number? This number is so great folks
There would not be enough space in the universe to hold that many bodies
I
Can't dissect Billy Crohn's calculations because he doesn't give us any calculations
So does anyone have a mathematical analysis of this population thing, but if you're good at mathematics
You're probably gonna understand what I'm trying to say
Well, I wanted to avoid some difficult math, but I guess there's no way around it
Human population history has been calculated by geneticists and anthropologists, but as you can see the math is not easy
This is just one part of one paper
Analyzing the manifestation of inbreeding in genes and its effect on population
So, let's see what creationist mathematicians have come up with to debunk it
And if you want to watch this video and you're not very good at maths then try and understand what I'm saying and try and stay
Along, okay fair enough. I'll listen carefully to your argument and if I manage to spot a flaw at some point
I'll stop the video. We have the original population
Okay, let me stop you there
No part of evolution theory suggests that the original population of humans was two
Humans evolved in groups through the interchange of genes
We can all trace our ancestry back to one man and one woman, of course
But they lived at different times in different places. There was never an original pair of breeding humans
But do go on the population doubles every 150 years. Sorry. I have to stop you again on what basis did the prehistoric population
Double every 150 years. Where does that figure come from? I
Messaged truthful Christian to ask him for his source and he wrote back
I got this number from a friend of mine at the fitness club in my local area
Yes, but it's not
Look
scientists have spent decades researching human population through
Archaeological evidence and the mapping of the human genome and they've written volumes of scientific papers
Calculating past population growth based on this evidence and you're saying that all they really needed to do was ask Richard Simmons
Now I don't want to be too hard on truthful Christian because no one who sincerely wanted to pull the wool over our eyes
Would be so honest as to admit that his scientific information comes from the local gym and truthful
Christian was honest enough under no pressure from me to accept that he may be wrong and his numbers may not be accurate
So clearly this guy isn't out to deliberately deceive and this disqualifies him for a golden crocodile
But let's pursue this local fitness club connection. I think I may have traced it back to this line from answers in Genesis
Let us assume a IG says that the population doubles every 150 years
Why assume such an arbitrary figure? Why not 80 or 200 or 120?
Because answers in Genesis was working backwards
the Bible gave it a starting population of eight people and a IG wanted to show that after
4,500 years that population would expand to 6.5 billion
Knowing the answer made the math very easy
What rate of growth is required to get that answer turns out to be a doubling every 150 years?
So then answers in Genesis turned the calculation around and started at the beginning if the population
4,500 years ago was eight people and assuming a doubling of the population every oh, I don't know. Let's say
150 years what population should we have today?
Why it works out to 6.5 billion and since that's what we've got the Bible must be right
Then using the same arbitrary doubling of population every 150 years
What population would we have today if humans have been around for 40,000 years?
There would not be enough space in the universe to hold that many bodies
But of course a doubling of the population every 150 years never happened for most of human history
Human populations expand according to the resources that are available to fuel that expansion
Hunter-gatherers have very low population growth because the land can't support a large population of hunter-gatherers
When the neolithic farming revolution came along populations grew because the same amount of land could support more people
And when cities grew up in Egypt Mesopotamia India and China they could support larger populations still
So prior to the neolithic human populations didn't grow very fast at all. They were constrained by the resources that fed them
Into this mix you have to add the occasional mass
Extermination
Around 70,000 years ago a volcanic eruption in Sumatra caused global cooling which reduced the human population to as little as
10,000 people in Africa and India
Coming up with ideas about human population at the breakfast table is easy if you apply arbitrary numbers and do a bit of simple math
Conducting careful research over decades doing more sophisticated
Sophisticated mathematical calculations not making arbitrary assumptions and basing every conclusion on the evidence is much harder
But the result stands up to scrutiny