["Ach, wie dichtig, wie flüchtig, ach, wie dichtig, wie flüchtig, wie dichtig, wie flüchtig ist der Mensch im Himmel"]
Oh, hey, Quarch. Hey, how are you, Quarch?
Okay, listen. I know this looks bad.
I know you think I'm bougie and you're here to take me to the guillotine.
Well, fair enough.
But before you do, can a dying queen make one request?
How about this?
I'm the new Scheherazade, so you can cut my head off,
but first, you have to let me tell you my life story.
Fair? That's super fucking great.
Now sit down, bitch, and allow me to explain myself.
I'll start at the beginning.
My earliest memories are of aesthetic bliss.
I was raised in a suburb of Washington, D.C.,
where the most exciting attraction for children is the National Museum of Natural History.
At least, it's the most exciting attraction for nerdy children,
who, might I add, deserve their abuse at the hands of dumber, cooler children.
Kids usually gather around the fossils, and don't get me wrong,
I liked a good stegosaurus as much as the next five-year-old,
but my real passion was the Gem and Mineral Hall.
Ugh, the sparkle and shimmer.
It inspired me to start my own little gem collection.
I had amethyst, quartz, obsidian, jade.
The little pleasure of each stone was almost enough to make up
for my sixth-grade teacher, Mrs. Romano, forcing me to pee my pants in public.
Fuck you, Romano. I'm glad your father died.
Comrades, losers, and haters, I would like to propose
that aesthetic sensibility, whether for gemstones, architecture, fashion, or music,
begins with absolute pleasure.
You rotate the crystal in your hand and are dazzled by the sparkle and the light.
Your nape hair stands on end, and a tingle goes down your spine.
Yes, God!
But as you get older, things get more complicated.
Northern Virginia is McMansion country,
and while my family lived in a more modest colonial,
I remember riding around in the back of the minivan,
looking at some stylistically jumbled monstrosities,
and I would get excited by some little detail,
like, say, a circle of fake battlements atop a misplaced tower.
But then my mom would say,
Look at this ostentatious trash!
So you learn.
You learn taste according to the social class of your upbringing.
And with taste comes all this adult baggage,
snobbery and pretense and conceit.
So I don't know what you've heard from my accusers,
but I assure you, I have nothing to do with taste.
I am but a simple queen longing for the pleasure of my childhood gems.
So, stripey sock catgirls of the heckin' Revolutionary Committee,
before you pass sentence,
allow me to make my case gorge.
One. Success.
Oh hey, how are you, gorge?
Look, I like stuff.
I like shiny things.
For me, there really is still a simple, childlike pleasure to it all.
But the adult reality is, opulence is more than just shimmer and sparkle.
There's a social context for it.
It generally means something.
Why does Donald Trump's apartment look like Liberace married a Turkmenistani dictator
and moved into a cheesecake factory?
Well, because he's trying to send a message.
Maybe to the world, maybe to himself.
He's saying,
Behold, I am a winner, a very stable genius with one of the highest IQs.
Powerful people have often used opulence to symbolize their power,
from the pharaohs of Egypt to the kings of France
to even the humble servants of the world's major religions.
I guess God likes shiny things too.
In America, opulence more specifically means not just power, but success.
It is the trophy by which you show the world that you've achieved the American Dream.
The plotline of our central cultural myth is the story of rags to riches.
In the words of Drake,
Started from the bottom, now we're here.
Started from the bottom, now the whole team's fucking here.
Opulence is the aesthetic display that you're here.
You've made it.
You're rich, bitch.
Remember in high school when you had to read
The Great Gatsby by F. Scott Sparknotes?
The character Jay Gatsby doesn't even like opulent mansion parties,
but he throws them anyway just to show his crush Daisy that he's made it,
that he's a success, that he's worth something.
And as we all remember, in the end,
they get married and defeat the monster Grendel to save the Hall of Hrothgar.
At least, that's what I wrote in my 10th grade English essay
about how the theme of The Great Gatsby is money always leads to happiness.
I got a D minus.
I like dollars, I like diamonds, I like money, I like shining,
I like those Balenciagas.
Fuck.
I'm sure Cardi B really does like diamonds and red bottoms
and driving lambs and all that shit,
but teacher, pick me, pick me.
Let's talk about symbols.
Let's talk about allegory.
Let's talk about metaphor.
Let's talk about themes.
Fellow students, let us place the text in historical context.
Everyone knows that Cardi B went from being a teenage stripper
to making money moves.
That's the American Dream.
Hip-hop opulence isn't just gratuitous glitz and hedonism.
It's a celebration of success for people who often come from backgrounds
where that kind of success is really improbable.
Don't you think it's kind of weird that conservatives still say,
rap music is the reason for the problems with the blacks?
For conservatives, the American Dream is supposed to be the solution to poverty.
And is there any sector of our culture
where the American Dream is more unironically celebrated than hip-hop?
It's not just hip-hop, though.
Flaunted wealth is pretty inescapable throughout pop culture.
You can't even turn on the radio without hearing about the Gucci
and the Ferraris and the Fendi and the Bugattis
and the Armani and the Maseratis.
Our entire culture has been replaced by a parade of overpriced Italian bullshit.
Which, to be clear, I'm completely in favor of.
Burn down the Statue of Liberty for all I fucking care
and replace it with a large-scale figure of Donatello Versace
holding a bottle of Cristal.
That's at least a more honest representation of our culture
than the hypocritical cheese furs currently inscribed on Liberty Island.
I guess Cristal's French, isn't it?
Well, no one really drinks Italian booze.
We have standards in this country.
Listen up, America.
We live in a society.
A society of champagne wishes and caviar dreams.
Not of climbers, but of graspers.
To paraphrase Ian Danskin,
maybe anyone can achieve the American dream,
but everyone cannot.
And the fact of the matter is,
most people don't.
I mean, what would it even mean to be rich
unless someone else was poor?
I mean, who's gonna polish your golden toilet?
Not other rich people, that's for sure.
So when you live in a society
that constantly equates wealth and success,
but which is also so unequal
that most people will never be wealthy,
well, what's the average person supposed to do?
Two, fantasy.
I wish the world were my gem collection.
I wish I owned everything.
I'm really just the worst kind of Philistine, you know?
I go to an art museum and it's like,
Monet, Rembrandt,
okay, that's super fucking great,
but can I buy it?
Well, no, I can't buy it.
The grim reality is, you can't own everything.
So what do you do?
Well, you fake it.
You create an illusion.
I don't own this building,
and you rube off the streets of Baltimore
and walk in here, as indeed you did.
But that's okay. I need a witness.
I need you to see me here
among the other art,
where I belong.
Being seen that way, it makes me feel good, you know?
It makes me feel valuable.
You know, you don't actually need wealth to be opulent,
because opulence is not abundance.
Opulence is the aesthetic of abundance.
It is the aesthetic of owning everything.
The phrase, opulence, you own everything,
is at this point, basically a gay internet meme.
Opulence.
Opulence, opulence, opulence, opulence.
But it originally comes from the documentary
Paris is Burning,
about the Harlem ballroom culture in the 1980s,
where it's proclaimed by MC Jr. LaBeija.
O-P-U-L-E-N-C-E.
Opulence.
You own everything.
It's not a celebration of a real lifestyle
of luxury and decadence.
In fact, as Pepper LaBeija says
of the queer Black and Latin American participants
of the balls,
A lot of those kids that are in the balls,
they don't have two of nothing.
Some of them don't even eat.
So ballroom opulence is a fantasy of wealth and glamor,
an illusion created by skillful artifice.
Participants walk categories like executive realness,
with the goal of being indistinguishable
from a real executive.
Nowadays every white queer says the word realness,
I guess in kind of a frivolous way.
I mean, whomst among us honestly hasn't
slipped into a dissociative fugue state,
dressed up as a clown,
kidnapped a few neighborhood children,
and told the cops,
I'm giving you John Wayne Gacy realness, hunty.
I did it, officer.
I did the cultural appropriation.
I am a colonizer.
I am part of the problem.
And I'm sorry.
Take me away, boys.
That's crazy.
That's mega coconuts.
I guess I should explain that American slang works
according to what we might call
a trickle-up model of linguistics.
All the new words are invented by the most marginalized
gay and trans people of color.
Then those words trickle up to straight Black people
and white gays,
and then finally white cishets start using them.
A lot of times the original meaning or context
gets lost along the way.
So originally, realness, as Sean Faye put it,
was not just a sassy byword for a convincing costume,
but a tragicomic disguise of the chasm
between what is being emulated and what is absent,
namely racial justice, class equality, and safety.
Realness, in that sense,
is a much more complicated and interesting concept
than the generic trans notion of passing.
Passing is just looking like
a 5'2 happy baby bouncy bio girl,
whereas in the ballroom sense,
realness has a subtext of defying injustice.
You're using artifice to create the illusion of a lifestyle
that has been unjustly kept beyond your reach.
You're not really an executive,
but you're looking like an executive,
and therefore you're showing the straight world
that I can be an executive.
If I had the opportunity, I could be one,
because I can look like one.
I think one reason there's been a surge of interest
in 80s ballroom culture, such as the FX drama Pose,
which is set during the era,
is that it dramatizes an essential truth about America.
It's really important to people in this country
to at least sometimes feel like they're living a luxe life,
even if in fact, they aren't.
Las Vegas is essentially an entire city
that exploits that need.
Vegas hotels like the Venetian, the Bellagio,
and Caesar's Palace are designed
to make you feel like a fancy bitch,
even though they're actually just high-rise traps
designed to lure you in and take your money.
And if there's one thing I can't stand,
it's traps.
But the trap works,
because part of what it is to be American
is to want to feel like a fancy bitch.
I actually love Vegas.
I was there last year for the only good YouTuber
Lindsay Ellis' bachelorette party.
I felt like a fancy bitch, and I wasn't tempted to gamble.
But when I was younger, when I was in my mid-40s,
I did once experience the first exciting stages
of a gambling habit.
I happened to go to the casino once out of curiosity,
and had some good luck playing blackjack.
I mean, I wasn't a high roller or anything,
but my first time I walked out with an extra $200.
And that was a lot of money to me.
At the time, I was working a customer service job
making $10 an hour,
so to make $200 in five minutes,
that's worth 20 hours of soul-crushing
customer service toil.
Before taxes.
So I went back and I went back,
but I never got lucky again.
And fortunately, that was enough to discourage me.
I remember one time as I was leaving the casino,
I saw this man standing outside with this look on his face
that I have never seen on a human being before or since.
Just absolute shock, despair,
this deep shame and self-disgust.
The kind of face that says,
I'm gonna have to explain to my wife
that I spent the kids' college savings
on a high-limit slot machine.
And there is nothing opulent about that,
nor the people at the slots in wheelchairs with IV drips
trying to pay off their hospital bills.
America, we are a bad country.
Donald Trump is a Vegas man,
he's pulling this grift on the entire country.
And it keeps working because the fantasy opulence
of the American dream is more enchanting to the imagination
than any abstract mathematics of economic equality.
So it may seem like Americans are all under the same spell,
but in fact, there are two very different types of magic
at work.
For the wealthy and powerful, opulence is a flex,
a demonstration of their wealth and power.
But for the marginalized and impoverished,
opulence is a simulacrum of the wealth and power
they've been denied.
The aesthetic might be similar, but in terms of function,
it's like the difference between a viper and a butterfly
serving viper realness.
Three, class.
Hey, how are you?
People don't understand how difficult it is
to be this blonde.
You know, a biological female that looks like me,
I'm afraid some transvestite psycho
is gonna sneak in through a rear window
and I'll have to dial M for murder.
I get vertigo just thinking about it.
I've always found the Marxist analysis of class
difficult to apply to the present day.
As a typical modern woman,
it's just super fucking hard for me to relate to.
And I oop, and I oop, and I oop.
That's praxis.
Like, bourgeoisie and proletariat?
Whomst?
Who is she?
Where's her summer collection?
That's super fucking great, but can I buy it?
Marx's typical examples are a factory owner
and a factory worker.
Now, I could be out of touch,
but personally, I've never met a factory worker,
or a factory owner for that matter.
They must all be on a brand trip to China,
working on the B&P summer collection.
What's supposed to distinguish the bougies from the proles
is that the bougies own the means of production
and the proles work for wages.
But what about a bartender who owns the bar she works in?
What about YouTubers?
Which side of the revolution are we on?
I'm just trying to figure out where I stand here,
because if the revolution starts on Twitter,
my head is definitely going in the basket,
and then I'll have no choice
but to do the conservative talk show circuit.
You know, like most people
whose brains are detached from their bodies.
Marie Antoinette did nothing wrong, A-R-U.
I feel like a class analysis with only two classes
must be overly simplistic.
My favorite book about class in America
is Paul Fussell's Class,
A Guide Through the American Status System,
which describes nine distinct classes.
Fussell is not as concerned
with economic relations between classes
as he is with status,
what Marxists sometimes call social and cultural capital.
Things like education, style, taste,
and attitude towards money.
Now the book was published in 1983,
so a lot of the references and details are out of date,
but there's an eerie familiarity
to a lot of the core observations.
And it's also just pretty funny,
like his quasi-scientific observation
that the higher your social class,
the smaller the balls in the sports you play,
or his description of middle-class living rooms.
Your real middle class refuses to show
any but the most bland books and magazines
on its coffee tables.
Otherwise, expressions of opinion,
awkward questions, or even ideas might result.
One of Fussell's core themes
is that it's not how much money you have
that defines your class,
so much as how you got your money.
If you had to work for your money,
then you're not really upper class.
The upper class has inherited wealth,
and as a result they're very confident
they don't feel the need to prove themselves.
Likewise, the lower classes have basically accepted
their position on the ladder.
But then there's the middle class,
who are social climbers,
and who compensate for their insecurities by,
for example, placing a pretentious collage
of university bumper stickers on the back of the family car.
This is the meaning of the Lord Melbourne quote.
The higher and lower classes,
there's some good in them,
but the middle classes are all affectation
and conceit and pretense and concealment.
Now, opulent aesthetics are typically cultivated
by people with something to prove,
whether it's marginalized ballroom performers
proving their worth to themselves
or the new rich building McMansions
to show off their wealth to others.
So there's something kind of odd about Donald Trump.
He inherited his wealth,
so he should know better than to have golden faucets.
But he doesn't.
As Fran Lebowitz said,
he's a poor person's idea of a rich person.
And that's actually his charm.
It's part of his mass appeal.
Trump behaves like a prole who won the lottery.
So there's actually something kind of relatable,
unsnobbish, and even pseudo-democratic
about the golden faucets.
People who have wealth but not class
are actually very popular in this country.
We don't like class here,
because class is exclusionary.
Whereas anyone can acquire wealth,
we tell ourselves.
So wealth feels potentially inclusive of everyone,
even though in practice, it isn't.
Now the upper-class cultural elite in this country,
the real classy people,
are mostly very unlike Trump.
Instead of being ostentatious and gaudy,
they embrace the reserved old-money values
of aristocratic wasps,
white Anglo-Saxon Protestants.
Fussell notes, for instance,
that they tend to value privacy over showing off.
They like to live at the end of long driveways
and houses away from public view.
They dress down while traveling
so as to avoid drawing attention to themselves.
These are essentially survival skills
of the experienced rich.
If you flaunt your wealth too much,
people might rob you,
or they might get envious
and come after you with pitchforks and guillotines.
Or worse, taxation.
Old money knows this,
but new money just cannot resist
the temptation to show off.
I actually wonder if the old waspy upper class
is dying out.
I feel like Donald Trump represents a victory
of money over class.
His presidency validates the idea
that you can be as vulgar as you want
so long as you have the cash to back it up.
So the old class system is dying out,
and in its place,
we have universally adopted the mindset
of the nouveau riche.
If you got it, flaunt it.
If you haven't got it,
find a way to flaunt it anyway.
Now I'm sure this is all very tragic
and disappointing to people of class and taste,
but to a tacky transsexual rhinestone connoisseur,
it's actually fantastic news.
Listen comrades,
I've been pretty down on opulence so far,
and I could continue analyzing it
in terms of inequality and class struggle,
but you already know all that.
That's why you came to cut my head off.
But hold on,
is that really all there is to aesthetics,
Marxist economic analysis,
or the SJW version
that makes everything about race and gender?
As the most notorious art critic of the 21st century once said,
but remember that it's both possible
and even necessary
to simultaneously enjoy media
while also being critical of its more problematic
or pernicious aspects.
So what about the enjoyment part?
Surely you wouldn't behead a queen
just for liking shiny thing.
Is there no room for art for art's sake?
The great philosopher and venerable German closet queen,
the fine Emanuel Hildegard Marlene Kennedy Davenport-Kunt,
said that pure aesthetic taste is disinterested,
that is, completely free of any material desire.
Of course, Ms. Thing also founded the hashtag NoFap movement,
so I don't know how seriously you want to take that.
But it's actually kind of similar
to what Plato said about aesthetic sense,
that it merely begins with a desire
for the bodies of beautiful boys,
which is really just a shadow of our true longing
for the concept of beauty itself.
God, the entire history of Western aesthetic philosophy
is just a bunch of repressed homos
trying to rationalize away their debased perversions.
What must that be like?
From the bottom of my motherfucking
and my fatherfucking heart,
that must be super fucking hard for them,
I can't even imagine.
I mean, it makes sense, really.
Straight men don't have these problems.
They got away with painting softcore for 500 years
and never had to think about it.
I guess Nietzsche's the exception.
He was straight and a philosopher,
but he was an incel and, let's be honest,
definitely a tranny chaser.
The only upstanding aesthetician in all of Western history
is the respectable English gentleman Oscar Wilde.
According to Wilde,
Those who find ugly meanings in beautiful things
are corrupt without being charming.
This is a fault.
Those who find beautiful meanings in beautiful things
are the cultivated.
For these, there is hope.
They are the elect to whom beautiful things
mean only beauty.
Spoken like a poet,
you want to be cultivated, don't you?
Don't you think I'm beautiful?
Look, I'll play it your way.
Let's swing back to the other side
of the Sarkeesian pendulum here.
As sentimental as I personally am
about art for art's sake and all of that,
but from a strictly sociological perspective,
I have to admit,
taste is pretty intimately related to power.
When you go to a museum,
you look at various objects on pedestals
under special lighting that makes them appear magical.
Now that's also what you do at Bed Bath & Beyond,
but the difference is that at the museum,
you can't buy anything.
And that turns out to be important for Kantian reasons.
In the retail context of commodity fetishism,
you correlate your aesthetic taste with material desire.
Whereas in the museum,
because you can't buy anything,
you feel like your aesthetic pleasure is pure,
that you're simply enjoying out-of-context objects.
But of course, that's an illusion.
The museum is the context,
and the context is telling you
that the things you're looking at are art.
And whoever decides what's in the museum
decides what good taste is,
what's beautiful,
what's valuable.
Think about the music video for Ape Shit by the Carters.
Beyoncé and Jay-Z pose in various places in the Louvre,
conferring upon themselves the status
and the cultural grandeur of the art.
But it's not just a flex.
It means something more than that
because of the racial disparity
between the performers and the setting.
Black people and black art
are mostly excluded from museums like the Louvre,
so seeing Jay and Bey there looking so regal,
with black dancers even overshadowing
canonical European art,
it's like a full moment.
A lot of people have a deep longing
for the sense of dignity and grandeur
conferred by classical art.
That's why trans women love that picture
someone photoshopped of the Three Graces,
but with dicks.
I'll admit that silly picture
actually had an emotional effect on me
because here in the West,
it's actually hard to think of your body type as beautiful
until you've seen it sculpted in white marble.
Oh, speaking of which,
white marble is a lie.
For most of art history history,
scholars have insisted
that the iconic ghostly whiteness
of classical statues
was the distinguishing feature of Western sculpture,
proof of the elegant taste
of the ancient Greeks and Romans.
In reality, of course, it turns out
they were painted the colors of something
a drag queen might wear to a quinceañera.
Scholars had been noticing paint remnants
on these statues for hundreds of years,
but were totally in denial about it
because the pure whiteness of these figures
was like a sacred dogma.
Margaret Talbot in The New Yorker
attributes the dogma in part to
a tendency to equate whiteness
with beauty, taste, and classical ideals,
and to see color as alien, sensual, and garish.
Garish.
In 2008, Fabio Beri, an art historian
who is now at Stanford,
complained that a boldly colored
recreation of a statue of the Emperor Augustus
at the Vatican Museum
looked like a cross-dresser trying to hail a taxi.
Hey, how are you?
And you just know that when the news first broke,
some horrified WASP classicists
turned to a colleague and said,
Oh, Kingsley, it looks,
it looks Mexican.
In fact, for the crime of writing about paint on statues,
some art historians have been harassed
by the alt-right,
who don't take kindly to anyone
questioning their white supremacist myths about antiquity.
There's some pretty insidious, uh,
identitarian prejudices here
hiding out under the cloak of taste.
Good taste for upper- and middle-class white people
generally includes a reflexive disdain
for anything a little bit too...
colorful.
It's these classes that constantly use the words
gaudy, garish, tawdry, tacky.
Joe Weldon, author of Fierce,
the History of Leopard Print,
observes that
Tacky, as a concept,
refers to the lack of cultivation
or the resistance to taste,
and more often than not,
refers to tastes that are not suitably conservative.
Furthermore, tacky is likely to be feminine,
ethnic, queer, deviant,
not manly, not practical,
not businesslike, not serious.
Aesthetic excess,
particularly of colors, patterns, and bling,
is especially offensive to conservative wasp taste.
Tacky is often where the imagination runs free,
where the heart is,
where the soul is,
and where the fun is.
Well that's good news,
because people call my aesthetic tacky all the time.
I can't imagine why.
Let me just get some more jewels on my tits.
Or camp.
People call me camp,
and sometimes I don't know if I'm being praised or insulted.
I suppose it depends on what camp means.
Camp was the theme of this year's Met Gala,
and my feed was flooded with Brooklynite intellectuals
competing to outwit each other
with the most erudite definition of what camp really is.
What I gather is there's a couple competing definitions.
The first I'll call coward camp,
this bratty, hipster notion of having bad taste on purpose.
I have no respect for this whatsoever.
This is nothing but an anxious and defensive refusal to take a risk.
You think you're safe from criticism
because your look is bad on purpose.
Fuck that.
Take a stand, you pussy bitch.
I take great offense to this
as a person whose look is bad on accident,
and Susan Sontag agrees with me.
In Notes on Camp, she distinguishes between
naive and deliberate camp.
Pure camp is always naive.
Camp which knows itself to be camp,
or camping, is usually less satisfying.
Sontag defines naive camp as failed seriousness,
a grand artistic vision that gets a little out of control
and enters into absurd territory.
Hey, how are you?
I don't know, my philosophy of style
is that people should wear what looks good to them.
I was joking earlier when I said my look is bad on accident.
I think my aesthetic is good.
This is what looks good to me,
though I'm aware other people might judge it.
I like what John Waters said about there being
good bad taste and bad bad taste.
One must remember, there is such a thing as
To understand bad taste, one must have very good taste.
I've wondered for a long time
why I'm so attracted to bad taste.
Like, I technically have the education to know better.
I know about Glenn Gould, but I prefer Liberace.
Why am I so tacky?
I think it's because I'm a transsexual,
which lowers you at least a class.
If you were born upper class and you're transsexual,
you're middle class now, bitch.
If you were born middle class and you're transsexual,
you are now lower class.
And if you were born lower class and you're transsexual,
ooh, sweaty, you'd better start a revolution.
Uh, Marsha P. Johnson, hey how are you?
Chicks with bread.
Trans women have a special relationship with glamour,
at least those of us who came of age in the 1960s.
In the most basic everyday sense,
glam is a way of styling yourself.
It's luxuriant hair, it's high drama makeup,
it's long nails, it's glitter everywhere,
it's posing like a fashion model.
But originally the word glamour comes from
the Scottish word grammary, meaning magic or enchantment.
And glamour still involves a kind of illusion,
or charm, cast on a spectator.
The connection between glamour and opulence
is explored in the 2004 essay
Viva Me Glam?
Is Transgenderism a Critique of,
Opulence-Driven Glamour Models,
by transgender writer and underground house music producer
Terry Temlitz, aka DJ Sprinkles.
Sprinkles writes,
Sprinkles alludes to an earlier form of glamour,
or grammary, that was associated with
witchcraft, paganism, and sexual deviancy.
But in our capitalist society,
glamour is a spell of opulence,
conjuring up what is often a fantasy of a lavish life.
For example, a lot of dry queens practice
this sort of illusionism by impersonating celebrities,
thereby acquiring the glamour of actresses,
pop stars, and models secondhand.
Sprinkles is bothered by the way this sort of
secondhand glamour acquires its power
from unquestioned social hierarchies.
Glamour is suspect as a critical-minded
political form because it is about
social distance, not social integration.
The promise of the pop glam diva is not
the promise of social transformation,
but individual transformation,
in which the exploited becomes the exploiter.
It is the promise of an individual's class mobility,
not social betterment or class critique.
It is, by and large, the American Dream.
Now I have to admit, this is a version
of the American Dream that hits
pretty close to home for me.
The overarching plotline of my whole
entire YouTube gender journey is that
I used to be a tragic mess.
And I'm still a tragic mess, but when I started
this channel I was a broke, gender dysphoric,
alcoholic, cross-dressing tragic mess.
I'd play a clip, but honestly those videos
are still too painful for me to even glance at.
And now, I mean look at me, look how far I've come.
I look like a moderately talented female impersonator,
hey how are you?
Those first several months of transition though,
they were rough.
I had a lot of trouble in the beginning.
I used to get laughed out of restaurants.
And I was so proud that I wouldn't let
anyone see how much that stuff hurt me.
You know, I would say,
well fuck them, I know I'm great.
And then I'd go cry my eyes out alone in my car.
And I was a YouTuber that whole time too,
which, I mean the cyberbullying alone,
I don't think you can even imagine the extent of it
if you haven't been in that situation.
You know, hundreds of strangers dissecting your voice,
picking apart your face and body,
clocking your clothes and makeup,
digging up your past, trying to deduce
the nature of your sexual pathology
from the shape of your skull.
A lot of it's hilarious to me now,
but there was a time when it caused a lot of pain.
But that pain spurred me to work on my glow-up
like it was the cure for cancer,
like my life depended on it,
which is basically how it felt.
Now, sometimes my trans critics mischaracterize me as,
as one tweeter put it,
cripplingly obsessed with passing.
And passing in day-to-day life was always a goal for me,
but glam, to me, is not about passing.
I think I actually pass better in no makeup
than I do in eyeshadow out to here.
You know, a cis woman can wear eyeshadow out to here,
and people think she's just really into makeup
or Instagram or cosplay or something,
but when I do it, I think it looks like drag,
which serves to call more attention to my situation.
But on YouTube, I mean,
clearly I don't try to pass as a normal woman.
Everyone here knows I'm trans anyway,
so what's the point?
I would describe this presentation
as female impersonator,
and that's basically what I am,
a female female impersonator.
And I present this way because it's fun,
I find it artistically fulfilling,
and let's be honest, there's part of me
that always wanted to be that kind of
larger-than-life superwoman.
But I'm also creating special effects for the camera.
As Sprinkles says,
Now, a lot of leftist trans people
have grown disillusioned
with the individual class mobility
represented by glamour,
as well as by transition glow-up narratives.
And I think that disillusionment
and a growing revolutionary sentiment
are at the heart of this intense
anger and resentment
that trans people have for trans women.
And I think that's what I'm trying to do
with this video,
and I'm trying to make it
are at the heart of this intense anger
and resentment I've noticed
a lot of trans women have for drag queens,
for glamorous trans Instagram models,
and let's be honest,
for me.
Here's Sprinkles one more time.
As long as an MTF's public acceptance
is gauged by her ability to emulate
glamorous body and style requirements
that elude most, quote,
real women, then I'll have to ask you
to pardon this transgendered writer
for not feeling represented
by RuPaul any more
than my mother feels represented
by Marilyn Monroe or Princess Di.
A lot of trans women
are basically fed up with having to
serve the world of fantasy all the time.
They want to be seen for who they are
without doing any of that shit.
They're fed up with glamour.
They're fed up with realness.
They're fed up with RuPaul.
And a lot of them are pretty fed up with me.
And I oop, and I oop, and I oop.
Six. Envy.
The Marxist art critic John Berger
called glamour the happiness
of being envied.
Being envied is a solitary form of reassurance.
It depends precisely
upon not sharing your experiences
with those who envy you.
But being envied is a form of happiness
only in the imagination.
The actual experience of being envied sucks.
This is the risk of opulence.
It invites not just
enchanted admiration, but also
envy. And where envy goes,
the guillotine follows.
Or at least, vindictive taxation.
This is why the experienced
rich know to tone down the opulence,
build a nice high wall around their properties,
and make a lot of high-profile
charitable donations.
We can call this kind of strategizing
the public relations of success.
It certainly helps to have a rags-to-riches story,
especially if you can make other people
feel included in some way in your success.
That's part of the appeal
of hip-hop opulence, is that it seems
to elevate not just a single performer,
but an entire underclass.
Conversely, being
perceived as exclusionary, elitist,
or snobbish is gonna cost
you big in terms of envy management.
YouTube music critic Todd
in the Shadows did a review of Ariana
Grande's song Seven Rings, in which
he basically drags Ariana, who
apparently is white, for appropriating
a bunch of hip-hop rags-to-riches signifiers
without any of the subtext of
starting from the bottom. She's not
showcasing a triumph over adversity,
she's just a white girl who
likes stuff. We started
from the bottom, now the whole team
is fucking here. So in Todd's
words, the song is a grotesque, bullying,
VIP-only privilege flex
of a mean girl shoving her wealth
in your face. I actually like that
song, but I'm into that sort
of thing. Bully me, mommy.
Aww! Fellow students,
as a case study in the public relations
of success and envy management,
let us compare and contrast
two successful YouTubers,
Jeffree Star and Gigi Gorgeous.
There's enough similarities between them
for the differences to be interesting.
They're both LGB and or T, they're both
white, they're both blonde sometimes,
they're both feminine, they're both rich,
and they both flaunt their opulent
lifestyles. But nonetheless,
people basically seem to like
Jeffree Star, whereas
Gigi, well,
I don't want to say people don't like her,
but they don't relate to her.
The best example of this is her
2017 video, I Wear Walmart
for a Week, with its gasp-inducing
like-to-dislike ratio.
Let's analyze what went wrong here.
So, for today's video, I thought
we would take it to a place I've
never been, Walmart. So that's a bad
start, Gorge. Most Americans
have been to Walmart. Never having
been marks your upbringing as upper-middle
class, at least.
Treating going to Walmart as some kind of
challenge kind of comes across as you
and your rich friends being like,
what if we pretend to be poor for a day?
I wonder if we're gonna see any people at Walmart,
you know that website? Babies crying,
the trauma. Gigi,
no! You need to turn the shade down,
like, 20 notches, Gorge.
I keep taking my shin on this cart,
I'm literally gonna have bruises.
Can someone remake these carts,
please? It's dangerous.
They're gonna cut your head off, Gorge.
What should we get next?
Maybe like a gown for a red carpet?
Do they sell gowns here?
This, to me, is peak Gigi,
strolling down the aisles of Walmart
with a two-liter bottle of Mountain Dew
that she's plucked from the shelves,
saying, I need something for a red
carpet. Do they have gowns here?
This, to me,
is an iconic fashion moment.
This is naive camp. This is everything.
The idea that she has privileges that
other people don't has never
once crossed her mind, and that is a
very special, precious
thing that I want to cherish.
Personally, I have no choice but to stan.
The YouTube comments section, however,
is not as amused as I am,
nor as forgiving.
This is the second time I've done a close reading of a
Gigi video. It's getting kinda weird.
Also, why hasn't she answered my letters?
Step on my throat, mommy.
Now let's look at Jeffree Star. Jeffree does
similar kinds of videos to Gigi.
He's even done his own video wearing Walmart
today, which people loved.
Now my first impulse when explaining the differences
in public perception is to scream
SEXISM. And there's maybe a little
of that going on. I do think a rich
woman is more irritating to people than
a rich man, but there's clearly more than that
going on here. Jeffree's fans are,
I assume mostly women, and
not rich women, regular women.
The women who work at the dollar store love him.
I'm like your biggest fan.
Ordinary people actually enjoy watching
Jeffree flaunt his millions of dollars of
designer bags and clothes because they either
live vicariously through him or they see
him as aspirational. It's the same
reason why poor people have always enjoyed
watching reality TV shows about
the extremely wealthy. The centerpiece
of Jeffree Star's brand is that he's
self-made. He represents himself
as having started from the bottom.
You know, he talks about his white trash upbringing
and just generally seems
like he hasn't let his wealth go to his head.
A good example of this is his private
jet Burger King mukbang.
Now at first you might think that a private jet
is not very relatable, but the Burger King
aspect brings it back down to earth.
Jeffree seems like he's
been to Burger King before.
He's able to order fluently, he's even
kind of charming to the cashier.
He doesn't scoff or pinch his nose
at anything. Also, the Gucci
barrette. Whereas
Gigi, I mean don't get me wrong,
I do love Gigi, but
I don't know if sis would make it
out of Burger King alive.
You know, she'd commit some terrible upper-class
solacism like, I don't know,
not understanding the concept
of a value meal. I'm sure Gigi would make
an entertaining video, just
not a relatable video.
You know, she'd somehow contract syphilis
from the toilet seat and do a story time about that.
That's really when Gigi's at her best.
She kind of comes back down to earth whenever she's
serving real transsexual housewives
at Beverly Hills meets David Cronenberg.
So I'm like, I see
this white little chiclet in my hand.
I'm feeling with my tongue and I'm like,
OH MY GOD.
Economic inequality in this country has always been enabled
by the fact that people
basically like the rich.
Yeah, we judge people who live in McMansions
and we get irritated by elitist, out-of-touch
behavior. But
ultimately, we have no choice
but to stand. And the people we stand
the hardest are people like Jeffree Star,
who, in a way, seems like
a poor person who just
so happens to be very rich.
And if inequality increases enough,
I suspect the standing will stop.
Because it's fun to watch Jeffree Star spend
$69,000 in one trip to the Louis Vuitton store
if what you're doing is
fantasizing about what you would buy
with that much money. But if you're thinking about
how $69,000 could pay off your
life-ruining medical debt, or about
how you'd be able to afford cancer treatments
for your dying wife, this kind of thing
will start getting under your skin.
And eventually, people
will start building guillotines again.
In fact, the only way I can imagine
a revolution happening in this country
is if rich people start behaving
as badly as possible.
So this isn't your dream job?
No. And this is free, right?
Whatever you want.
Seven. Ruin.
Good evening,
Gorge. Ever notice how
most vampires are like
counts or queens or
at least rich? I guess
some are edgy biker teens, but
I don't associate with that trash.
Gothic horror really got started
as a genre with 18th and 19th
century novels, which were usually
set in an old, decaying castle
or mansion. By the late 19th century,
the aristocracy had lost a lot
of its relevance as a class,
so aristocrat vampires like Count Dracula
represented a dying
world order, and also
maybe the metaphorical blood-sucking
of commoners by the landed gentry.
Vampires were also usually seducers,
and the aristocrat seducer
trope had actually played an important
role in turning public opinion
against the nobility. So the
gothic aesthetic is an aesthetic of
dead and decaying opulence.
And that aesthetic has evolved over time,
from the ruins of a medieval castle
to the iconic haunted house,
which in American horror is
usually a decaying Victorian
mansion. It's a trope with an
interesting backstory. During the
golden age, industrialization produced
a new wealthy class of people
who built what were essentially 19th
century McMansions. When the Great
Depression hit, a lot of these Victorian
mansions were abandoned and began
to decay, which gave them morbid
associations that made them perfect
for stories about hauntings
and psychos
and weirdos. So ruined
opulence becomes
gothic, which kind of makes you think.
We live in an age of opulence
and inequality and growing
irritation with abusive men in power,
the middle class is shrinking,
social unrest is on the rise,
it seems like a new economic
order could be on the horizon.
When the opulence of our age decays,
will there be a new gothic
aesthetic of ruined shopping
malls? Well, there
kind of already is.
The urban explorer Dan Bell is a
YouTuber known for his Dead Mall series,
in which he explores the ruins of
abandoned shopping malls. For example,
the now demolished Owings Mills
Mall just north of Baltimore.
The mall opened in 1986
as the Owings Mills Fashion Mall.
Champagne, gold dust, and
pink feathers heralded in
a new era for Owings Mills.
Today's opening of the Owings Mills
Fashion Mall does not only mean a new
high fashion place to shop, it also
means lots of new developments and jobs
for Baltimore County. It had a
Macy's, a Lord & Taylor, a Saks Fifth
Avenue. It was a big, high-end
mall. But in 1992,
a woman who worked as a cleaner
at Saks was murdered during
an armed robbery on the trail between the mall
and the Baltimore metro station.
After the murder, the mall got a reputation
for being unsafe, and
slowly the stores closed down.
Dan recorded two videos at Owings
Mills in 2015, when only
five of the original 155
stores remained.
He takes us through the strangely clean
and empty halls, the
drained fountains, the
gutted food court.
Watching these videos seems to provoke
an emotional response in a lot of
people. Some say they feel
nostalgic or sad, some
express rage at the waste and futility,
some find it creepy or
even horrifying, and some
have a dark sense of humor about the absurdity
of it all. One commenter says,
I think it is still hitting people with
slow-motion shock that the
20th century is really over.
In the 80s, this looked
like the start of a big new world
of wealth for everyone.
In fact, it was the last gasp
of 20th century general
prosperity.
I agree with all these comments,
and I feel every one of these
emotions. I think there is
a new aesthetic sensibility
emerging here, a gothic
aesthetic for the 21st century,
this decaying opulence
that is the carcass of
20th century consumerism.
Oh, it gives me a chill!
My nape hair stands on end
and a tingle goes down my
spine.
The Owings Mills
Mall was totally demolished in
late 2016, and Dan's
final video about it, we see clips
from his earlier Owings Mills videos
intercut with absolutely
post-apocalyptic footage of the
half-demolished ruin.
It's not like the feeling of
exploring a ruined temple or abbey
where you somehow perceive
the spiritual significance of the
original building. In a dead mall,
you do sense the ghosts of
the shoppers and the workers,
their aspirations and material
longings, but
what does the crumbling wreckage of a
J.C. Penney really mean?
That is a question
that will haunt me to the grave.
Alright comrades,
I've said my piece.
I'll come quietly. There's no reason
to tie me down. I mean,
unless you're into that. In which case,
by all means. No,
I won't resist.
I accept my fate.
🎵
Fuck you, Romano.
I'm glad your father died.
Let's just get that out there before I just say it.
I must be honest, definitely a Chinese chaser.
Gosh, I sure do think I'm funny.
But he was an incel.
And definitely a Chinese chaser.
Look at me.
I'm ashamed.
I'm ashamed of what I've written.
Huh?
Kant, yeah.
But I'm saying his name wrong because I'm...
an asshole.
I hope you're enjoying this theory and watching me rub snot into my hands as I
shriek naked in a tub full of jewels.
How much leg do we want to get in here?
A lot, I assume.
I'm just getting oil all over my fur.
Great.
It's not real fur, whatever.
Let me clarify that for the vegans in the comments section.
Ugh.
Moral people.
There's one that I can't stand.
People who have some sense of decency.
Okay.
Is a hair light really a good idea?
Why don't we illuminate my frizziness?
Who invented that?
An asshole.
What about a bartender who owns the bar he works in?
Uh, I guess it was a shitty to be feminist.
Ugh, Christ.
The demands of these people.
These bucky teeth, man.
It's like...
It's like being catty.
Catty, catty.
That is a question that will haunt me to the grave.
So catty and stupid.
Ugh, okay.