Oh, no!
♪
How dare you!
How dare you alter your unreleased game that's still in open beta, Blizzard!
Don't you know you're censoring...your...self?
Alongside this incredibly convincing argument, of course,
is the far more hilarious complaint that male characters are being treated exactly the same way and sexualized just as much.
But what about muscular or topless male characters?
They're sexualized, too!
Why does nobody complain about that, and they only whine when it's female characters?
S-Jews are ruining games!
Save Tracer's butt!
Sign the petition!
How many times have you heard this one?
The claim that a muscular man is automatically sexualized.
Is it a good argument against censoring female characters?
Have you even...looked at video games?
How is this even comparable to this?
Is this supposed to be sexually appealing because he's almost naked?
I guess this man must be the most sexually attractive because he has the biggest muscles,
and muscles are always sexy, right?
It's almost as if sexualization is more than just nudity.
Maybe for something to be sexy, there has to be deliberate posing, framing, and attitude instead of plain nudity.
There's something that pushes it beyond that and makes it erotic.
And maybe part of the issue is straight men really have no idea what women and gay men find attractive in men.
It's pretty obvious when this is considered more sexual and attractive than what people actually attracted to men think is sexy.
Oh, Fabio.
Oh, ex-Benedict Cucumber Patch.
Oh, Brad Pitt.
But no, it's Feminazi Diss-Jews Conspiracy, I tell you!
They're taking all our butts away!
Hahahaha!
Special thanks to Aaron Salisbury, Alexander Corbett, Alicia Parker-Martel, Amanda Beverley, Axel Blaze, Bob, Kieran, and Jason Walter.