🎵
So why is it that humans just can't stop killing each other?
Well, I don't know.
What do I look like to you, some kind of philosopher?
🎵
So look, Thrasymachus, this is a question for God and the prophets,
not for preening transsexuals who can't get out of bed without a Bloody Mary.
🎵
However, if I were to make a modest contribution to the subject,
I would humbly offer up the hypothesis that humans are horrible to each other because,
well, violence is fun.
🎵
And when I say that, I of course mean that it's fun to be violent.
It's not fun when other people are violent to you.
I mean, unless that's what you're into.
🎵
That is what I'm into.
Did I say you could speak?
No, mistress.
Then shut up!
🎵
Mmm, that's good.
Chocolaty.
Stanley Kubrick's A Clockwork Orange is very uncomfortable to watch,
and not just because it depicts horrible acts of violence.
Most of the movies I like depict horrible acts of violence.
I mean, if you're going to watch a non-violent movie,
you may as well read a fucking book.
What's disquieting about A Clockwork Orange is that it encourages us to
viddy the old ultra-violence largely from the perspective of the sadistic protagonist,
a jaunty rapist who likes to sing and dance as he tortures and humiliates his victims.
What's creepy about Alex is the film encourages us to identify with him,
and he kind of draws us in.
I mean, he listens to Beethoven,
and I personally am attracted to every man who has ever liked German composers.
Also, he tries the wine.
Try the wine!
Shh!
So we watch Alex kick and spin and smash things and beat the shit out of homeless people
and bash old ladies in the face with giant sculptures of dicks,
and all of this to triumphant classical music and show tunes.
It's clear that for Alex, this is all a lot of fun.
So the question I want to ask is, how unusual are people like this in real life?
How normal is it to enjoy violence?
I mean, extremely violent behavior is uncommon,
but part of that might be that most of us live in political circumstances
where behaving like a violent maniac is highly frowned upon.
And there's also that tedious old thing called having some semblance of a moral conscience,
and I think that's part of the reason why a lot of people don't really enjoy
watching A Clockwork Orange.
It's not that they don't enjoy violence,
it's that in order for them to enjoy violence,
they need some kind of reassurance that the violence is okay,
and that enjoying it is morally and socially allowed.
I guess it's kind of like sex.
I'm not going to want to have sex in a fluorescent-lit bathroom stall.
At least, not since I started taking this shit.
I need candlelight to get me in the mood, you know.
A little goddamn ambiance.
And you could say that the moral conscience
is the fluorescent-lit bathroom stall of the human mind.
You can't properly enjoy violence
with all that internal nagging going on in the background.
But in that case,
what is the romantic candlelight of the sadistic psyche?
What do we need to get to a place where we can enjoy violence?
Well, think about the TV show Law & Order SVU,
which has just as much sex and violence as A Clockwork Orange,
but which is much more popular.
SVU is a show where hero cops with no regard for due process
brutally interrogate suspected sex offenders
and smash them in the face with wooden drawers.
You like that, don't you?
I love it so much.
You all do.
I think a lot of the appeal of SVU
is that it gives upstanding American citizens
a way to sate their curiosity about heinous sex crimes
while promising the moral purification
of justified police violence.
Oh, so that promise is the candlelit ambiance
of the moral psyche.
When we believe that violence is morally justified,
when we think the guy being thrown around the interrogation room
fucking deserved it,
we become capable of enjoying it aesthetically.
Exactly.
And I think this kind of moral lampshading
partly explains the popularity of rape-revenge plotlines
you see in movies like Kill Bill, The Crow,
and Curious George Kills the Rapist.
For viewers with too many moral hangups
to get off on totally senseless violence,
a rape-revenge plotline is a cheap way
to establish the emotional precedent
required for gratifying bloody payoff.
But I wonder if there may not be
as much of a psychological difference
between the good person's enjoyment of justified violence
and the evil sadist's enjoyment of random violence
as we might like to think.
Yes, the good person has a moral conscience
as a kind of inhibitive influence,
but once you get past that,
there's a kind of amoral kinetic rapture
in swinging, thrashing, stabbing, shooting,
blasting, and burning,
an aesthetics of violence and destruction.
Now I for one hardly ever enjoy real-world violence
because I empathize with the victim
and my conscience vetoes any enjoyment of it.
I mean, unless I get real frustrated.
Shut up.
Please, just shut up.
I love this noise.
I can't think straight.
You're so filthy.
It's time to drink your milk.
Just...
But you know, when I'm playing video games,
but you know, when I'm playing video games
and there are no moral or practical consequences
to any of my actions,
I behave like an absolute goddamn psychopath.
I guess that a simulation of a thing being fun
doesn't mean that the thing itself is fun.
I mean, The Sims is a simulation of life,
and that's fun,
but life itself is terrible.
To be clear, that was a joke, not a cry for help.
I'm actually fine.
I have tons of friends.
I'm fine.
I'm really, I'm fine.
I'm happy, okay?
Here's what I want to know.
Unless violence is fun on some basic level,
why are simulations of it so fun
that the gameplay of most video games
is based entirely around it?
Some critics have suggested
that this is simply toxic masculinity at work,
and that it's a patriarchal moral defect
that our media is so violent.
And yeah, it's true that men
are mostly responsible for this, granted.
But honestly, I feel a little bit infantilized
by the moral critique,
since I like violent media,
and I feel like I can tell the difference
between real and fictional violence.
Although sometimes the distinction
between real and simulated violence
can get blurry.
Joshua Oppenheimer's disturbing documentary
The Act of Killing
chronicles the contemporary lives
of the Indonesian gangsters
who massacred millions of alleged communists
from 1965 to 66.
One of the killers, Anwar Kongo,
explains on a local television program
that his torture and murder methods
were inspired by sadistic American movies.
The documentary takes a surreal turn
as the original perpetrator
is set to work producing cinematic reenactments
of their youthful war crimes,
stylizing the events after westerns,
mafia films, and other Hollywood genres.
It's a particularly uncomfortable case
of life imitating art.
And on that topic,
Stanley Kubrick had a clockwork orange
withdrawn from British distribution in 1973
after the film was alleged to have influenced
a handful of real life assaults.
Now I'm not saying that violent movies
make people violent,
and we know that most consumers of violent media
never commit acts of violence themselves.
I mean, I watch violent movies all the time
and I've never killed anyone who didn't deserve it.
So now woke ContraPoints thinks child abuse is funny.
I personally drowned several of my babies
and it was very traumatic for me.
Why did I become an SJW again?
Hey, what I want to know is
what's the difference between fans of violent movies
who are peaceful and those who are sadistic killers?
Well, who better to ask than an Indonesian gangster
with a thousand dead communists under his belt?
So in other words,
as long as you can justify it to yourself
with some kind of flimsy excuse,
you can kill without remorse.
And I imagine it also helps
when the US-backed government of your country
endorses the killing
and you never have to face any consequences for it.
What's interesting to me
is that the sadistic enjoyment of violence
is psychologically identical,
whether or not your justification rationally holds up
or makes any sense.
In other words,
the psychology of a righteous sadist
may not differ from that of an evil sadist,
except that the former happens to have better reasons
backing him up,
or lives in a better political situation.
But hold on,
is there even such a thing as a righteous sadist?
I think it's okay to enjoy violent movies,
but is it ever not bad to enjoy real violence?
What would be helpful here is an example,
some act of violence that my audience thinks is righteous,
and that a lot of them probably even enjoy.
Unfortunately,
my audience is morally superior,
and none of them would ever enjoy
ContraPoints has completely leapt out
and can't stop wringing her hands
over a poor little Nazi getting hit in the face.
Alright, alright,
let's grant that punching a Nazi is morally acceptable.
Let's say it's morally required, even.
Well, why don't we try to bring everyone on board?
Suppose there's a Nazi TERF
and he's about to punch a baby,
and punching the TERF Nazi
is the only way to stop him from punching the baby.
Socrates,
is it just to punch the baby puncher?
ContraPoints sponsors would like to apologize
to the baby community for this video's
ongoing trivialization of infanticide.
They'd also like you to know
that some of Natalie's best friends are babies,
and they all think babies should just learn to take a joke.
Why are we even still talking about this
over-discussed Nazi-punching bullshit?
I guess part of it is that it's the only recent example
of actual far-left violence in America
that anyone seems to be able to dig up.
Not for long, bourgeois dogs!
Cat girls of the world, unite!
Tabby, could you bring it down
just 27 notches or so?
Why don't you take a second to relax?
Just chill out a little bit.
Here, have some spiked milk.
["Russian Queen"]
That is having a very interesting effect on her.
I guess my continued uneasiness
with leftist punching discourse,
whether it's Nazis or TERFs or whatever,
is twofold.
First there's the optics problem.
We want to convince people that,
for instance,
trans women are not creepy men
who want to assault cis women.
And I can't help but wonder,
is the slogan,
kill all TERFs,
really the most effective way to convey that message?
And I realize the costume I'm wearing
is not the best for making this point either,
but you know, I just didn't plan well.
The other worry has to do with when violence
stops being strategic and starts being fun,
as in our collective enjoyment
of the Richard Spencer punch.
Because then it's not just that we're saying
sometimes preemptive violence is necessary
to prevent worse crimes,
it's that we're actively fucking enjoying it.
And anytime real violence becomes fun,
that's a little alarming,
because even if your actions are genuinely justified,
you don't want to get in the habit
of enjoying real violence,
because the violence will continue to be fun
whether or not your justifications are any good.
Though I agree there's something sort of
inherently liberal about this anti-sadism hangup.
For most of history it was just accepted
that war involves a certain amount of rape and pillage,
and that executions were entertaining public spectacles.
As a boring French postmodernist
called Michael Foucault pointed out,
in the 18th and 19th centuries
there was a so-called humanitarian revolution
that was suddenly ashamed of overt sadism
with respect to criminal justice
and treatment of the mentally ill,
replacing brutal executions
with intricate techniques of discipline.
And a boring French communist called Alain Badiou
argued that this contemporary ethics
based on pity and tolerance
is actually just fucking neoliberal bullshit
that encourages first world people
to stage third world humanitarian interventions
that look a lot like invasions for some reason,
as well as opposing genuine liberation movements
on the grounds that such movements
amount to violent ideology,
the bourgeois liberals claim.
So I guess in a sense my weird hangup about violence
benefits the people in power,
since you have to break a few eggs
to make a communist utopia,
and sometimes to make political progress
you have to tar and feather some folks
and cut their heads off just a little bit
or punch them in the fucking face.
Now I realize all the non-leftists watching this
are absolutely horrified right now,
and they're thinking,
what's to stop your violent revolution
from becoming just as bloodthirsty and unjust
as those Indonesian gangsters killing communists?
To which I respond,
well that's an easy one,
it's because my side are the good people
and your side are the bad people,
I'm so sorry.
Seriously though, that is a pretty good question.
Why don't I change the subject
to avoid how much of a problem it is
for the argument I'm making?
Isn't all politics kind of violent?
What about capitalism?
Politics is the practice of organizing groups
of human beings,
and it's the relations of power
that maintain or disrupt that organization.
So there's always violence
or the threat of violence in there somewhere.
In our own society,
police will use violence against us
if we disobey the law or are black.
And even when white people do obey the law,
there's always the implicit threat of police violence,
including the potential arrest and incarceration
of pretty much every citizen
who doesn't have enough money to-
Let's talk about western values.
According to the great tradition
of European political thought,
sovereign power is justified by the social contract.
In other words, we all consent to be governed
because it's in our own interest.
Except it's really hypothetical consent
more than anything,
because no one actually asks you,
and you can't say no.
Wait a minute.
Shh!
I guess if you live in a liberal capitalist society,
it's pretty easy to see how fascism
and revolutionary movements are inherently violent,
and how those political situations
generate conditions where violent sadism can flourish.
What's harder to see is how the same tendency
spills out at the seams
of our own supposedly humane society.
We think of the police as peacekeepers, not killers,
yet it's not unheard of that-
Oh.
Oh no.
Oh god.
Likewise, we think of our wars as liberation projects
or humanitarian interventions,
but when you put real human beings in combat situations,
the nature of war has a way of just-
Oh.
Oh god.
No.
Fuck.
We tend to pass particularly harsh moral judgment on sadism,
but sadistic violence isn't even necessarily
the worst thing that can happen to people.
There's also the quieter structural injustices
that lead to millions of people starving,
or workers throwing themselves out of windows
at the iPhone factory,
or the low-key normalization of sexual assault
in supposedly civilized countries,
none of which requires so much as a single cackling maniac.
So in order to think about this intelligently,
we need to weigh the risk that revolutionary violence
will spin out of control and lead to sadistic mayhem
against the risk that our own complacency
with the injustices of the status quo
will make us quiet enablers of more subtle
but equally unjust forms of violence.
And I don't feel confident enough to say
which one I think is the bigger risk,
but I do know I don't trust the politics of anyone
who doesn't acknowledge the problems with both options.
So, in conclusion,
is violence good?
Or is it bad?
I guess we'll never know.
You know, with any true philosophical question,
there always comes a point when you realize
that all the rationalizations you tell yourself
for all the things you believe and do
just don't really make any sense.
And that's when it's time to stop thinking about it, you know?
Just do the fucking laundry.
Drink some wine.
I don't know.
Do whatever.
Look, what do you want from me?