The universe is incredibly big and seems full of potential for life, with billions of habitable
planets. If an advanced civilization had the technology to travel between the stars,
at just 0.1% of the speed of light, it could colonize our galaxy in roughly 100 million years.
Which is not that long given the billions of years the Milky Way has existed, so in principle,
any space-faring civilization should be able to spread rapidly over huge sectors of the galaxy.
And yet, we see nothing, hear nothing. The universe seems empty, devoid of others.
This is the Fermi Paradox, which we have discussed in more detail in other videos.
Confronted with the seemingly empty universe, humanity faces a dilemma. We desperately want
to know if we are alone in the Milky Way. We want to call out and reveal ourselves to anyone
watching, but that could be the last thing we ever do. Because maybe the universe is not empty.
Maybe it's full of civilizations, but they are hiding from each other. Maybe the civilizations
that attracted attention in the past were wiped away by invisible arrows. This is the
Dark Forest Solution to the Fermi Paradox.
The Way of Life
The hunter awakes in his hiding place and carefully listens for suspicious
noises from the thick undergrowth before he gets up. Another night has passed without
incident. The forest is dark and full of fog. He considers calling out to others to end his
loneliness, but stops himself at the last moment. What if they are like him?
All living things seek to survive, secure resources, and multiply. Their greatest
obstacle are other living things that share the same objective. Competition between species
favored the survival of beings with advantageous traits. Our ancestors were inventive, competitive,
expansionist, and greedy for resources, which led them to winning the competition for our planet.
Today, most other animals are so utterly at our mercy that we wipe out about a dozen species a
day, just as an unintentional byproduct of how we like to run things. But humans are more than
individuals. From us, cultures emerge that also compete with each other. Competitive and
expansionary cultures spread faster and further, and merge with, subdue, or destroy others. If we
look at our history, it becomes clear we are dangerous. Not just to others, but also to
ourselves. Our human nature has driven us to take over every corner of our planet, and soon we will
look to the stars, both to expand our domain and ensure access to ever more resources. And then we
might stumble upon others trying to do the same thing. It's likely that the competition of life
also takes place on faraway planets, so it's logical to assume that an alien civilization
that came to dominate their planet would be in some regards similar to us. But if they're similar
to us, they too may be dangerous. The implication. As the hunter sneaks through the dark forest
all alone, he knows that there might be others like him. He can't know their intentions, if they
are aggressive or not. The hunter knows he would kill to ensure his own survival, so he has to
assume that they would too. And it might be that if he stumbles upon another hunter, the one that
shoots first survives. None of this means that conflict is unavoidable. So far, the progress
of the modern world seems to have made us more peaceful, not more violent. Maybe this is true
for other civilizations too, that eventually progress means less conflict, not more.
Different alien civilizations also should vary from the mild and peaceful, to the malevolent
and militaristic. The existential problem we're facing is that when we meet others between the
stars, we have no way of telling who is peaceful or aggressive, and what their true intentions are.
Similarly, they might not understand or trust our intentions, even if we tell them that we
are peaceful. On top of that, if we did discover another civilization and they discovered us,
the light years between us would mean years of communication delay.
Both sides would be in a state of uncertainty, wondering if the wisest move is to just attack,
because there's another serious issue, technological explosions, and the first
strike advantage. We don't know where the limits of technology are, but we do know how much
technological progress matters in war. A few hundred or thousand years can turn conflict
with uncertain results into a one-sided massacre. Caesar's legions would stand no chance against
Napoleon's army with their cannons and muskets, which would be eradicated by artillery from the
First World War, which would not stand a chance against today's drones and guided missiles.
So the power level of different civilizations may vary massively, and even if not, between the
time it takes us to detect another civilization and us saying, hi, we might already be hopelessly
behind on the tech tree. Which is bad enough, but the nature of interstellar conflict makes this
worse. If your opponent is light years away, sending an invasion fleet takes so long that
by the time it arrives, it might be hopelessly obsolete. So war between civilizations might be
just about eliminating the other to remove an existential threat to yourself, someone else who
might be so scared of you that they attack the first chance they get. In this environment,
the only way to guarantee a win is to strike with such force and speed that the target has no chance
of survival or time to counterattack or escape to seek revenge later. The stakes are the highest
possible with no room for error. If we assume that the majority of civilizations live on planets,
that leaves them pretty vulnerable. All you need to do is throw something massive at a planet to
make it uninhabitable. So the ultimate interplanetary annihilation weapon is probably
something like a relativistic kill vehicle, a missile shot at a planet at a significant fraction
of the speed of light. For example, a missile the size of a person going 95% the speed of light
has as much energy as all nuclear bombs on Earth. If you shot a few dozen of the civilization you
wanted to wipe out, success would be fairly certain even a single hit would suffice.
This is not that absurd of an idea. A civilization only slightly above us on the Kardashev scale
would have enough energy to send multiple strikes against every planet it suspects of harboring life.
What makes these weapons so sinister is how much they favor a first strike,
since they would be so fast that it might be impossible to protect yourself effectively
against them once they're launched. Conflict between civilizations may not be lengthy affairs,
but rapid winner-takes-all situations, where the first one to shoot wins.
This makes any civilization an existential threat to any other. And if every civilization is an
existential threat to every other, there may be only two kinds of civilizations out there.
Quiet ones and dead ones. So what should we do? Should we worry?
It's unlikely that anybody has noticed humanity yet. The radio signals we've transmitted in the
last 100 years traveled a relatively tiny distance and have long decayed into unreadable
noise. At our technological stage, if we don't actively try to get noticed, and if nobody
specifically looks at our pretty unremarkable solar system, we'll stay hidden. But one day
we will venture into space in a serious way and need to consider these kinds of questions again.
We don't know if there are others or if we are going through the forest alone.
But we have no way of knowing for sure. For the time being, it seems the best we can do
is to carefully listen. And even if we see others step into a clearing and make themselves known,
we should not reply right away, but carefully watch them from the undergrowth.
Perhaps we are also thinking about this all wrong by allowing our primitive brain that evolved in
the context of the gruesome competition of life to conjure fears of predatory aliens all around us.
Maybe the fact that we are looking at the universe like this is a sign that we are not grown up yet
as a species. There could be a friendly, welcoming community of alien civilizations waiting to hear
from us when we are ready. As for now, the good news is there is actually little we need to do.
We just need to be thoughtful about the signals we send out into the galaxy,
we need to watch the sky and learn more about our galaxy, our forest. Because whatever the
nature of our forest is, full of dangers or friends, or nobody at all, only careful
observation can tell. So, let's do that. At last, the hunter reaches a clearing and
finds a comfortable position. Slowly, the sun melts the fog away. Lost in thought,
he admires the vegetation until suddenly he is eye to eye with another hunter,
frozen in terror just like himself. His mind is racing, considering all the different options.
The hunter takes a deep breath and makes a decision. Maybe the only way out of the dark
forest is to step into the clearing, together.
And with this hopeful picture, we say goodbye to the year 12,021 of the human era.
It was a wild year to say the least, still much more fun than 12,020.
Kurzgesagt had its most successful month ever and published a book. We tried a lot of new techniques
and already got into Blender and Cinema 4D, hiding more and more 3D in our videos.
We have so many ideas for next year and big and ambitious plans that we can't
wait to share with you. And all of this was and is possible because of your direct support.
Thank you so much. Kurzgesagt only works because of you.
So, in tune with the end of the year, we've designed a few products that will help you
to visualize your place in the universe. Our very shiny The Night Sky poster shows
you the little piece of space we can see from Earth with our own eyes, or travel further out
with our stellar Zoom collection that depicts our home in space from an increasing distance,
or dream with our space-themed notebooks, scenic posters, and pens. We design and produce every
single product with great care. Getting something from our shop is the best way to support
Kurzgesagt. We hope you have a wonderful end of the year and that 12,022 is more fun and
less exciting than the last two years. Thank you for watching.