Hello boys! I get a lot of people on YouTube calling me degenerate, but I'm still not
sure what that means. I try to be open to criticism, so I've decided that what I need
is a glorious knight of wisdom to set me straight, and I think I've found just the man. Some
call him the valiant champion of Mother Europe, the ever-chosen of the gods, the radiant paladin
of the Fourth Reich. But to this priestess of blasphemies, he'll always be the Golden
One.
Oh my god. Look at his butt. Oh my god. Daddy, can I have some meat? Looks like meat's back
on the menu, boys! Oh daddy. You know Lars, things have really changed since the last
time we talked. I'm a fair maiden now, to a certain extent, and I've been chaste since
I started my transition, so in a sense, I'm a virgin. And I don't know about the rest
of these decadent sluts, but I for one care about a little thing called purity. So, now
that my decade of gender dysphoric alcohol-drenched debasement seems to be coming to a close,
I think I'm really ready to begin the training, master. But first, let us fend off degeneracy
by purifying ourselves in a bath of Swedish lake water and pure absinthe. It's time.
Down, down, I always wanna die on my own. I never really cared until I met you.
What? Is this the bad kind of cultural appropriation? It is, isn't it? Well, mmm, they're shiny
and I want them. It's not my fault black people have good ideas. What am I supposed to do?
Not steal them? I'll pop it out. Alright, thou resplendent champion of the north, hit
me with your finest wisdom. I'm gonna go train some shoulders and admire myself in the mirror.
There's always a nice thing to do. Well, at least we agree on something.
Aha! Autogynephilic narcissistic spose! Abigail, isn't not invading women's bathrooms
like your whole thing? Misogynistic mental illness confirmed!
Abigail, what is your damage? Are you okay? How's your mom doing? Is everything alright?
You wanna get in the tub? Ow. So you're a lost baby girl and you're a game sweet prince.
He has an Instagram and it is delectable. Meets back on the menu, boys. He carries the
Charles Atlas Seal of Approval. What ho, you jaunty lads. My captain, my king. Yaaas.
If the golden one didn't exist I would have to invent him. I need him. And maybe you need
me too, Lars. I'm the moon to your sun, the Brune Hilda to your Siegfried. As you become
more of a burly mask, I become more of a silky fem. But you know, I'm noticing that even
though you're straight, you don't seem super interested in the bodies of the women in your
life. And this is just a casual suggestion, but maybe what you want is a fair maiden like
me. I'm not like the other girls. I've got the t's and the d. On second thought, leave
trans women alone. I don't want that blood on my hands. Well, this is no longer a relaxing
bath, and that's why we never bathe with fascists.
Well, I've locked my t, I've popped my e, let's talk about degeneracy. What are people
talking about when they call someone or something degenerate? Well, let's take a look at some
examples from my YouTube comments section and see if we can figure it out from context.
Transgender communist degenerate. Kill yourself you fucking degenerate tranny freak. Degen
tranny lal. Trannies grow out of their degeneracy by the time they're senior citizens, or at
least that's what I would assume since you never see old dudes in dresses. Lol what's
up with that? This is degeneracy. You oughta be slung from a tree. Everybody likes to rhyme.
You little homos are future cannon fodder, a bunch of physically weak degenerate dogs.
The end.
Aw, these people are trying so hard to upset me. They've only got one card in the deck
though, alas.
Anyway, what I'm gathering from that sumptuous sampling of the choicest fuckboys is that,
like a burly nord with his fair maiden, the accusation of degeneracy is usually paired
with a loathing of queerness.
Now it's not always just about queerness. In fact, fascists and social conservatives
use the word degeneracy as a catch-all term to refer to queers, non-whites, communists,
communists, people with disabilities, basically anyone who gets killed when the fascists win.
But where does the word degeneracy come from? Let's watch an instructional video to learn
more.
The word degenerate comes from the Latin prefix de-, which means away from, and the Latin
word genus, which means race or kind. So, to be degenerate is to no longer be of your
race or kind, and if you think this already sounds pretty fashy, you've been paying
attention.
The current use of the term degenerate crystallized in the 18th and 19th centuries, when Lamarckian
proto-evolutionary biology, bourgeois disgust toward the urban working class, and a growing
colonialist awareness of supposedly inferior ethnic groups gave rise to degeneration theory,
the idea that civilization is in decline due to biological devolution.
Hold on, are these the exact same dingbats responsible for scientific racism?
The exact same dingbats, yes, and one of the chief dingbats was the French aristocrat Artour
de Gabineau, one of the intellectual grandfathers of Nazism. Gabineau wrote a book called Essay
on the Inequality of the Human Races, in which he developed the idea of the Aryan master
race, warned that miscegenation would lead to social chaos, and gave the word degenerate
its modern fashy definition.
M'lord.
The word degenerate, when applied to a people, means that the people no longer has the same
intrinsic value as it had before, because it has no longer the same blood in its veins,
continual adulterations having gradually affected the quality of the blood. In fact, the man
of a decadent time, the degenerate man, properly so-called, is a different being from the racial
point of view, from the heroes of the great ages. I think I'm right in concluding that
the human race and all its branches has a secret repulsion from the crossing of blood.
Notice that the degenerate man is the product of a decadent time, and decadence is a concept
closely related to degeneracy. Decadence literally means decay, which, like degeneracy, implies
a fall from a previous state of grace. By the late 19th century, concerns about decadence
were everywhere in the European cultural imagination. During this period, German nationalist
composer Richard Wagner wrote his essay condemning Jewishness in music, which he first published
under the pseudonym Freigedank, which literally means free thought. That's right, he pulled
the goddamn free speech card.
ETHAN!
In the 18th century, queer, absence-swilling artists reclaimed the word decadence as the
title of their movement. Everyone was accusing everyone of degeneracy and decadence. It was
4chan writ large.
So the idea that Western civilization has become decadent is not exactly new then.
Not at all. The idea that European civilization is in some way suicidal or self-destructive
goes back to the 18th century, when scholarship about the fall of the Roman Empire led to
speculation about what causes civilizations to decline. And one of the hypotheses was
that effeminate hedonistic emperors and general decadence left the Romans vulnerable to butch
Visigoths and vandals.
Is there any truth to that?
No. It's vulgar pseudo-history encouraged by social conservatives. The decadent emperors
Nero, Caligula, Elagabalus reigned from the first to the third centuries. The empire didn't
collapse till the end of the fifth century, which leaves at least 200 years between the
decadence and the collapse, at which time the empire was thoroughly Christian.
And in any case, the eastern half of the empire still survived for another thousand
years.
Well, hail Caligula. But you know, a lot of people still believe this story about ancient
civilizations collapsing because of the queers. Here's feminist Camille Poglia on how the
transgenders destroy civilizations.
The movement toward androgyny occurs in late phases of culture, as a civilization is starting
to unravel.
Hang on a second. I'm going to need to shift up a gear for this.
Okay, and you can find it again and again and again through history in the Greek art.
You can see it happening all of a sudden. There's a kind of, you know, the sculptures
of handsome, nude young men athletes that used to be very robust in the archaic period
suddenly begin to seem like wet noodles toward the end. People who live in such times feel
that they're very sophisticated, they're very cosmopolitan. Homosexuality, heterosexuality,
so what, anything goes and so on. But from the perspective of historical distance, you
can see that it's a culture that no longer believes in itself. And then what you invariably
get are people who are convinced of the power of heroic masculinity on the edges, whether
they're the vandals, the Huns, or whether they're the barbarians of ISIS. You see them
starting to mass on the outsides of the culture, and that's what we have right now. There's
a tremendous and rather terrifying disconnect between the infatuation with the transgender
movement in our own culture and what's going on out there. I'm concerned, I feel it's
ominous. I question whether the transgender choice is indeed genuine in every single case.
Riley J. Dennis. Why did you destroy ancient Rome?
So the idea is that our infatuation with effeminate decadence means we're going to be destroyed
by real men. You know, like ISIS. This doesn't deserve a response. We're moving on. Where
does fucking Nietzsche fit into all of this?
Oh god, do we really have to do this?
So there's this dead German asshole named Friedrich, who's every edgy 19-year-old's
favorite philosopher.
Hey baby, the ladies tell me I'm Apollonian in the streets, Dionysian in the streets.
Shh, go to sleep.
Basically what he said is that the moral system of Western culture, especially Christianity,
is decadent, in the sense that, unlike pre-Socratic Greek society, we have all these hang-ups
about guilt and sin and the afterlife. And Nietzsche says these ideas originate with
people who are weak and sick, and that they repress our basic biological instincts to
value strength and beauty and worldly happiness.
In practice, this turns out to be a Rorschach test that everyone reads their own ideas into.
There's a fascist interpretation that says we need to cast off the slave morality idea
of universal human equality to make way for the triumph of beefy Aryan studs.
And then there's the more progressive interpretation that says we need to stop worrying about,
like, fucking Christian morality, man, and reinstate the cult of Dionysus, which, okay,
I'd be down to go to that party, especially if we don't have to talk about Nietzsche.
What all this is leading up to is simply the point that by the time 20th century fascism
was really kicking into gear, European society was already primed with a couple centuries
of degeneracy discourse. Racist pseudoscience was combined with degeneration theory and
Wagnerian mysticism to produce the core ideas of National Socialism, namely 1. The German
people and nation are like a biological organism that is prone to infection and decay. 2. The
Jews, Poles, Roma, Homosexuals, Communists, and the Disabled are degenerate elements that
contribute to decay. And 3. The degenerate elements must be purged in order to secure
the health and existence of the organism.
So there you have it, the history of degeneration theory from Foppington to fascism.
Well, thanks for the history lesson, Doc. One particular thing I've noticed about modern
fascists is they're especially obsessed with breeding bountiful crops of white,
black, and brown. And that's not to say that they don't have a history.
Nazis call the Jews vermin, but it's the white people they think should breed like
rats. And they specifically loathe anything that stands in the way of fit white reproduction,
including, as they see it, being gay, being trans, being queer, being fat, being a beta
male, being a slut, being a feminist, not getting married, not having kids, having kids
that aren't white, masturbating, looking at porn, drinking alcohol, doing drugs, using
birth control, having abortions.
Condoms and dorjies and mass immigration, malt liquor forties and miscegenation,
boys who use dildos and girls with cock rings, these are my favorite degenerate things.
Very cute, but don't you think they might have a point about the drugs and alcohol?
Oh god damn, fine, we'll talk about the alcohol thing.
There's like ContraPoints fans now who watch my videos and look up to me, so I have to be
responsible and I hate it.
So look, if you're gonna drink, I'm certainly not gonna stop you, but don't even think about
driving, okay? Drink lots of water, and pace yourself. There's plenty of time to be blackout
when you're dead, and you're gonna be if you don't take it slow.
Alcohol is dangerous, it's unhealthy, it's only fun in moderation, and it can put you
situations with really horrible people, so I would never recommend that anyone get involved
with alcohol for any reason.
I mean, unless you like having fun and feeling good.
Where were we?
Absinthe and coffee and bitchy sarcasm, estrogen crying and fruitless orgasms,
antifa furries and denby drag kings, these are my favorite degenerate things!
Hi there.
I hope you're having
a soothing
degenerate bath.
What I want you to do is just
lie back and
try to relax.
And I am
just going to
slowly start to drip
hot candle wax
So for fascists and identitarians, anything that doesn't contribute to the greater cause of white
procreation is degenerate, and individual fascists differ on what those things are.
Most of them agree that homosexuality is degenerate because apparently gay people
can't raise children. Fascists venerate nuclear families of one dominant white man and one
subservient white woman because they view the situation as the perfect factory for churning
out clean-cut heterosexual white kids. And if you soften the emphasis on whiteness, you get
basic social conservatism. So this really isn't just about fascism, though I do like to talk
about the fascists because they have the biggest muscles. Speaking of which, a lot of rightists
have realized that in the 21st century, the social conservative position is not very cool. So what
they do is they say they of course have no problem with individual homosexuals, what they have a
problem with is the gay agenda. What they have a problem with, essentially, is queerness. Now, what
is queerness? Well, people have all kinds of scholastic debates about this, but in its most
generic sense, queer means that you have some kind of weird sex thing, so either your gender is all
fucked up or you have creative tastes and sexual partners. But unlike the words homosexual or
transgender, queer is tinged with a connotation of rebellion, often rebellion against the
heteronormative commandments of marriage, monogamy, procreation, and productivity.
So social conservatives and even a few fascists claim that they're willing to tolerate gay and
transgender people, but only if you shut up about it, conform to straight society, and try to act
as normal as possible. What they can't stand is loud non-conformist queerness, because think of
the children. We're talking pride parades, activists, leather daddies, gender fucks, kinksters,
polyamorists, sing it with me, these are my favorite degenerate things. To fascists, the pursuit of
individual happiness must be subservient to the health and success of the race. So in a sense,
traditionalism is a much more collectivistic philosophy than even communism, which only
demands the communal ownership of the means of production. At least in theory, communism doesn't
tell you what gender to be or who and how to fuck. In practice though, there's not a single position
on the political spectrum that's immune to complaining about degeneracy. While I was
researching this video, I randomly came across an article from an American communist newspaper
from 1976 that claims,
While we communists oppose attacks on anyone by the bourgeoisie, including homosexuals,
we do not uphold homosexuality as a democratic right. Homosexuality is a form of social sickness,
a form of social perversion. It is a form of bourgeois ideology, which appeals especially to
the petty bourgeoisie because of its appearance as sexual freedom. Homosexuality arose from class
oppression and the oppression of women.
Geez, fellow degenerates, we're kinda short on allies out here, huh? We've got the fascists
calling us sexual bolshevists, and meanwhile the communists are calling us bourgeois decadents.
Why does everyone hate decadents so much? Is pleasure really so wrong?
I know that most people will probably always be straight, cis, monogamous, and pro-creative.
And you know, that's probably for the best. Someone needs to have the babies and keep
society running. All we gentle decadents ask is to be allowed to enjoy our special delights
and peace. My goal is not to purge masculinity from society or anything of the kind. In the
perfect society created by me, there will be plenty of beefy studs around, so don't you
worry about that. And that's the difference between me and the fascists. I want a society
where people like me are simply allowed to exist. And, this is the important part, where
people not like me are simply allowed to exist. Fascists want a society where only people
like them are allowed to exist. The queer quest is to survive. The fascist quest is
to be the only survivor. So if society can tolerate for thousands of years the existence
of priests, which is to say bejeweled men in dresses who have no children and are a
giant tax-exempt drain on the economy, well, you can certainly tolerate queer people who
crack nazi codes and write you musicals and sing you songs. So if you think the meaning
of life is to create as many white babies as possible, you know what? Fine. Go make
white babies. But I really must insist, upon my right, and the right of all degenerates,
to coexist alongside you in our own decadent communities of race-mixing, sexual anarchy,
and rock and roll.
Rock and roll.
A rock-on, gold-dust woman, take your silver spoon, take your grain.
I wake up in the morning, see your sunrise loves to go down.
Lousy lovers pick their prey, but they never cry out loud, cry out.
Well, did she make you cry, make you break down, shatter your illusions of love? Well,
tell me, is it over now? Do you know how to pick up the pieces and go home?
Rock on, ancient queen, follow those who fail and you're shut down.
Ah, that was jack it up. Rulers make bad lovers, you better put your king and dumb up for sale.
One more time. Oh, did she make you cry, make you break down, shatter your illusions of love?
Well, tell me, is it over now? Do you know how to pick up the pieces and go home?
Rock and roll.