Your brain is two brains, two hemispheres, each doing half the work of being you.
Half your vision goes to each and half your movement directed by each.
Right controls left and left controls right.
Your two brains coordinate through a wire of nerves, but this wire can be cut
and was, for a time, used as an epilepsy treatment.
After the cut, people seemed the same, though their brain was split in twain.
Except some post-split patients described that while selecting their morning outfit
with right hand, left might come along to disagree.
Actually, left hand might quite often disagree,
which these split-brain patients found frustrating.
What's happening?
To investigate, remember, right brain sees and controls one half
while left brain controls and sees the other.
But only left brain can speak.
Hello.
Because that's where the speech center is located.
Right brain without this is mute.
In normal brains, this doesn't matter because each half communicates across the wire with the other.
But split-brains can't, and thus you can show just the right brain a word.
Ask the person, what did you see, and you'll hear...
Nothing.
Because left-speaking brain saw nothing.
Meanwhile, right brain will use its hand to pick the object out of a pile hidden from left brain.
This is deeply creepy.
Ask, why are you holding the object,
and speaking left brain will make up a plausible sounding but totally wrong reason.
I always wanted to learn how to solve one of these.
Left brain isn't lying, it's just doing what brains do.
Creating a story that explains its past actions to its current self.
A behavior which does rather cast doubt onto the notion of free will,
but that's a story for another time.
Creating reasons for why it does things is just something left brains do.
It happens in normal healthy humans all the time,
and if you think about it closely, you know you've done this.
Back to experiments.
Give right brain an object, ask the person what's in your hand, and they won't be able to say.
I'm not holding anything.
And when asked to draw, a split brain can draw two separate objects simultaneously
with each hand in a way unsplit brains find challenging.
These experiments on split brain patients are deeply unsettling because they really
point in the direction of a mute separate intelligence something living in the skull.
You can even ask questions of a split brain and get disagreement on the answer.
So if your brain is split, who is the you in this situation?
From the outside, it's tempting to think of the part of the brain that's speaking as the person,
but something is hearing and answering questions.
And the right brain can't speak, it does understand faces, which left brain can't.
If this is you, you don't know who your friends and family are in a crowd.
This act of cutting exposes two minds in one head,
and the talking mind doesn't know there's someone else in the house.
The left brain can describe the situation it's in,
but nonetheless will constantly be surprised by right brain's actions and explain them away.
There's a question to be asked here.
Why, after separation, does right brain not totally freak out,
but instead plays along helpfully answering questions
and listening to left brain's dumb stories about what's happening?
It's the best pony? I don't know.
Speculation time, but one answer is the cutting doesn't make right brain a separate
intelligence, consciousness, person, but rather it has always been.
In normal people, perhaps right brain grows up as a companion without a choice,
feeling at first somewhat equal partners,
but then as speech develops that it can't participate in,
that increasingly becomes the central point of life,
it resigns to mutely coordinate with left brain.
At this moment, in your normal head, there are two of you watching this video.
One having a mind equals blown moment and the other
mentally rolling its eye at the obviousness of it all.
In split brains, right doesn't freak out because not a whole lot has really changed.
You might not agree and may be arguing right now why it can't be possible,
exactly as we would expect talking left brain to do.
Speculation aside, split brain patients show at the very least that in the mind,
there is a separate something that can hear and understand and respond,
given the right circumstances.
Your brain isn't entirely yours. Who is you? You is too.
But we can go deeper.
You are many.
The pile of meat that is your body is made up of trillions of tiny individuals
that have a life of their own, so at which point do the many become one.
What makes lots of tiny things? You.
Click here to go to our channel and watch the next part.