Hi, I'm Harriton Splimby, and welcome to Serious Law Analysis.
Oh, fucking...
Just... fucking...
You will pay for what you have done.
...
Today on Serious Law Analysis,
we're covering a creative work that I heavily implied
might have been coming next in the last few videos.
And that's right, today we're covering
the Control-Alt-Delete Webcomic and Animated series.
In retrospect, I think I might have made it too obvious.
For those of you too young to remember the early days of the world,
before we had the Internet and hadn't yet achieved the dream
of having to argue with Holocaust deniers all day,
humans would amuse themselves by painting stuff on the walls of their caves
or later drawing it onto paper or canvas.
These scribbles became known as...
...
Eventually, however, humans evolved past this bullshit
and realized you could divide up your space into smaller subspaces
called Parnells and then use that to create several sequential images,
which when read in order could tell a story.
This sequence art later became known as comics
for reasons we forgot because it doesn't matter.
Fast forward to the late 90s and early 2000s
where we played video games and things were finally good.
Then people who enjoyed video games gained access to the Internet.
But because they didn't yet have the bandwidth
to play most games online or watch puppy compilations all day
and argue in the comments about 9-11,
people instead would amuse themselves online by using webcomics,
also known as digital versions of comics that you find on the web.
And since the bar for publishing onto the Internet
was as low as being able to afford server hosting
or even lower if you used a free website,
people were finally free to create comics
for a small or niche in audiences they liked
without any need for mass market appeal
or the production costs of ink and paper and printing
or, um, quality.
Enter the gaming webcomic,
a form of webcomic centering around jokes about games and gaming culture,
the most popular of these was Penny Arcade,
a comic still going to this day,
rife with hilarious and well-thought-out humor.
Don't state me, bro! Ha ha ha!
Hilarious! It's just like the thing!
With the guy!
The bedrock of this type of comic tends to feature several characters,
often representative of the authors,
sitting on a couch making hilarious jokes
about video games that are out right now
or inside the fiction of a video game
interacting with it to hilarious consequences.
These two forms were the bedrock
of many early gaming webcomics
from the late 90s to the early 2000s,
and there were many successful comics using this format
like Penny Arcade, PvP, Little Gamers,
Bob & George, 8-Bit Theater, and others.
All tremendous pieces of art
with a lot to say about games
and how bad it is that our games are being usurped by money men
and how funny it would be if you died
in a way a lot bigger like it's just like in the game.
But for every one of these comics,
there were dozens of poor imitators
out to replicate their popularity and profit
by reusing the same tropes.
An explosion in the gaming webcomic had begun,
and it would continue for over a decade.
Enter Tim Buckley with his own webcomic,
Control-Alt-Delete, often referred to as CAD.
CAD isn't like the other webcomics.
It's not art. It doesn't have value or meaning.
It's trash, and it doesn't say anything at all.
It's full of worthless jokes where the punchline is violence.
It's not like Penny Arcade. CAD is the story of Ethan,
a character who looks suspiciously like
how Buckley draws himself.
Ethan and his roommate Lucas talk about video games
and occasionally are inside the games
where something bad happens to them or people they don't like.
Wow, that's original.
Let's compare and contrast this with a good comic, shall we?
In this 2002 page from Penny Arcade,
the author insert characters burn a voodoo doll
hurting George Romero.
Oh, my God, look how much better these guys are.
This is great. Meanwhile, look over here
at CAD in the slow lane for Idiots
using violence as a punchline.
What a stupid thing to put in a comic.
Over time, CAD stopped even trying to tell jokes,
and it started spending more and more time exploring
the personal lives and development of its characters.
The main characters, Ethan and Lucas, went on dates,
moved apartments, made and lost friends,
and started long-term relationships.
Ethan quickly meets and begins dating Lila,
a girl who plays video games, which, as we all know,
is like finding a unicorn,
and like all girls who do play games,
it's her only character trait.
The two inexplicably fall in love
even though Ethan has nothing to offer anyone
and is basically unlikable.
It's pretty clear from reading this
that Buckley doesn't know how human relationships work.
You could almost point out this...
almost says something
about how people who play video games a lot
view human relationships, but...
No, no, no, no, no.
No, it's bad, and it doesn't mean anything.
Tim Buckley's just really bad at making comics.
Oh, also, despite being basically unable
to do anything but play video games,
Ethan eventually builds a sentient AI robot
who becomes the fourth main character.
Zeke exists to occasionally joke
about how humans are made of meat and bad
and he's better than them.
It's clearly inspired by characters
like HK-47 from KOTOR or Bender from Futurama,
but there's no actual jokes here.
It's what I like to call a joke by association.
It's not really a joke.
It's just a vague gesture
in the direction of a joke
that you might remember from somewhere else.
Somewhere else.
I'm somewhere else.
Why are you doing this?
Don't do this to yourself.
Don't become one of them.
One of what?
The worst thing about this comic
is that it doesn't know what it wants to be.
No, wait.
Actually, the worst thing is CAD Premium.
For a few years, you could pay a monthly fee
to get access to episodes of the CAD animated series,
which the comic inexplicably had.
It ran for two seasons,
and some episodes ran up to six minutes.
If you thought a story featuring cartoon violence,
a futuristic killer robot,
video game opinions on a couch,
and awkward, boring, serious relationship drama
had trouble finding its identity in comic form,
just wait until it comes in a box set
containing barely two hours of animation
made in about a week that you paid
35 entire dollars of your actual human money for.
Three episodes of the 12-episode first season
are dedicated entirely to an extended Star Wars reference.
They reenact an entire Star Wars film
in each five-minute episode,
compressing it down so much you'd barely even realize
that's what they're doing unless you listen
to the director's commentary track,
which this show has for some reason.
The villain, instead of Darth Vader,
is Jack Thompson, a lawyer who tried to sue game developers
for making their players violent.
The Death Star is a sign that makes people
stop playing video games?
It's time to test the power
of this fully operational anti-gamer billboard.
Speaking of Jack Thompson,
Thompson appeared to have struck a nerve with Buckley.
One page of the comic is straight-up
an open letter to Jack,
a four-panel, long mini-novel
spoken directly by Buckley himself
from within the comic.
What's amazing about it is how it manages to,
while claiming gamers are peaceful
even though they've played a lot of violent games,
ends with the threatening phrase,
which, by the way,
is also a line from that scene in Fight Club
where they threaten to cut off a guy's testicles
if he defies them.
Do not bother us.
Imagine writing something like that
and thinking, yeah,
that proves that gamers are peaceful
and intelligent and can be reasoned with.
It almost says something about gamers
when people sit down and write things like that.
Where's that fucking noise coming from?
Where's...
What?
Don't you think you might be reading a little too much into it
about what a bad comic that sucks might say?
Stick to thinking about real art.
Ugh, this is just like that Sonic thing, isn't it?
The Sonic thing?
You're overthinking a blue hedgehog, man.
Why can't you be objective?
Why can't you talk about the level design and mechanics instead?
You could be talking about how Mario 1-1
teaches you how to play it.
But it's not just a hedgehog, is it?
I mean, it's animals fighting a developed machine empire.
Like, there's very, very obvious themes going on here,
a discussion of ecology versus technology.
If you want to talk about how great nature is
and how bad technology is,
why don't you go live in the woods?
You wouldn't do that, though, would you?
You wouldn't have your precious lattes to drink
while you complain on your iPhone about capitalism.
I don't drink lattes. What the fuck are you talking about?
By now, you've probably noticed
a fairly strong contradiction in the comic.
Between the crass, random, non-canon of the many parts
intended purely for no-strings-attached comedy,
the serious parts where Buckley himself
definitely doesn't personally threaten someone,
and the actual serious lives of the main characters
who have problems that don't go away,
the comic keeps reverberating back and forth,
going to further and further extremes.
Sometimes you'd get a story where Lucas goes on a date
with a woman who turns out to be fat,
so he awkwardly pretends to be interested
for hilarious comedy,
and then they go back to her place,
and it turns out she was only pretending
to be fat as a test,
and they start a relationship that lasts
for five years of the comic?
Then you'd get a chef character saying nonsense for a joke,
and then something random happens,
or maybe you'd get the players, four characters
whose whole deal is they murder each other
in different ways over and over.
Then it turns out Ethan's girlfriend is pregnant.
Then they joke about what if the guns in the new
Gears of War game were guns with trains
instead of chainsaws?
You snap back and forth so quickly,
you get whiplash of the mind.
The tension between the comic's supposed reality
and meaningless comic fantasy world
eventually snapped when,
during a scene at Ethan's job where he's making a joke
about consumers being stupid
and not knowing as much about games as him,
he gets a phone call.
Lila, the comedy video game girlfriend character,
is in the hospital
because she's had a miscarriage.
This culminates in perhaps
the most well-known page of a comic
in history.
♪
When asked by a noted art scholar
the appropriate distance from which to stand
when viewing his magnum opus,
plainly entitled
Loss,
Tim Buckley famously responded,
What?
Fuck you!
and banned me from his forum.
The release of Loss profoundly shook
the edifice of its audience.
People were equal parts
shocked, horrified, surprised,
offended,
and completely mystified.
The semi-serious but still mostly jokey
plot parts of the story are utterly shattered,
giving way to a harsh and cold reality
where characters in other contexts
have committed or received
tremendous acts of violence,
only capable of a genuine moment
of horrific suffering.
A comic famous for using too many words
to say nothing at all about a video game
on a stationary couch
takes four panels and zero words
to show a horrifying discovery
and a trip through an entire hospital.
A gaming webcomic,
a comedy gaming webcomic,
has an arc in it about the characters
having to deal with the miscarriage
of their child!
This comic struck a nerve on the Internet.
Over nine years later,
people are still making fun of it.
This comic has been parodied
and referenced in memes
an uncountable amount of times.
Entire webpages have been dedicated
to tracking them all
and failed to contain them.
In the next two comics,
the characters struggle to even react
to what has happened.
It's breaking my heart
to watch her hurt like this.
The next comic is a joke about how there aren't
enough dragons in Dungeons & Dragons anymore.
The next comic is a single panel
of the four players about to murder each other.
For the next little while,
the comic switched between dumb video game jokes
and Buckley trying desperately
to restore the comfortable,
consequence-free tone he had developed
over the five years of the comic.
It takes at least eight pages
before Ethan can go back
to making goggles out of pineapples.
By late November,
the characters have fully patched up their problems
and they get married,
and we get tearful speeches
about how important these characters are to each other.
Life dropped an epic husband,
the rarest of its loot table,
and I was lucky enough
to win the need roll.
["Cheering"]
Then, for about four years,
the comic was basically stand-alone silly jokes
interspersed with bits where there were
mini-comics set in a universe like Star Wars
for some reason.
One could say that,
with the advent of Loss,
a lesson had been learned.
Don't put one of the most
emotionally traumatizing events
a human can experience
in your...
comedy gaming webcomic!
Then, in September 2012,
Ethan tried to build a time machine
and a future version of Ethan comes through it
and kidnaps him into the future.
The next two months of comics were an extended storyline
in which it turns out that Ethan's actions
destroy most of humanity
as the robot he builds eventually goes insane
and murders everyone he loves
and takes over the world,
but in the process,
the time machine is damaged
and threatens to destroy all of time,
so Ethan has to sacrifice himself
to turn the machine off,
killing him and saving the future
as his inner monologue makes a tearful goodbye
to a character no one really cares about
because she's basically just written to be
a love interest for the author stand-in.
Ethan, our main character, dies.
He dies in the most convoluted fashion possible
and no one ever learns what happened.
Now that's how you end a...
gaming webcomic.
Except it didn't end.
It's still been going for five more years,
but with just the self-contained sketches
and the characters from the old version
in a rebooted form,
the comic somehow continues to limp on.
It literally killed its main character
and then it just sort of started again.
So that...
THAT was CAD.
CAD was mean-spirited,
hateful, and angry.
CAD was, uh, uh,
judgmental, tone-deaf,
self-righteous screed of a webcomic.
And...
Wait.
I'm warning you.
Don't do this, man.
Don't go there.
Sorry, are you talking to someone?
Is there someone here?
Doesn't CAD...
say something about gamer culture?
Stop!
No! No!
What have you done?!
What's happening?
Why?
It's caused this crisis.
It's caused this virus.
These games aren't fitting for one of us.
They are responsible.
We are responsible.
We haven't done hyving these people,
They know bemoaning them.
Don't fuck with us.
What...?
Hi, I'm Heritan Splimbi,
and welcome to...
What the fuck is happening?!
What just happened here?
Tommy Wiseau's infamous film,
The Room,
asks some really interesting questions
about how we look at art.
No, seriously, come on!
Stay with me here!
In terms of pure filmmaking skill,
of course, it's awful.
The script is a nightmare.
It's poorly edited,
with random shots of San Francisco
just kind of slammed in there.
It has such below-average shot composition
and mise-en-scene
that I actually feel bad
for even saying those words,
and the ADR is terrible, too.
Yeah, can I have a dozen red roses, please?
Oh, hi, Johnny. I didn't know it was you.
Here you go.
That's me.
How much is it?
It'll be $18.
Here you go. Keep the change.
Hi, doggie.
You're my favorite customer.
Thanks a lot. Bye.
It has a reputation
for being a hilariously bad film
everyone can laugh at for being bad.
He's a bad movie!
Made even more interesting
by the incredibly weird performance of Wiseau.
I've fed up with this world!
But I think, under the proper lens,
the film has a little more to say to its audience
than, look at me, I'm so bad.
Tommy Wiseau didn't write a film
about a perfect guy
who gets cheated on by his girlfriend
and basically has his life ruined for no reason,
and he didn't choose to play that perfect guy
for no reason either.
And here, taking a particular critical look,
I think a valuable message
can be learned from the film.
The film has often been criticized
in terms of its base components
like writing or acting.
Lisa, for example,
behaves completely irrationally
or perhaps with deliberate malice towards Johnny.
I have him wrapped around my little finger.
Oh, you should be happy then.
But I don't love him.
Suddenly falling out of love with him
and cheating on him and then spreading lies about him
for seemingly no reason.
You are lying. I never hit you.
You are tearing me apart, Lisa!
Why are you so hysterical?
I contend here
that Wiseau based the play script
that would later become the film
on an actual life experience,
an actual breakup that really happened
at some point in his life.
I treat you like a princess,
and you stab me in the back.
I loved you, and I did anything for you
to just please you,
and now you betray me.
How could you love him?
Aah!
I'm not saying the events happened
exactly as Tommy writes them.
In fact, they definitely didn't.
Obviously, Tommy didn't kill himself,
and obviously, women don't grow distant
from the people they're in a relationship with
for no reason.
Women change their minds all the time.
The Room is a fictionalized,
exaggerated representation
of what Tommy thinks happened
in this real relationship,
being completely, perhaps even incoherently honest
about why he thinks it fell apart,
and it's clear that he thinks it fell apart
because his girlfriend started acting weird
and crazy and trying to hurt him.
What's important here is to understand
that to Tommy,
this is genuinely how he views this woman.
This character is to him
an honest expression of that person,
but there has to have been a real Lisa once,
and her perspective,
her side of the story, isn't told.
We don't get to see the things Tommy did
that led her to move on from him or cheat on him,
and we only have Tommy's word
that he wasn't abusive and was a really good guy,
and maybe the fact he genuinely thought
to depict this woman as a monster
trying to ruin his life
says something about how he understands
other people and their feelings.
The Room, precisely with its unrealistic,
biased inaccuracy,
accurately depicts why breakups actually happen.
People don't fully understand
how the other person feels
and begin to think of them as malicious figures
because that's the only way we can make sense of people
when we don't fully understand them.
I've talked to plenty of guys about breakups,
and very often you get the same old story
just like this one where their partner
turned out to be a crazy bitch
who just wanted to hurt them,
but if you're ever lucky enough
to hear the other side of a story like that,
they're often just frustrated with people
who can so easily view them like that
if they have a few arguments.
Wiseau tried to make a film about his breakup,
but it turned out to be a film about his inability
to understand why it happened.
No. No.
No more.
The Room is a filmed version
of the real, heavily distorted perspective
on breakups that many heterosexual men often have,
and in many ways, when you look at the film this way,
it serves as a call to action
to learn to see past the leases we think we see
and understand that relationships
tend to fall apart for a reason,
and we can learn to do better
by seeing people for who they are.
For all its actual flaws,
and even because of some of its clearly
deeply flawed misogynistic writing,
The Room ends up being
an actually valuable demonstration
of the distorted ways people perceive relationships
and how this eventually destroys them
better than any film made by, say,
I don't know, any man actually working
in Hollywood right now,
especially the ones currently cashing in
on the popularity of The Room.
Hi! I'm he...
AH!
Gah!
Ah!
As you might be aware,
EA recently closed Visceral Games,
the studio working on a Star Wars game
that had been in the works for a long time,
being worked on by M. Night Shyamalan
being worked on by, among many others,
the director and writer of most of the Uncharted games,
but also one of the best-written game series ever,
Legacy of Kain,
and pivoting the entire game away from what was being made.
This update, posted on EA's website by Patrick Suderland,
vice president of EA,
cites
fundamental shifts in the marketplace.
Single-player linear experiences
simply aren't profitable enough,
at least compared to certain other recent kinds of experience
that emphasize time investment
and incentivize further transactions
made over the course of a single product
rather than a simple one-off purchase.
This is one of many management decisions
that exists in a marketplace
driven by the forces inherent to a capitalist society.
The decision is, sadly,
the result of the overall company goal
to continue to grow and satisfy investors,
and this practice trumps creative freedom
or what games players might actually want to see.
Penny Arcade covered this story
by featuring one of the two main characters,
a stand-in for the author,
directly, personally calling Patrick Suderland
an incoherent, art-destroying monster.
Literally, the only thing I know about you
is that you destroy things.
Jobs, art.
I mean, where should I even start?
What you did is bad for games,
bad for gamers,
and trying to frame it as anything but cowardice
is offensive.
Penny Arcade is consistently cited as far better than CAD
because CAD's just a bunch of nonsensical rants,
and it keeps just using violence as a punch.
No, wait.
This is Penny Arcade's violence.
How did this get in here?
This is obviously hilarious.
Oh, my God, he was killed by a gun.
Ha ha ha.
Here's to another two decades of comedy gold
and insightful commentary
on the future of gaming.
Penny Arcade got so popular and influential
on the back of this stuff
that its convention, PAX,
is one of the biggest industry events of the year
with even major companies showing off games there.
CAD also had a convention of its own
for a couple of years labeled Digital Overload,
and I hesitate to admit,
things don't get popular enough
to have an entire convention
without being at least partially accurate reflections
of their audience.
I hope the problem here is clear.
Even the most intelligent,
well-paid, popular,
and, uh, verbose writers
gaming culture has to offer
seem unaware that these decisions
are not made in a vacuum,
that games are threatened not
by a secretive anti-art coward
but by an environment that systematically crushes
most of the people who work on them
in order to make its owners and shareholders
vastly rich and which has no interest
in anything's intrinsic value.
Gaming culture is largely unable
to conceive of this level of socioeconomic criticism,
of analysis of systemic problems
and wider issues with society
beyond one person's individual failings
and therefore cannot accurately fathom
exactly what is damaging the things they love.
Instead, they have to fantasize
about their very own Lisa hiding somewhere in EA
trying to kill art
like some kind of fucking Disney villain.
This is why people hate CAD so much.
Not because it's bad.
No, bad things come and go all day.
Every day.
CAD is such a source of focus and aggression
with millions and millions of words
written about how awful it and its creator is
because it's an embarrassment.
It makes everyone else near it look bad
because as bad as it is,
it managed to be honest.
So people have to try as hard as they can
to project these things away from them,
try to shift the blame onto Buckley himself
and away from the fact they share
a lot of the same perspectives.
Think again about that Jack Thompson comic.
No one just ends up in a position
where they'll write something like this all on their own.
Jack Thompson, wrong and dishonest as he was,
received thousands of death threats
and messages full of harassment for years
from people just like Tim
or people who had been influenced by this comic.
No, CAD is merely a particularly silly
and vulgar expression of a broader set of bad ideas
that continue to go largely unexamined
by the people who hold them.
Tim Buckley's disjointed personal philosophy
and lack of skill didn't come from nowhere.
We don't get to pretend he's just some random guy.
Blaming one man for the flaws of a broken economic system
is making the same mistake as blaming Tim Buckley
for accurately presenting the culture in which he exists.
We just have to learn to accept
that there might be a lesson in things we hate about us,
that even if it's bad and we don't like it,
we have more in common with it than we want to admit
and can even learn something from it.
CAD turned out to be reflective
of the cultural reality that produced it,
and people are only angry at it this much
because they don't like what they saw in the mirror.
You all right?
Oh, my God.
When we look at ridiculous behaviour within our sphere,
instead of trying to project it out of ourselves,
say it's just some random idiot somewhere
doing something dumb,
maybe we should accept that CAD, Penny Arcade, Visceral Games,
and even EA's business decisions
are aspects of a wider culture
that can be reflective of our own feelings
and beliefs and values,
even if we don't like what comes out of them.
And maybe if we learn to criticise ourselves
and change our own behaviour,
we can start to change the wider culture.
Thank you for your time.
I must set aright that which has been made wrong.
Copyright © 2020 Mooji Media Ltd. All Rights Reserved.
No part of this recording may be reproduced
without Mooji Media Ltd.'s express consent.
Please, forgive me.
You are my world,
my best friend,
the love of my life.
I promise,
I promised
I would never hurt you,
that I would never leave you.
I have to break that promise.
I'm so sorry.
Video games,
I love you.
Ah!
It's time.
Yes.
Yes!
Sing Now
Come on, come on.