In my video, Coronavirus vs Politics, I mentioned that the WHO had announced a global death
rate of 3.4%.
Globally, about 3.4% of reported Covid-19 cases have died.
And that President Trump said he thought that number was false.
Well, I think the 3.4% is really a false number.
So in order to establish the facts, I explained in my video how the figure was derived.
The figure is correct because it's simple maths – the number of deaths at the time
of the study divided by the total number of reported cases.
That's the number of people who've tested positive.
It's known as the case fatality rate, or more colloquially, the death rate.
But judging from the posts on the forum, not everyone got it.
So I'll try to make it easier to understand, this time with analogies and illustrations.
Let's start with the claims that the figure wasn't known.
Well, it was known because it's a simple matter of dividing two numbers for a given
population on a given date.
About 3.4% of reported Covid-19 cases.
And at the time of the statement, the number of reported cases worldwide was 98,192.
And the number of recorded deaths was 3,380.
Just to make sure the WHO got their sums right, I did the calculation myself.
3,380 divided by 98,192 and multiply by 100 to give you the percentage.
That gives you 3.44%, or 3.4% to one decimal place.
So the figure was right.
Epidemiologists call this the CFR, or case fatality rate.
It's not measuring all the infections or all the deaths, it's only measuring the
reported cases and recorded deaths.
And that was clearly spelled out.
So the honest scientific answer is not, we don't know, the honest scientific answer
is 3.4%.
The only way that number can change is if the number of reported worldwide cases and
recorded worldwide deaths up to March 3rd were revised.
But so far they haven't been.
I think one reason for people's confusion is that they assume there's just one number,
one definitive CFR.
In fact, there are many.
As I explained in the video, if you sample global figures at a different time, the CFR
would be different.
So for example, up to September 22nd, the CFR was 3.1%.
Or if you focused on just one part of the world population, like Denmark, the figure
would be different again.
I explained that the CFR will vary from country to country because it's dependent on a number
of variables, such as demographics, quality of healthcare and so on.
To use an analogy, it's a bit like giving world ticket sale figures for the movie Avengers
Endgame up to May 3rd, 2019, as a percentage of population.
Let's say 50 million people saw the movie.
Out of a world population of 7 billion, that would be 0.7%.
The percentage of people in Spain who saw the movie during the same period would obviously
be different.
And the percentage of the world who saw the movie on a different date would be different
again.
You can't say we don't know the global figure up to May 3rd or that it's an estimate
just because ticket sales for different countries on different dates are, not surprisingly,
different.
OK, I'm going to anticipate a flood of posts here along the lines of, we can't be sure
that all the deaths are due to COVID-19.
Some people might have died of natural causes.
But because they coincidentally had COVID, doctors just put it down to COVID.
So that number is an estimate, which means the CFR is wrong.
Firstly, the number in this equation isn't the number of deaths, but the number of recorded
deaths attributed to COVID-19.
Of course, the fatal conditions it causes, like cardiogenic shock, septic shock, multiple
organ failure or respiratory failure, could have happened anyway that same day.
And that's probably true in some patients.
But in most cases, if the patient hadn't contracted COVID-19, he or she might have continued living
for another 10, 20 or even 60 years.
The best way to measure that is something called excess mortality, the number of deaths
above the seasonal average.
And this shows something surprising.
The number of excess deaths in the UK and the USA is actually higher than the number
of recorded deaths due to COVID-19.
So if we take the excess mortality divided by the number of cases, it actually comes
out as more than the CFR, not less.
Most of the posters, though, thought the CFR was wrong for another reason.
They were mixing up the case fatality rate with the infection fatality rate.
For example, imagine thinking 3.4% was the real CFR because you assumed that all cases
were recorded.
But of course the CFR doesn't assume all cases are recorded at all.
It assumes they aren't recorded.
That's the point.
You'll never record all the cases unless you've tested every single person in a population
every single day.
Since that doesn't happen, epidemiologists have to estimate the total number of infections.
And when they divide the number of deaths by the estimated number of infections, that
doesn't give them the CFR, it gives them something called the IFR, the infection fatality rate.
In fact, the WHO explained this back in February.
While the CFR in China at that time was 2.3%, the IFR was estimated at between 0.3 and 1%.
And they explained it again in March.
The data we have so far indicate that the crude mortality rate, the number of reported
deaths divided by the reported cases, is between 3 to 4%.
The infection mortality rate, the number of reported deaths divided by the number of infections,
will be lower.
If the reason still isn't clear, I'll explain the difference with a simple illustration.
Let's say the 12 people in orange are those who've been tested positive for COVID-19.
They're the number of cases.
Two of their number died as a result, and they're marked in red.
So 2 out of 12 is therefore the case fatality rate, the CFR.
And simple maths tells us that that number in this illustration is 16.7%.
The sample size isn't statistically significant, but this is just for the purpose of illustration.
Now let's say there are another 17 people somewhere among the population who had the
virus but their symptoms were so mild they never got tested.
So they obviously don't show up as cases.
We don't even know how many there are.
But epidemiologists can estimate their number through various methods.
Let's say their estimate is 16 people, which is pretty close.
We'll show them in yellow.
If we add those 16 to the 12 others who were recorded, that makes a total of 28 suspected
infections.
So now if we divide the number of deaths, too, by the number of suspected infections,
28, we get the infection fatality rate, or IFR, which in this example is 7.1%.
Some people thought that my IFR figure of roughly 1% was wrong in the earlier video
because they've seen different figures at different times for different populations.
So let me stress again that just like the CFR, there's no single infection fatality
rate.
My figure of around 1% isn't the result of sloppy research, it's the estimated global
figure for that particular time period.
Of course it's going to be different for South Korea and it's going to be different
for Wuhan.
Most IFRs lie between 0.5% and 2% depending on the population, the quality of healthcare
and so on.
And the reason I say about is because even the figure itself is an estimate.
The exact number of infections, unlike the number of cases, isn't known.
The illustrations show why there's a huge difference between the IFR and the CFR, and
why confusing the two very different measurements can mislead you into thinking epidemiologists
have made a mistake.
Some posters gave away the fact that they were confusing the CFR and the IFR by referring
to uncounted cases.
Others gave it away by the low figures they cited.
I mean, obviously the global case fatality rate wasn't 1% on March 3rd, or 0.5%, or
1% to 2% or lower, or less than 1%, or 0.5% to 1.6%, unless my math is shockingly bad.
So where do those figures come from?
Coincidentally they're all within the range of estimates for various infection fatality
rates, which suggests that these posters, like the President, have confused the CFR
with the IFR.
One poster even said that if I played more of the President's interview, I'd see
that he was talking about the figure for uncounted cases.
Yes, I know, that's the infection fatality rate, which is why he was clearly confusing
the two figures.
That's why his claim was wrong.
You can't argue that a figure for a case fatality rate is false simply because you've
mixed it up with a completely different measurement.
I hope those people who didn't understand the difference do now get it, but we'll
see.
My bet is that the next response will be, well, it doesn't matter anyway.
After all, you can't expect a politician to know the difference between the case fatality
rate and the infection fatality rate, even if they are completely different.
That's just splitting hairs.
What he means is that only 1% of people infected will die.
But here's the problem.
If the President of the United States – not just this President, any President – wrongly
believes that the figures he's hearing from scientific bodies are false, that can lead
to policy decisions based on his beliefs rather than actual data.
Sometimes life and death decisions.
And if he goes on national television and, based on that misunderstanding, tells people
WHO epidemiologists are exaggerating the severity of a virus, a lot of them will believe him,
as we've seen from these posts.
And that leads to a distrust in science and complacency.
That's why the media needs to fact-check claims by government leaders and report the
correct figures.
Whether or not you believe that me giving the correct figures will lead to panic, or
you think I'm being disrespectful, subversive or treasonous, as in other countries when
leaders are fact-checked, well that's a matter of opinion.
But a lot of people do want to know the facts, and I think they have every right to know.
Don't they?
My thanks to all those who've donated to the charity Health in Harmony, which I've
asked you to support as a way of supporting my channel, which of course isn't monetised.
Donations from people who follow my channel have now exceeded $100,000, which is fantastic.
It's allowed the charity to expand their healthcare for forest protection into Madagascar
and now into the Shingu region of Brazil.
Details are in the video description if you want to know more about this innovative and
very effective charity.