Hi, my name is Nick. I am a YouTuber formerly known as Nickatine2, currently posting on
the Nick Sci-Fi account here on YouTube. I'm making this video to tell you to subscribe
to my new account, as my old one has just been suspended for two weeks. Now, the cause
of this suspension is one earlier video of mine which was flagged and removed about six
months ago for being somewhat offensive to Christians, bless their little souls. Now,
the most recent video of mine to have been flagged and removed was a video called The
Chilling Effects of Tickle Porn, which featured a 28-second segment of a young woman wearing
a shirt and panties being tickled on her exposed navel. Now, this video in no way violates
YouTube's terms of service. In fact, I downloaded the video off of YouTube. It had been up here
already for several months and had more than 100,000 views. Now, keep in mind that the
average Hot for Words videos contains material more sexually explicit than this. The average
movie trailer contains material with more exposed female flesh than my video. The average
video YouTube features on its page contains more sexual activity than the video I uploaded.
In fact, I have seen more sexually explicit material in footage of the New York Stock
Exchange than I have seen in the video for which I have been suspended. But nevertheless,
YouTube has decided that my video was just too offensive to keep on their website. It
would just offend the people so much that they would stop clicking on advertisements.
They lose all their ad revenue because, God forbid, someone has uploaded a picture with
a female stomach. Holy shit!