Hello everyone, so as you may be aware a while back
I made a few videos about the YouTube channel CinemaSins laying out various mistakes
They've made and criticizing their general approach to movie criticism. A response to those videos has been uniformly positive
YouTube users are still leaving me plenty of supportive messages on those videos. For example, Patrick Harris says
Thanks for the video. Like many CinemaSins viewers
I had previously not understood the word satire, but after watching your videos
I now realize that I was using it incorrectly and CinemaSins is not in fact satirical.
Another commenter says keep up the good work
I can't believe CinemaSins conditioned me into laughing at their repetitive unfunny jokes. A humorous intent is no defense
if the joke unfairly denigrates other people's hard work through deception and
falsehood and
John Doe says oh I get it
CinemaSins watches movies and finds things in them to nitpick and you did the same thing to their videos. That's very clever
Although I'm not a fan of yours
Attaching my ego to a clickbait YouTube channel would be ridiculous and thus I will not get mad at you and leave you a nasty message
Anyway, after making those videos I did the sensible thing and stopped watching CinemaSins entirely for more than a year and it was wonderful
I've never known such peace to be honest. It's been the best year of my life so far
However
Recently a friend linked me to this video
Everything wrong with Blade Runner in 17 minutes or less put out by CinemaSins to coincide with the release of the recent
Blade Runner sequel and I thought oh
Go on then, you know, I can handle just one. It's been a while
Maybe they aren't as bad as I remember. Maybe I was exaggerating back then
So I gave it a watch and I saw this
CinemaSins gave Blade Runner a sin for being quote
Super advanced and super dilapidated all at the same time
You know like it's a mistake. Oh
God I'm even getting mad looking at it right now now Blade Runner is of course a
Cyberpunk film and the juxtaposition of advanced technology and societal problems like inequality
Is by design, you know rather than technology leading to a utopian post scarcity future
Films and other works of art in the sub-genre typically ask what if technology keeps advancing?
But we're unable to solve our various societal problems
You know, what if we still have things like inequality class divides crime police?
Slavery and all that, you know
how will the advance of technology interact with and even possibly exacerbate those problems a
Blade Runner being set in the future that is super advanced and super dilapidated at the same time
It's the whole point a point that is
Completely missed by CinemaSins who give the movie a sin and ding it as if it were a mistake
Akin to the boom mic showing in the shot or something
Anyway after thinking about this sin for about four seconds
I realized I was gonna have to make another CinemaSins video, but then I thought
Skipping all the way to the present day
Wouldn't really be right would it?
CinemaSins have put out over a hundred videos in the past year and I bet they've made some really gratuitous mistakes in those
So that's what we're gonna do today pick up where we left off with CinemaSins and catalog just a portion of everything
They've got wrong in the past year
Let's show them how to nitpick properly and let's start off with a sin from their video on the movie 10 Cloverfield Lane
You're the only one small enough to reach it. It's what the filtration system
This guy is the king of over preparedness for disasters and did not know this girl or anyone other than him would be down here
When he built this shelter, but still made the air filtration system accessible to only people one-fifth his size
So why would John Goodman's character build an air filtration system that he was unable to access what a buffoon he is
But let's take a peek at the movie real quick
Your filtration system
Ah
You see he could reach it but something was blocking the hatch and why would something be blocking the hatch
well a minute earlier in the movie a
Then unknown force caused the bunker to shake and that damaged the air filtration system and blocked the hatch to it
Also here when CinemaSins say that John Goodman's character Howard didn't know that anyone else would be down here with him
And that's not true either as there are various clues in the bunker pointing to the fact that Howard had
Previously kept someone else there such as the word help scratched into the glass on the inside of the exit hatch
I also like this sin from later in the video where CinemaSins call a Molotov cocktail a
makeshift Molotov cocktail, you know as
Opposed to the official line of Molotov cocktails that you'd buy in the store
I guess in their video for the rock CinemaSins call these helicopters Blackhawk helicopters
But they're not this is a Blackhawk helicopter, which as you can see doesn't really look anything like what they showed
You know beyond being a helicopter
Let's take a look at a sin from Star Trek 3 the search for Spock
There are your life forms these were microbes on the tube surface microbes by their very definition are microscopic living organisms
I hate to be nitpicky, but these seem way more visible without a microscope than usual
Well, I love to be nitpicky and the line was they were
Microbes in the past tense implying that they are no longer microbes and indeed if we look at the movie
These were microbes on the tube surface. We shot them here from Enterprise
Let's take a look at a sin from their video for the movie The Bourne Supremacy now from near the end of the movie
Somehow with all these witnesses Bourne still escapes into the ether after this
So a lot of witnesses saw Bourne after his car crash in the tunnel
So how did he possibly escape and you might be wondering well, what's wrong with this?
Well, let's now watch us in from the start of their video for the next movie in the series The Bourne Ultimatum
Which continues the story after this car crash?
So the Moscow police are coming after Bourne because of that tunnel chase scene from the last movie
How the fuck did Bourne get spotted in the first place?
And how is he identified by anyone in that dark ass tunnel and that's unbelievable, isn't it?
How did Bourne get away with all these witnesses there and then the next movie?
How did any of those witnesses see Bourne in that dark tunnel?
Shameful
These videos came out only two days apart, by the way
Similar to that. Let's look at a sin from their video about Ghost in the Shell
Earlier we saw that the major is heavy and dense enough to bend a metal roof tile
But here she's buoyant enough to float on water instead of sinking like a rock
So how can the major float when she's so heavy?
Well
The shot CinemaSins used is taken from the end of the diving scene after we've already seen the
flotation device on the majors back carry her to the surface
CinemaSins neglect to show that obviously what they also don't mention here is the following
conversation on the boat where Batou talks to the major about how dangerous it is for cyborgs to go swimming and
Specifically mentions the majors flotation equipment, you know, how did CinemaSins miss this scene?
Well, it turns out they didn't major is swimming in this scene much like she does in the original only the original brings up
How dangerous it is for cybernetic humans to go deep in the water like this because you know
They're made of heavy machinery, but this movie doesn't mention it once since this scenes compress so much
It feels like it's in gif format. So
CinemaSins did see that scene
They must have in order to use it to criticize the live-action remake and that's pretty shady, isn't it?
This just confirms my suspicions that CinemaSins write their scripts while watching the movie for the first time and don't go back to do
Any editing when the movie provides them with additional information that proves them wrong at the start of their video for Citizen Kane?
Citizen Kane
They call these gondolas
Viking canoes and then go on to say this
rich guys castle has a drivable par-4 on hole 16 just so he can feel good about himself toward the end of the round a
drivable par-4 at
365 yards
Well that seemed a little off to me
So I went to check and found a page on golf week.com that lists the average PGA Tour driving distances for recent years
And they have never averaged over 300 yards and they're professional golfers. So is this a drivable par-4?
Well, maybe for about 30 people on the planet
But that's it and I'd like to thank CinemaSins for getting two obvious things wrong in the first minute of their video about Citizen Kane
So that I didn't have to force myself to watch the rest of it from Citizen Kane to the Lego Batman movie now
This is where the movie loses me and starts to just be noise
tossing in the Wicked Witch from Wizard of Oz Sauron Bremlins agents from the matrix King Kong Voldemort Daleks Daleks
Daleks
What's that? Oh, it's a day look isn't it?
incredible
In their video about blade they criticized the distance between the bite marks of the quotes vampire incisors
But vampires are usually depicted not with sharp incisors, but with sharp canines as indeed
They are in blade
That's a canine right there in their video for the jungle book remake CinemaSins call Shere Khan a quote
African tiger, which is odd both because the jungle book is set in India and African tigers don't exist
CinemaSins still don't know too much about animals. I see let's do a few more animal examples here
Starting with their video for Saw 2 where they say that this person is wearing a horse mask
That's a horse snout there. I guess and in their video for Pocahontas
They call this raccoon a rodent but raccoons aren't rodents in finding Dory
They think that the octopus characters camouflage automatically blends in with the background
But this is not the case in
Reality the mimic octopus for example is able to control its camouflage ability at will not only to blend in with its surroundings
But also to mimic other animals and in their video for the movie split they call these mice
Gerbils so where does one learn about animals because CinemaSins need to go and be there in their video for
Shrek they say that the DreamWorks logo has two letter E's in it
And I'm not too sure about this to be honest
I mean I I see the first one sure between the R and the a there and with them on that but after that
I'm lost I'm afraid in how to train your dragon to they refer to a character called Doba
However, there isn't a character called Doba in this movie
There's a character called gober, so I'd guess they meant him is probably a safe bet
Similar to that in Jack Reacher they refer to a character named Stacy
However, there is no character called Stacy in Jack Reacher
Who is Stacy CinemaSins? I have no idea
Watch the following sin from Captain America Civil War. What was her name again?
The Loras you called her Doc. Steve remembers the name of some random redhead buck
He tried to impress more than 70 years ago. How can Captain America remember things that happened 70 years ago?
well
If you remember CinemaSins
Captain America fell into a coma sometime in the Second World War and woke up in the present day so for him
Consciously, it's a relatively recent event
Let's do another superhero one this from early in their video for Batman vs Superman
Dawn of Justice all it takes to get the most precious element on earth is a couple of free divers with a motorboat and a
Dream is it ever explained how this Kryptonian vessel full of kryptonite crash-landed in the Indian fucking ocean
So that's some people finding kryptonite in the Indian Ocean there, that's odd, isn't it? Where did that come from?
Well, if you recall CinemaSins, there was a movie called Man of Steel
Which I know you've seen because you did a video about it in which the plan of the antagonist in that movie was to
Terraform the earth into a new Krypton using a large terraforming machine
Located above the Indian Ocean and that's how the kryptonite got there
It was the big kryptonian terraforming machine from the previous movie in the series and there's even an establishing shot of it earlier in the movie
And CinemaSins used that in their video
Look at this following nonsense from their video about Gone Girl the morning of what the morning of what? Yeah
Yeah, we know it means this is the morning of her disappearance, but won't her disappearance. Tell us that the morning of what?
the morning of July 5th
It says it right there on the screen
Next movie, let's do The Conjuring 2
So, okay at the start of this movie a character relives the events of November 13th
1974 when Ronald DeFeo jr. Shot and killed six members of his family in Amityville
CinemaSins criticized the movie for showing the family sleeping through the gunshots
But this is actually faithful to the account of the case
Police were puzzled by the fact that nobody appeared to have gotten out of bed to investigate the gunshots
As all the victims were found face down in bed, so plus one to the movie for accuracy
I guess but that's not what I want to talk about here
I want to talk about this in movie proves Vera Farmiga has a way better imaginary dream shotgun than you do a dream
Shotgun. Hey, well, you see the murders were actually carried out with a lever action rifle
Not a shotgun and is that unfair of me, you know criticizing CinemaSins for not recognizing an invisible gun
Well, no because later in that scene the character
Experiencing the vision walks in front of a mirror and the rifle is briefly visible
and I know CinemaSins saw it because they featured it in a sin, so
Near in their video about I am legend CinemaSins say the following the viral zombie apocalypse somehow
Destroyed two-thirds of all the most famous bridges in New York. The bridges were destroyed
Somehow I wonder how any ideas movie
...
That's right, the military destroyed the bridges. How did CinemaSins miss that?
Well, they give the movie a sin for having the broken bridges at about 25 minutes into the movie and the bridges aren't shown
Being blown up until a flashback that happens over 30 minutes later
CinemaSins just didn't go back to edit the bridge sin out when they were shown to be wrong
Because they're lazy and their videos are bad. This next sin is from their video for the movie Krampus
Back when Howard handed Tom this gun
He didn't give him any more ammo and when Howard got attacked by the gopher from Caddyshack Tom fired off two rounds
So where the hell did these extra rounds come from?
Well, that's because revolvers don't auto-eject casings. The cylinder would still look like that even with all of the shots fired
You'd have to eject the casings manually. Now, here's an annoying one from their video for John Wick
Every umbrella at a funeral is black cliche and this is something they're repeating their video for Justice League
Flashpoint Paradox. Now depicting umbrellas at a funeral being black isn't a cliche
It's an accurate representation of a behavior that actually happens in reality and this worries me a little
it makes me think the CinemaSins guys have been turning up to funerals with like
This and not understanding that that is generally considered inappropriate
Anyway, let's move on. Now CinemaSins have previously taken some heat for their assertion that there is no gravity in space
And in their video about the animated Transformers movie, they repeat that mistake
Sarcastically saying this is how gravity works in space kids
When the character Unicron drops another character into their mouth. The thing here though
Is that Unicron is the size of a planet?
So that's exactly how gravity quote
Works because if the character has the mass of a planet then it will attract other objects of mass in the same manner as a
planet
CinemaSins seem to think there's some sort of difference
Gravitationally speaking between being quote in space and the inferred opposite state not in space
Whatever that means but no we're in space now
CinemaSins all the time as far as gravity is concerned. Anyway, the earth doesn't like
Generate gravity for us or something
These guys need to go and read their Albert Einstein
Kind of Logan to carry professor X to his bed for some rest and I'd be calling by this imagery if he wasn't also leaving
The wheelchair so far away from the bed is to render Charles immobile until further human assistance arrives
So why would Logan leave the chair so far from the bed instead of moving it closer? That's rather mean, isn't it?
Anything to say for yourself movie?
Forces forces glad you're not in that business anymore. They don't want me. They want you. Oh
Look at that
He does move it closer and you can even see it closer to the bed in the CinemaSins video a few sins later
Shameful stuff there their video about the movie in time is quite droll
The second sin in that video is complaining about how the movie never explains its premise and the third sin in that video is complaining
about the movie
Overexplaining itself fire an expositional monologue that gives away the conceit now the conceit of that movie by the way
It's that people stop aging at 25 and then use remaining lifetime as a currency
So you have poor people with only a few hours on the clock and rich people with hundreds of years, you know
You get it. Now. I mention it here because CinemaSins later give the movie a sin for the characters being
motivated by currency and
Yes, I'd imagine the ticking death clocks they have in their arms that will kill them when they run out of time would be
Pretty big motivators actually in their video for the movie the purge election year
CinemaSins are surprised to see somebody stab through a bulletproof vest and this is a mistake. They repeat in their video for the rock
Now the thing about bulletproof vests is they're bulletproof
What you'd wear to protect against knives is a stab proof vest and they're different things designed and constructed in different ways for different
purposes
Bulletproof vests are built to disperse the kinetic energy of a projectile
Throughout the material and aren't really built to stop something sharp and pointed that can pierce through the material
The more, you know, hey in their video for I robot
they think that the characters are driving a hover car and give the movie a sin when they hear the wheels screech on the ground and
But it's actually a prototype car with spherical wheels and not a hover car their video for the movie
Moana is pretty offensive at several points
CinemaSins refusal to do any research or look anything up comes off really badly
When they're watching a movie based on the mythology and culture of a people at CinemaSins have no idea about
For example, they give the movie a sin for featuring a fish hook constellation
Which they call fictional but in reality is an actual Polynesian constellation
Better recognized in the West as the tail of the constellation Scorpio
They also give the movie a sin for featuring this thing which is a Polynesian slit drum
Which CinemaSins say looks nothing like a drum
Apparently they were expecting one of these in the ancient cave or something
Watch the following sin from their video about the movie battle Los Angeles
First off can you be a little more specific wouldn't you want to know the exact time left before the rescue helicopter arrives?
Also ten minutes ago random marine number four yelled
So I'd synchronize those swatches if I were you now the mistake CinemaSins made there was that the soldier was actually shouting
25 meters not 25 minutes to indicate distance and not time
So that explains that supposed discrepancy there in their video for now you see me too. They make a rather funny mistake
This is what we've been waiting for now
It's time to get the work since when do the world's best magicians blindly sign up to be basically MacGyver going after wrongdoers and corporate
Stooges also
Why are they all shining their flashlights on these blueprints in the shot as though flashlight activated blueprints are an actual thing?
You see those aren't flashlights. They're black lights
They're revealing something that was drawn in ink that only shows up under a black light
There's also this sin from later in the movie. This is my twin brother chase
What the actual movie also character has a twin brother or any kind of sibling that they never mentioned before?
So has that character's brother never been mentioned before?
Well about half an hour into the previous movie in that series
This is said two TV specials slowly days then your brother slash manager disappeared with all your hard-earned money
Did you research?
So that character's brother was mentioned before hardy-ha
Similar to this sin is the following one from their video about home alone. Why do the McAllisters have a doggy door?
There's no mention of a dog or cat throughout this entire movie
Is it sole purpose shooting bad guys in the crotch with bb's no mention of a dog throughout the entire movie?
However two minutes into the movie this happens
Let's do another similar one from the movie trolls
I'll just get my worthless scullery made to get another place setting ready for the lovely lady
glitter sparkles
Crystal only introduced Bridget as his plus one
So the only way chef could know her name is if the screenwriters were committed to seeing Christine Baranski chew the hell out of this
So, how did this character know this character's name when they weren't introduced
Well ten seconds previously in the movie this happens meet the lovely lady glitter sparkles
So what happened to their cinema sins was it so hard to find things to criticize about
Trolls that you had to lie about something that just happened in the movie. I don't know
Take the gloves off sugar Ray that's like a 30 year old boxing reference at this point
This is movie taking place in the 70s
Or is it just a dated boxing reference worst thing is the movie will never answer this question
So what time period is the nutjob set?
Apparently the movie never answers this question
Well, we as viewers can infer the general time period of the movie from several contextual clues
For example the opening of the movie shows these old-fashioned cars driving on the roads
And there's this guy wearing suspenders and a flat cap
There's this 50s mobster looking guy sitting on a bench this newspaper that displays the date as October 21st
1959 and combined from all these contextual hints. I'm able to estimate the general date that the movie set as
October 21st
1959 the movie will never answer this question
My foot cinema sins were confused there by the sugar Ray reference probably mistaking it to mean sugar Ray Leonard
Who was only three years old in 1959 and thus probably not yet a well-known boxer
More likely though the characters were referencing sugar Ray Robinson who was a boxer active throughout the 1950s
Some more time period shenanigans now first from their video about Pirates of the Caribbean on
Stranger Tides which cinema sins say takes place in the late 17th century
The movie is actually set in 1750 which isn't in the 17th century
Just trust me
And I've got no clue where cinema sins got the late part from I think that was just a random guess really in their video
For the movie King Arthur they refer to a medieval battle happening
even though the movies set during the late Roman occupation of Britain making medieval an
Incorrect descriptor there. They also elsewhere refer to England's army
Even though England didn't even exist at that point and watch the following sin from their video about Alice through the looking-glass
In Hollywood doctors do not squirt out part of the medicine to fucking test if a syringe is working how you ever got started on
This troop I will never know but not get the off rather
Angry about syringes that so yes doctors don't squirt out a bit of the medicine in order to test if the syringe is working
But they do squirt out a bit of the medicine to ensure there are no air bubbles in the syringe
Injecting air into someone can be very dangerous
So what they do is tap the syringe a few times and then squirt a bit out to force any air out of the syringe
before use
Isn't learning fun watch the following sin from Fantastic Beasts and where to find them
Legilimens yeah, but I always have trouble with your kind Brits
That's British also
Legilimens is someone who can read minds someone that was never once introduced in the entire world of Harry Potter before now
So this Legilimens thing is something that was never introduced in the entire world of Harry Potter
Well that's not true because it's in the books for a start
But maybe CinemaSins just meant the movies and so has it been mentioned in the movies before
Well if we watch Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince
That's right Snape says it let's take a look at a sin from their video about the movie Central Intelligence
It's 6 p.m.. And they're in the Eastern time zone
So there's no way there's a football game on unless this bar is showing reruns because the NFL never plays games that start at 6 p.m.
Eastern
Okay, so there's a lot wrong with this and so the NFL never plays games that start at 6 p.m.. Eastern
Well the first problem here is that there's nothing in the movie to indicate that this game has just started
It could be a game that started earlier
And is still playing at the next problem here is if we do a little zoom and enhance
We can make out the team logo on the field which is this
The Tiger Eye logo of the team the LSU Tigers which is a college team and thus wouldn't be playing in an NFL game anyway
So this sin is wrong twice in two completely different ways well done CinemaSins in their video for the movie
Don't Breathe they tried a character for urinating at a crime scene for leaving his DNA there
Although actually urine doesn't contain DNA that's a fun biology factor for you there
in their video for Toy Story 3
They spell the character Sid's name wrong and refer to him as a serial killer
And not noticing that Sid is actually featured in the movie as a garbage man also from this movie is the following sin
Then why did you take it out in the first place also didn't previous movie show us your organs still work even when not attached
So why not just look through that eye to figure out where it is, right?
Yeah, why didn't she just look through the eye to find where it was that I'd be clever wouldn't it oh wait
She does do that in blade 2 they incorrectly refers to the mutated vampires as
Creepers when they're actually called Reapers in the ring too. They think the town the characters move to Astoria
It's in Washington and when it's actually in Oregon in
Ghostbusters they refer to this thing as a bicycle, but it isn't
In Hellboy they're confused when a character pulls the pins on two grenades
But throws them one at a time and not understanding how grenades work
I guess pulling the pin doesn't actually do anything by itself the pin is just there to hold the strike lever in place
It's releasing this lever that causes the grenade to explode after a short delay
You can actually put the pin back in a grenade safely assuming the leaf has been held down the whole time
Although I'd advise against trying it in that video for unbreakable
They give the movie a sin for having train seats that face backwards as well as forwards
I don't know. Why is that an unusual thing in the States like over here pretty much all the trains
I like that in their video for suicide squad they claim the character dr. Moon explored a cave featured earlier by herself
But if you watch the movie you can see someone else with her in that flashback implying there were other people with her on the
Trip unless that person is just someone she bumped into in passing in the middle of a jungle which while possible would be kind of weird
In the original planet of the Apes
There's a scene where the Apes flush some humans out of a cornfield using sticks and when cinema sins watch it
They think the Apes are cutting the corn down
With blunt sticks
Above course, they're not they're just flushing people out
I mean you can obviously see they're not cutting down the corn
So I haven't got a clue what cinema sins were on about here in their video for the movie contact
They mock the appearance of this nebula, but that's actually a real nebula. It's called the pillars of creation
They also say that the moon is quote nowhere near that size relative to the earth
But without a reference for where the camera is located here
That's a silly statement
After all, if you're very close to the moon, it would appear larger than the earth
You'd need to know exactly where the camera was located in order to make that judgment
Let's watch a sin from their video about the movie kung fu panda free
If no one could find you pink on the down I've got this but yeah, he's right
So let's watch the clip from the movie to give us a little bit more context here
Wow
But how did you know where I was I received a message that led me here
How could you receive a message if no one could find you sounds suspicious to me. So, okay
How did pose biological father get a message telling him where Poe was if he lives in a secret village any ideas movie?
No, it was a message from the universe
That's grown
As I hope you would when I sent the message to your father, huh, you sent the universe mail, whoa
Yes
But again, that's a reveal from the end of the movie and cinema sins couldn't be bothered going back to correct their earlier mistake
Let's watch a sin from their video about the
2017 live-action remake of beauty and the Beast since this movie suffers from the exact issue about the castle being in plain sight
I'll just repeat the same sin
I gave the last movie the Beast has only been secretly beasting for 10 years
But Maurice is somehow unaware of this very nearby castle
Also, it's super weird that the villagers wouldn't be at all disturbed that the prince of the very nearby castle hasn't been seen or heard
From in years and even if this prince is habitually reclusive you'd think that someone would know one of the 300 live-in servants and wonder
Where they are, right, right?
No, I wouldn't think that was weird because I watched the movie as days bled into years
The prince and his servants were forgotten by the world
For the Enchantress had erased all memory of them from the minds of the people they loved
Now that clip occurs during the opening narration. So how did cinema sins missed that?
Well, check this out for the Enchantress had erased all memory of them from the minds of the people they loved
That's an excellent attempt to close a plot hole opened by the animated movie
But it leaves me with a whole new set of questions. Yeah, that's right. They gave it a sin
So what happened here then?
You know at some point between writing this sin and the one from later in the video cinema sins somehow forgot the details of the
Opening narration that they watched, you know
That or these videos are a collaborative effort written by several people who don't talk to each other or something
Let's watch a sin from their video about Star Wars the Clone Wars
Crime Lord Jabba the Hudson has been kidnapped by a rival band of pirates. Excuse me. What his son
Are you serious funny? We're only hearing about this guy just now
This warlord reaches out to the federal government to help him find his captured son instead of simply taking matters into his own hands and
Sending a bunch of bounty hunters to do it
So why didn't Jabba the Hutt hire some bounty hunters to find his son that seems like the sort of thing he'd do, right?
Well 15 minutes into the movie this happens. Yes commander
We've discovered that Jabba the Hutt has also hired bounty hunters to track down his son
It turns out Jabba did hire some bounty hunters cinema sins just lied about it in their video for the movie sing
They wonder if the shrimp act need a handler to push their tank around but later when they're dismissed from the show
We see that they do in fact have a handler with them in their video for Star Trek Beyond
They give the movie a sin because the alien planet has air that humans can breathe. What a coincidence, eh?
What they missed was this scene 18 minutes into the movie
approaching ultimate
Class M planet now an M class planet
There is the Star Trek universe's designation for a planet suitable for human life
And now you might say well that's still an unlikely narrative convenience, isn't it?
Even if they did establish it earlier in the story and you would nearly be right except for the fact that the antagonist is later
Revealed to actually be a human Starfleet captain played by Idris Elba who crash-landed on that planet long ago
and
Thus the planet would have to be able to support human life or he would have died when he crashed and none of the events
Of the film would have taken place
So there now do you want to see possibly the worst cinema sin I have ever encountered
This really gets me this one from their video about the movie too fast too furious
If slapjack is only going over 100 then seconds later Brian hits the nos and is blasting past 160
How is slapjack not eating Brian's dust, right? So this is
annoying
So the characters slapjack and Brian are engaged in some sort of illegal
Street race and though both cars appear to be going at a similar speed
When we see close-ups of their speedometer as we see that Brian is doing 160
Whereas slapjack is doing about a hundred
What a silly movie mistake you might think if you were some sort of utter
Buffoon who had never seen a car you see Brian's speedometer is in kilometers per hour
That's why it says 160
Slapjack's speedometer on the other hand is primarily in miles per hour. So it shows him doing 100. But what are these other?
Smaller numbers in red on the inside there
Well, that's the speed of slapjacks car in kilometers per hour. And would you look at that?
He's doing about 160 which is how fast Brian is going and that's why the cars appear to be going the same
goddamn speed
At cinema sins don't seem to have much of a clue when it comes to cars in their video for the movie
Jason Bourne, they incorrectly identify this Dodge Charger as a Dodge Challenger
And in their video for Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles out of the shadows
They jokingly expect this SRT to turn into bumblebee
Except of course, we all know that bumblebee is a Camaro
Let's take a look at a sin from their video about the movie angry birds
movie has mine birds because it's super funny and you just didn't realize it
Is going on here is he in school and if so, why is he hireable as a clown? Why is he painting?
Why was there a mime hanging out a second ago? Where the fuck is this village?
This is the one time I'd welcome a little fucking narration. So what's going on here then?
Well, this section of the movie is actually a montage of various scenes from the main characters life showing situations in which he's been
Angry, I guess and this particular scene is a flashback to his time in school
I mean, here's how he looked just five seconds ago
and then it cuts to him in school and he looks like this a little kid version of himself and
I guess the filmmakers trusted in the ability of their audience to recognize a series of flashbacks and not try to
Interpret it as a linear narrative in which the character rapidly changes age appearance and location
But I guess they didn't account for the cinema sins guys who need to be led by the hand through absolutely everything
Let's watch the first few sins from their video about the movie
Warcraft there has been a war between orcs and humans for as long as can be remembered or as long as it's been since Tolkien
Created the orcs were blatantly stealing for this game movie also narration
But there was once a time when we did not even know who our enemy was
We just said you've been fighting with humans as long as you can remember
So, how do you remember the time before that when you didn't even know your enemy but in the beginning?
How could we have known know what you've given me three statements so far two about knowing one about wondering how you could have known
And already I think I see the problem with this movie
Okay
So there's a few problems here
Firstly the orc voiceover says we've been fighting humans as long as we can remember
But there was once a time when we did not know who our enemy was now, that's not actually a contradiction
Knowledge of the existence of a time before your memory begins does not mean you personally remember it
Just that you know about it for example
I have knowledge of the existence of ancient Rome, but that doesn't mean I personally remember it does it?
Secondly here where cinema sins say known what you've given me three statements so far etc
That's not true cinema sins cut a line out of the opening narration here
Let's have a listen, but there was once a time when we did not even know who our enemy was
So the following line, but in the beginning how could we have known is referring to this previous line about what the green fell magic did to them
Cinema sins just cut that line out to make the narration seem worse than it actually is I mean
It's still pretty bad, so I don't know why cinema sins bothered to misrepresent it really
But they did in the Lego movie
They point out this Lego bike and say the minifigures couldn't ride it because it only has one stud at the back
But actually they can ride those they stand over the middle. That's not a seat back there
That's just a rear wheel guard in Die Hard 2. There's the following sin recalibrate sea level recalibrate sea level
Don't the planes have independent meters and gauges that are not reliant upon control towers to determine how far they are up in the air
No, actually one of the purposes of the control tower is to transmit to the planes a code based on atmospheric pressure
That the planes need to calculate their altitude above sea level not all planes can do that independently
Here's a fun one next it
Do you know how cinema sins like to do this in case you confused it for Bruce go, Kentucky?
You know hardy ha we obviously know the country who would need to be told what country we were in
You know certainly not us at cinema sins
Well, that's in there is from their video about x-men apocalypse, and now here's a sin from later in the video
Because someone decided to wake up apocalypse right now an earthquake in Egypt was felt all the way to Germany they think they're in Germany
Even with the word Poland appearing on the screen in the movie. They still got the country wrong
They also think that Andalusia is a city in Spain instead of a region in Spain and they confuse Goa India with the non-existent
Gao India, so we'll just add geography to the list of things cinema sins doesn't understand alongside animals
history cars guns
Movies and whatever else oh this video is getting on a bit isn't it and let's double time a few minor errors here
In peach dragon they type 3 minutes and 15 minutes instead of 3 minutes and 15 seconds
They here type spirit instead of spirit
They forget the space between in and 15 in the title of their video for the boss, baby
They leave out the word to in this sentence from there the mummy returns video
everything wrong with Deadpool in 16 minutes
Everything wrong with Deadpool in 15 minutes in the secret life of pets
They use the wrong ending template for the video the one from their music sins channel a mistake
They repeat several times in other videos before correcting it
I mean I could keep going this video contains just a portion of the mistakes
I found watching through cinema sins offerings from the past year. I've got 10 a4 pages filled with this
Both sides this video could have been three times as long
Easily, but I think I should probably arbitrarily stop here
So what have we learned today?
Well, nothing new the cinema sin still hasn't improved at all if anything they've gotten worse
And they're still incapable of following along with even the simplest stories unless they're held by the hand the whole time with on-screen text and narration
Which they'll then complain about anyway, and then probably forget
They'll still lie about and misrepresent the content of movies in order to provide their audience with an unearned smug feeling of superiority
Over something and they still don't know anything
At all about anything and the worst of all they're not funny
The cinema sins YouTube channel is probably the only human creation to which I would deny the title art
Thanks a lot for watching everyone if you'd like to see more videos like this
Well, don't support me on on patreon. I'm not gonna be making more videos like this. I mean once a year max
Every cinema sins video is a Gordian knot of wrongness and untangling it costs a part of your soul
Thanks to all my patrons anyway, I mean I couldn't continue to do this without them
So I should probably be blaming them here rather than thanking them thinking about it
How dare you support me?
Honestly, I take it as an insult. I'm supported in this
Anyway see you next year, I guess and we'll look at everything they got wrong between now and then bye