Okay, happy spring!
Hi!
Let's review, like, a very Halloween-y thing.
Because that makes sense.
Yeah.
A peculiar lemon...
I don't think it's peculiar, that's just sad.
Yeah, I tried.
Need to take a class on, like, the garnishing of drinks.
So yeah, we looked for a peculiar cocktail
to go with
our book that we are discussing
this week, Mrs. Peregrine's Home
for Peculiar Children by Ransom Riggs.
And, uh...
Nella went and found one with vinegar.
Yeah. A vinegar gin martini.
Yeah, so it includes
Earl Grey tea, honey,
um...
balsamic vinegar, your really fancy stuff
that's quite expensive.
I got that for Christmas, like, two years ago.
So I think that might, you know, turn the tide towards us.
A little splash of lemon, and...
Yeah, this could be, like, those pickleback things.
Maybe this could work.
I think it could.
Okay, it works.
Hey, it works!
I think this would not work without the ancient balsamic.
Yeah, this is...
A whole new world of possibilities just opened up before my eye.
Yeah, this is like...
Just like in the book!
Yeah, no, this is like the book.
It's peculiar, but it works.
So we're trying to, from here on out,
Siskel and Ebert this thing to, uh...
We don't discuss it before.
Um...
So whatever our guns are,
we're gonna stick to them, and then maybe
hugging and crying will happen, maybe screaming and fighting.
Who knows?
But before we get started on Peregrine,
we're going to announce our next one
based on your suggestions.
We asked for an adult one
with minimal to no romance,
so we went with, uh...
This is not library copy.
Shades of Grey by
Jasper Faford.
I'm pretty sure that's just Ford.
This one seems to be an adult dystopian novel,
so I think that'll be quite interesting
to contrast with the wide, wide world
of YA dystopia, so thanks for that.
Um...
You poor bastard. You published right before
Shades of Grey.
I know, this came out in 2009.
You poor bastard.
Thank you for your suggestions.
Keep on making them.
As for next week, I guess, you know,
whatever. Preferably female protagonist.
Yeah.
Like, let's see if we can do
female protagonist, no love interest,
or minimal if we must.
We shall see.
Can you show me a unicorn?
I'd like a fairy in a jar that can grant wishes.
Peregrine's Home for
Peculiar Children, which came out a couple years ago
by Ransom Riggs.
As far as I can tell, that is
his real name.
He was just meant to be a writer.
And also,
an alma mater of the University of Southern California
School of Film and Television Graduate School.
So, gotta represent.
One of yours. Yeah, he's one of ours.
He's one of ours, only he actually graduated.
Um, I will say this.
This book is a perfect example
of why, if you write a prologue,
you should really get rid of it.
Yeah. Like, write it for your own
pleasure, but when you actually go to publish it,
you can just really get rid of it.
No book really needs a prologue.
I think for both of us, it kind of, like, put up the, uh,
uh-oh.
But luckily,
it improved vastly after the prologue.
Okay.
So, Nella, what did you think of
Miss Peregrine's Home for Peculiar
Children? Well, on the whole,
I did enjoy it.
I...
I enjoyed the, uh,
the gimmick of the
pictures included.
Sometimes I definitely did feel a little forced.
But, like, someone's like,
we have to go, like,
hold on, I have a picture for that.
And they, like, go get it, like, in the middle of, like,
an action scene. Like, it happened
several times. Yeah.
So, like, in case you haven't read it, and we
won't spoil it too much,
the big gimmick of this book is
that there are pictures in it.
And the pictures are
pictures that he found from actual collections.
Like, he cites them at the end here.
And, uh, so these pictures
are, like, um,
basically what the book is
written around.
Yeah, on the whole, I liked it. Uh, it definitely
Oh, boy, the sequel fodder.
I'm really getting surprised by these books where they have such
obvious, and then the sequel
ending. Um...
And then we went off for more
adventures. Yeah. It took me a little bit to
get really into it and start
liking where it was going, because
the main character, when I was taking notes as I was
going, in the first four percent
of the book, all my notes consisted
of, oh my god, I hate this protagonist.
Eat a dick.
Do you even understand what Realtale is?
Like, he's very
sheltered,
and he's a privileged white boy.
But I think that works, like,
because he's a privileged white boy. It ends up working, yeah.
But in the very beginning, I just really
wanted to put it down, because he was just
so...
so, like... Teenage boy.
Teenage boy.
I thought this was great.
Like, I really... I
thought it was great, except for the gimmick.
I...
I mean, I thought this was, like, a great, like,
you know,
writing prompt.
Like, you could... Like, this was what
inspired me, but, like,
it really kind of got distracting.
But whenever it was just, like, we'd be
having a scene, putting along, and all of a sudden...
Someone has to go get a picture to refer to.
A picture has to be described.
I remembered the picture, or, you know,
and then someone else, like,
hold on! I got a picture for that!
But honestly, like,
I thought this book was
I think way more messed up
than it was intended to be.
But in a good way.
Well, it definitely had that
Neverland is a terrible place.
Yeah, it had unfortunate implications, but it didn't shy away
from them. Like, the fact that
basically, like, whenever he does find
the peculiar children about halfway through the book,
they are existing in this
arrested development type.
Like, they are
in their 90s, but they're still mentally
children.
Very much a fairy
world entrapment going
on, where they can't escape
it at this point.
So that's really
fascinating to me, because
you can never leave. It's paradise,
but you can never leave, sort of thing.
Here's our basic setup. This kid,
our main character, Jacob,
witnesses a terrible thing. He witnesses
the murder slash
accidental death, maybe, of his
grandfather. And this
sends him on a search for truth,
which eventually leads him to this place his grandfather
grew up, the home for peculiar children.
And basically,
the first few chapters are this character
dealing with literal PTSD.
Like, he's
in therapy. He's going through
all these motions of trying to cope with what
he saw, or what he thinks he saw.
And eventually, because
he's super rich, he can whimsically
go on this trip to Wales to find
this place that his grandfather
always talked about.
I think what I really liked about it,
because I basically decided
about halfway through the book, that this was all in his head.
Which is completely
up to, because it kind of had this
Pan's Labyrinth-y feeling of
this is a coping mechanism.
This story he is concocting
is a coping mechanism for this real life
horrible thing, because of
the things that his father
eventually revealed to him about his grandfather.
Maybe his grandfather wasn't such a perfect guy.
Maybe he did things to the family
that weren't so great.
And maybe you put him on a pedestal.
And I really related to that, because I think
that is part of growing up, is realizing
that your parents and grandparents aren't
like these perfect, infallible
beings. They are,
you know...
Personally, my grandfather,
like, getting into
sad, frowny time territory.
When my grandmother died,
there was all this bitterness in the
family, and I basically found out
that my grandfather, you know,
before I was born, was not a stand-up
person. He was actually kind of a bad guy.
And I basically decided to
unperson him. And for the last seven years of his
life, I didn't speak to him. I was
just like, gone.
And I think that's interesting.
Whenever he finds out these things about his
grandfather, and you can
read it either as, his grandfather
was totally innocent, or
he comes up with this really elaborate
story to frame the innocence
of his grandfather. And I feel
like you could read it to where it really goes either way,
because of the way he sort of
demonizes, like, his parents
not believing him, and like,
the mental health system doesn't believe him,
and nobody believes me, and I'm,
you know, I'm special.
Well, to me, it's also... I mean, that theory to me
works just because he's
so
quick to feel
like he has nothing left for him back in
the real world. Yeah.
As teenagers are wont to do.
Like, no, I can't possibly
go back. There's nothing for me.
Yeah! Like, oh,
16!
No, I want to run away and live in Neverland forever.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe.
Maybe that makes it illusional. It's all in his
head. It makes that thing work even better, because he is older,
and it is, like... Yeah.
It's not just, like, kid's imagination, like, no, you are mentally
unbalanced. Yeah, like, you know, he cray.
Or maybe not. Maybe it's all real.
But I feel like it's just based
purely on, like, the way that
the things
that are answered, like these
uncomfortable truths about reality that we
as adults all have to come to terms with sooner
or later. Yeah. This protagonist
kind of looks at them and goes, nope!
Kill your children. I'm
special. I don't know. I read it as that the world
he uncovers is real.
Mm-hmm. I took it for face value,
which still ended up
metaphor for real
life. Like, holo-gast.
God, the holo-gast. The holo-gast.
The holo-gast is terrible.
Not the holo-gast. Why did you use that word?
Don't make puns about the holocaust.
Yeah, it's like, if holocaust is actually in your
book, maybe lay off the holocaust
puns. Just a little bit.
I don't even know if you were realizing you were
making a pun about a holocaust,
but it's really important. I think we probably did.
At least it's a play on words.
Whatever. No.
Someone had to bring it! No, I'm sure it was
intentional.
Okay. The only real, because
I really like the characters. I like the way that the
you know, I like the quirky
children. They were all really interesting. They
weren't like typical boring child characters.
Yeah. They had a purpose.
The only thing that really bugged me was like
the end kind of went way too
fast, and it was kind of
honestly dragged.
And also, the main
the villain
and his, like, it's really hard.
I speak from experience. When you have a point of view
character, and your
audience needs to know the villain's motivation,
it is really hard
to not go into, you got
me monologuing, you sly
dog. But, oh my
god.
Again?
God damn it.
He got him monologuing quick.
Let's pull the caper
while he's monologuing.
I was actually going through it like
there's a very slow
burn to the sudden
ending explosion.
Well, it is very like nothing, nothing, nothing,
nothing, nothing, nothing. Whee!
Yeah. And then everything
falls apart really quick.
But I think that lends a lot
of credence to my theory. Like, when you
find out the bad guy and what his
motivations are, you know,
it's like, yeah, I was totally right.
I was totally right about this all being
in his head. And he's insane.
And then the end is like, he's dead.
Or something.
Or he's like, or it's gonna
like, but anyway, yeah.
I think, you know, this would make a great, like,
this could, if Tim Burton
does end up making this, this could be like a
return to form for him because it's so perfect.
You know, it would make a great
stop motion. Like, I could see something
in the vein of ParaNorman, you know,
or Coraline. Like, that was my
two points. That was my biggest comparison
reading it. It felt very Coraline.
And I know some people had problems
with that, this idea that like, sort of
monsters is a metaphor for Nazis,
but then there are Nazis, and
it takes place basically during World War II, sort of.
Yeah. So, you're
getting it on both ends, pretty much.
Yeah. But I thought
that worked. I really liked that.
Especially when you take into
consideration that this might completely
be all in his head angle.
You know, when the Nazis
come in, or the
monster Nazis. And then Dumbledore fought Grindelwald.
And I like that Dumbledore was like
a chick, too. I thought that was
great. I was like, our awesome
Dumbledore character is a woman. You never
see that. I know. Yeah, like, I
like Miss Peregrine. I thought she was a little
too, like, I'm
keeping secrets for your own good.
I thought Dumbledore was McGonagall.
Yeah, it's like Dumbledore. Which everyone can get behind.
Yeah, yeah. And I thought it worked.
And I actually,
except for the main love interest, which of course
there is one.
Guesses why! But at least it's like
super background noise.
I liked all the girl characters. It's super awkward, though.
Read it. You'll see what I'm talking about. Yeah, like,
their love is awkward love.
I mean, I dug it, because I liked that
at least it brings up the awkward,
and I was like,
you know, like, that's a really
awkward boner you got there.
I don't know how I feel about this.
This is a frown boner.
I liked Bronwyn, too.
She was so great.
Okay, so anyway,
I wholeheartedly recommend this. I thought it was
great. This is one of my favorite YA books I've read.
I mean, I wasn't wild about
the gimmick or the, like, really hurried
ending, but for the most part, I really liked the
characters. I like how unafraid it was
of its own implications, and
how messed up it was if you consider that it's all
in his head. As reading it,
well, I read it without the
um, it's all in his
head theory. I saw
it as this was really happening, this really is a magical
instance that is
occurring. I also liked that it didn't shy
away from the implications of this world.
Um, they are slightly
horrifying, but they're
explained, which is what I
really liked about it. Um,
so, hey, you know. Except for some of the naming
conventions. Well...Hologast.
I don't...you know me, I'm not really
as big on like...well, aside
from the Hologast.
That didn't bother me until you brought it up now
is all I can think about. Right.
I don't know, I saw it right away.
Takes one of my all-caps down for my all-caps
recommended. But anyway,
for all you folks who recommended this, thank you,
and of course, give us something else
We have some ideas
from our previous
week's comments.
Two weeks from now,
Shades of Grey by Jasper
Ford, and
after that, we will
announce our next one. Again, YA
fairy in a
bottle that grants wishes.
No romance. Let's see if
you can do it.
Unicorn.