Okay.
Why is this hard?
To lift.
Like...
Physically.
No, I think I have to undo this first.
Okay, and then...
Yay!
I blame Lindsay for this.
Well, um...
I... yeah.
This is all her fault.
This came about a few months ago
when on Twitter one day I decided
I was going to
write my own romance novel.
Only it was going to be...
Since there was Twilight with everything.
And this is a really not surprising thing
in young adult literature right now.
The fact that there's
the next big thing, it's Twilight with witches.
And I saw several Twilight with angels.
Fallen angels.
They're always fallen.
Twilight with fairies, right?
Twilight with fairies.
I'm waiting for Twilight with Loch Ness Monsters.
I definitely saw Twilight with werewolves.
Like, where the werewolves were the...
The vampires?
But the thing is, it's many
flavors of the same story
in different gimmicky
paranormal...
Yeah, so I feel like what we've
learned from this
explosion of romance novels
and their popularity
is that you gotta
have a gimmick
and we want in.
Yeah, we want in.
So what is Fifty Shades of Green?
We are crowdsourcing
the next worst
blockbuster paranormal romance novel
and you're gonna help.
I mean, we could probably do it without you, but what would be
the fun in that? Because if we've
gotta do this for the shits and giggles
of it, we wanna document it.
We want to see what
it takes to write the next
Twilight. And it doesn't have to be Twilight
with aliens.
But I want it to be Twilight.
I want it to be Twilight.
I want Twilight with aliens, but if the crowd
wills it so and we find a better idea, then...
But this is the point of
this. We want
to go on a journey of
self-discovery
in the Lovecraftian sense
and we want you
to come with us and we want you to be
our guides. Journey to the
belly of the beast. This is absolutely going
to be a collaborative process.
You, the viewer, gets to vote
on what we're doing and how
we're doing it. So I feel like this
is a good way for us to celebrate our love
of books by imitating
books that we hate.
So how's this gonna work?
The goal here is to actually
crowdsource with the help of
writers like
you
an actual book which we
will then actually shop around
to agents and actually get rejected
and then
probably actually self-publish.
But, you know, it's gonna be...
So you can see the fruits of your labor.
Yeah, we're gonna see the fruits of our labor.
The goal is not to make a deliberately
bad book. The goal is to make
a book that will sell
in a
bad way.
If that makes sense. That doesn't mean it can't
be funny, though. No. It can actually be
ridiculous and hilarious, but you have to
believe it. You have to believe
in the book itself.
The badness will be organic.
I feel like crowdsourcing is just as
viable a method of writing than, say,
publishing your fan fiction with
search-to-replace names.
For the next few weeks, we're going to
talk about different topics
within the
romance genre that has
taken over the world.
And these books that are so inexplicably
popular. We'll definitely be discussing
things like why the characters
are as they are. Plot. What plot?
Genre. Life begins at man.
Life begins at man.
Mousy, woefully
pale. Thin me.
Woefully skinny me.
My porcelain
skin makes me strange
to others.
You can really divvy this process up into
three parts. Part one is the discussion.
Part two is the actual writing. And then part three
is going to be the road to
what is probably going to be self-publication.
But it's the
journey that is important.
We'll definitely be trying
to sell this.
So we're going to start on this next week
where we are going to
talk about genre. We're going to make
some decisions.
What is our gimmick? What is our genre?
And
that's where you'll come in.
We're going to have all sorts of
experimental ways for people to interact.
It's called Twitter.
It's experimental.
The tweet.
So you can of course leave comments
on our website at
ChezApocalypse.com and on our Blip page,
50 Shades of Green. You can also tweet
at us at ChezApocalypse or if you want to
find my old Twitter that I will probably
revive for this project.
Sexy Alien Book.
Which is exactly
what it sounds like.
And we will start making our
decisions.
And we will make
a terrible awesome
or awesomely terrible project.
And remember, the road to madness
is only fun when you bring a friend
down with you. And alcohol.
And alcohol.
Or weed.