Many of our viewers have asked us a very serious question.
What if we made a big pile of bombs and exploded every nuclear weapon in the world all at once?
Strangely enough, we couldn't find a good source to answer this question to our satisfaction.
So we gathered together a few scientists to calculate what would happen and find an answer
to this extremely important scientific problem once and for all.
Currently, there are 15,000 nuclear weapons on Earth. The US and Russia both have around 7,000,
while France, China, the UK, Pakistan, India, Israel and North Korea own around 1,000 between them.
But how much destructive power is this really? Let's try to put these numbers into perspective.
On Earth, there are about 4,500 cities or urban areas with at least 100,000 inhabitants.
Some are bigger than others, so we'll assume that on average, we need three nuclear bombs
to completely wipe out one city. This means we could destroy every single city on planet
Earth with our nuclear arsenal, killing more than 3 billion people, roughly half of humanity,
in an instant. And we'd still have 1,500 nuclear weapons left. Now that's what an expert would call
overkill. So we can say with confidence that we have a lot of nuclear weapons and they can do a
lot of damage. But what if we make a huge pile of all 15,000 bombs and pull the trigger? Let's drop
our nuclear pile in the middle of the Amazon rainforest, just to show nature who's boss.
Our warheads, piled haphazardly, fit into a small warehouse. A typical US warhead has the
power of 200,000 tons of TNT. So 15,000 warheads would be the equivalent of 3 billion tons of TNT.
For scale, this is enough to rebuild the whole island of Manhattan with every building and
skyscraper using stacks of TNT. The closest thing we can compare to the energy gathered here is a
volcano. One of the deadliest volcanic eruptions in recorded history took place in 1883 on the
island of Krakatoa. The eruption was so powerful that 70% of the island and the surrounding
archipelago was destroyed, killing tens of thousands of people. Its effects were felt
around the world for days after the event. Our nuclear pile contains 15 times the energy of the
Krakatoa volcanic eruption. So let's finally push the button. Three, two, one. In a second,
a fireball 50 kilometers across vaporizes everything in its way and creates a blast
wave that flattens 3,000 square kilometers of forest. Every living thing within 250 kilometers
will start to burn. The explosion will be heard literally around the world as the pressure wave
circles the earth tens of times over the next few weeks. Millions of tons of incinerated material
are catapulted into the atmosphere. The mushroom cloud reaches the outer reaches of the stratosphere,
pushing up against space itself. After things have calmed down, a small crater about 10 kilometers
across is left in the center of the worst world fires the planet has seen in millennia,
spreading throughout South America, burning down forests and cities alike. And now the unpleasant
part begins. Extremely radioactive material will kill living things very quickly and a large area
several kilometers around the crater is now uninhabitable, as is everywhere for hundreds
of kilometers downwind. Much of the fallout is carried high into the atmosphere by the mushroom
cloud and carried around the planet. The amount of radioactive material in the environment doubles
worldwide, which still isn't civilization ending, but we may see more cancer for a while. A portion
of the particles will flow to the edge of space for years and cause a nuclear winter that could
lower global temperatures by a few degrees for a few years. This explosion was pretty bad if you're
in South America and especially Brazil. The Amazon rainforest is pretty much history, which is not
great, but human life will go on. Okay, but what if we explode more nuclear weapons? Let's suppose
humanity decided to mine every bit of uranium on earth and build as many nuclear bombs as possible.
At current usage, it's estimated that there are around 35 million tons of uranium in Earth's
crust, enough to power human civilization for over 2000 years or to build millions of nuclear
warheads. For the sake of argument, let's say we create a pile with a yield of 10 billion Hiroshima
bombs, which makes up a cube three kilometers high that contains roughly the energy of the asteroid
impact that ended the age of the dinosaurs 65 million years ago, except it's also nuclear.
Three, two, one. Our pile explodes in a fireball stretching so high into the sky that it's visible
from half of South America with so much power that the ground just splashes like water forming
a crater 100 kilometers across. Bedrock on the scale of whole mountain ranges is vaporized in
an instant while thousands of tons of material is catapulted away with such speed that it's ejected
into space. Some leaves earth forever while most of it comes raining down as hot burning
debris that heats up the atmosphere to oven like temperatures killing most big animals and causing
firestorms all over the world. The Earth's crust rings like a bell struck by global earthquakes
stronger than anything in recorded history decimating cities around the world while
hurricane force winds flatten every single tree in South America and wildfires consume the continent.
The abundance of hydrocarbons in the Amazon burned to form ash are cast into the atmosphere
darting the sky and keeping sunlight from reaching the surface dropping temperatures to near freezing
worldwide. The ensuing global winter may last for decades and results in the extinction of every
large animal species, humans included. We could also mention that every corner of the planet is
covered with radioactive fallout but at this point it doesn't matter that much anymore. This is
humanity's extinction event. The astronauts aboard the International Space Station get to enjoy a
great view for a while but it's not unlikely that the spray of rocks blast into orbit will destroy
the station. Those lucky enough to be in bunkers or in submarines deep below the ocean surface may
survive the longest before they exhaust their food supplies and have to venture out for more.
They'll find the world a charred, freezing, radioactive wasteland. The planet itself doesn't
care at all. After just a few million years, the wounds of the explosions have healed and life is
thriving, arguably even more so than when humans were around. If intelligent life emerges again,
it might be able to work out what happened. When they study geology, they'll find a bizarre and
very thin layer of rock covering the entire world enriched in radioactive elements like uranium and
the other nasty things it decays to, mixed with rare earth metals and plastics that humans used.
They would probably be very, very confused. Videos like this one take well over 1,200
hours to finish. Over the years, we put more and more effort into research, conversations
with experts, illustration and animation, sound design and fact-checking. For this video,
we put a lot of extra work into our sources document. You can read how we got to the
information in the video, what our experts thought about it, where they disagreed with
each other. We can take the time to do this because of you, our viewers. Because you watch
and share our videos, buy our posters and support us on patreon.com. If you like what we're doing,
please consider becoming a patron or get one of the nice things we made with love. Thank you for
watching.