The Sun. Smooth and round and peaceful. Except when it suddenly vomits radiation and plasma
in random directions. These solar flares and Coronal Mass Ejections, or CMEs, can hit Earth
and have serious consequences for humanity. How exactly do they work, how bad could they
be, and can we prepare for them? While the Sun seems pretty solid, it's actually
like a very hot ocean. So hot that it rips atoms into electrons and nuclei, all flowing
around each other in a plasma. This plasma is pushed around and shaped by the Sun's
magnetic field, similar to how the Sun's gravitational field reaches out to the planets
and shapes their orbits. But magnetism is very different from gravity. Magnetism is
one part of a dual force, electromagnetism. Electricity creates magnetic fields, and magnetic
fields create electricity. On the Sun, the plasma, made of electrically charged protons
and electrons, creates a magnetic field as they move, and this magnetic field then shapes
the flow of particles. They're stuck in a dynamic feedback loop called a dynamo, which
keeps the Sun's magnetic field alive. This magnetic field stores enormous amounts of
energy and leaks out over the solar system. It carries with it a constant trickle of solar
plasma like a light rain known as the solar wind, creating a sort of space weather. But
it isn't always calm and smooth. As the Sun's plasma churns and flows around itself, its
magnetic field gets all kinked and twisted. This creates magnetic knots that build up
enormous amounts of energy. When the magnetic knots break, like a tangle of springs exploding
outwards, the Sun can vomit plasma and other awful things into the solar system. These
solar storms come in many types, like solar flares, a tidal wave of high energy radiation.
They race through the solar system at the speed of light, sweeping up protons in the
solar wind, accelerating them into a high-speed solar proton storm. Then there are coronal
mass ejections, which rip millions or billions of tons of plasma from the Sun's atmosphere,
catapulting it through the solar system at speeds of up to 9 million kilometers per hour.
When these monsters hit us, nothing happens on Earth. While even smaller storms can damage
satellites, affect radio communication, or will be dangerous to astronauts, for people
on the surface, space weather is harmless. Earth's atmosphere protects us from the worst
effects of a solar flare by absorbing the blast of X-rays high up in the atmosphere,
well before it reaches the surface. The electrified plasma from a CME is deflected by the Earth's
magnetic field, diverting the energy storm to the North and South Poles, where energetic
particles fall into the atmosphere, causing the atmosphere to glow and creating beautiful
auroras. As with any sort of weather, most of the time, things are fine. Sometimes there
are hurricanes though, or in the case of the Sun, solar superstorms. And we know that they
happen once or twice every century. If one were to happen today, we would first detect
strong solar flares, a sort of flash before the much more dangerous thunder. The thunder
is a CME, consisting of billions of tons of hot magnetic plasma that crosses the 150
million kilometers between the Sun and Earth in less than a day. When it arrives, it causes
a shockwave that violently compresses the Earth's magnetic field and transfers energy
into the magnetosphere. But it can get worse. If the magnetic field of the CME is aligned
to Earth's in just the right way, the two magnetic fields merge. As the magnetic cloud
passes over Earth, it stretches the Earth's field into a long tail. Eventually, the energy
stored in the tail becomes too much to contain. It snaps and explosively releases its energy
towards Earth. A geomagnetic storm has begun. A few hundred years ago, nobody would have
cared. This storm gushing over the Earth is not relevant for machines made out of meat
and bones. But it's very relevant for machines made out of metal and wire. Remember the dynamo
– magnetism creates electric currents. Earth in the 21st century is covered in millions
of kilometers of wires transporting electricity and a complex grid of machines like transformers
that make this transfer possible. A CME's energy can induce currents in our power grid
that can either completely shut it down or worse, destroy the transformer stations that
keep our grid running. This has happened already, like when the Quebec power grid failed after
a strong solar storm in 1989. But in general, our engineers know how to deal with these
storms and so we usually don't even notice. The last time a solar hurricane washed over
Earth was in 1859. The Carrington event, the largest geomagnetic storms ever observed on
Earth. Massive auroras occurred as far south as the Caribbean. In some places, they were
so bright that people got up thinking the sun was rising. Luckily, we only had one sort
of modern technology – telegraph systems. They failed all over the world, shocking their
operators and chucking out sparks. Today, we have a tad more technology and our luck
may run out soon. Another bad solar storm is bound to happen eventually. A storm as
strong as the Carrington event missed Earth only by a small margin in 2012. Studies projected
that it would have inflicted serious damage to electronic systems globally, costing up
to $2.6 trillion to the US alone. The time to replace all the damaged systems was estimated
at between 4 and 10 years. It's hard to say how bad it could have been. Experts disagreed.
Some assumed there would just be temporary blackouts, but others worried it could be
much worse. We won't know for sure until a big solar hurricane hits us. The probability
of such an event is estimated to be 12% per decade. That's about a 50-50 chance of at
least one in the next 50 years. And there is more unsettling news. A 2019 paper found
that even calm stars like our sun can create superflares every few thousand years. Eruptions
orders of magnitude stronger than the strongest storms we have observed in the solar system.
If such a storm hits us unprepared, the consequences could be catastrophic. It's hard to overstate
how much we depend on electricity. It's not just the lights at home. It means no computers,
no communication, no navigation. A sustained power outage might lead to a breakdown of
the supply chain. Water supply systems failing and hospital generators running dry. Supermarkets
not being refilled while food rots in the fields. The lack of power might make it extremely
hard to reboot our broken power grid, taking years or decades to restart our starving civilization.
Okay, time to panic. As much as daily newspapers might like for solar storms to send us back
to the Stone Age, they probably won't. Fortunately, even though solar storms aren't preventable,
virtually all of their nasty side effects are. Scientists observing the sun have a few
hours up to a few days to see a CME coming. And the engineers working the systems that
keep the world running are well aware of the risks posed by solar storms. Transformers
and substations can be taken offline. Short preventative blackouts, or in other words,
by unplugging stuff. Engineers can open up extra lines to dissipate the extra power.
And with investment and upgrades cheap compared to those other natural disasters require,
we could protect the world's electric grid against even the nastiest of storms. But we
do need to prepare. While the risk is manageable, it is real. For while our sun bathes us in
warm and pleasant light, one day, it might send a monster our way that we better be ready
for.
This video was sponsored by you. Kurzgesagt videos are only possible thanks to your direct
support. For example, if you want to stare at our smooth and round sun for a little longer,
we've made two minimal infographic posters, one about the scale of the sun and one about
the age of the universe. Both should make you feel sufficiently tiny and help you appreciate
your existence a bit more. But wait, there's more. We have a bunch of new stuff from the
long requested bacteriophage infographic poster to a new optimistic nihilism poster that lets
you enjoy some existential dread in style. Or join us in our ant obsession and get the
new ant explorer notebook with beautiful infographics and facts about ants and gold
lettering on the cover. If you'd rather update your wardrobe, have a look at our beanies
or t shirts, or you know, all the other stuff. We put a lot of love and care into developing
our products and only make stuff we want to have ourselves. If you want to support Kurzgesagt,
getting some merch is the best way to do it while receiving something beautiful in return.
Thank you for your support. And thank you for watching.
Transcribed by https://otter.ai