Well, before we make our bad life decisions, uh, I think you need to top me off.
Oh, yeah.
What's, uh, what's up with the dirndl today?
Oh, I was feeling, uh, like Bavarian today.
Oh.
Uh, you should save that for the cultural appropriation episode.
Yeah, I thought of that.
But Germans don't count.
I think almost the frustrating thing about, like, all these comments is, like,
since we pick a theme for each episode, uh, we can't, like, you know,
we're trying to save, like, oh, we'll do this comment next week, or, like,
when people write out scenes, we'll do stuff with the scenes later, I promise.
Oh, God, yeah, we're saving each and every scene.
Yeah, we're saving the scenes, but right now we're gonna try and focus,
because this week we're gonna try and hammer down what the plot is,
so we can move on and actually start cobbling together our project, like, for realsies.
And who are the characters that act in this plot? Very important.
Piscasaurus clarified, first off, that the Cthulhu mythos as a concept,
not any of the gaming or anything, but the Cthulhu mythos as an intellectual property
is public domain, so we're good.
Holla!
Second, the misconception about the mythos.
The overarching theme is not that the universe is malevolent,
just that it is apathetic to us because we do not matter that much.
All the more for us to shit on.
Yeah.
Woohoo!
Um, shall we start with the villain?
So, what we were getting a lot of was that it should be a cult.
It should be a cult of man, you know, Cthulhu worshipping a cultist.
Well, we got a lot of this.
Like, we had, I think, the thing we had the most re-villain was cultists.
And so, there was that.
But I think also, like, the idea that they're not Cthulhu cultists, but Azathoth cultists.
Yes.
Who's, like, a bigger man.
Sarah Desnes points out that the main antagonist should be female.
That you can use as contrast to the female protagonist.
Then you can use these comparisons to make antagonists look even worse
and female protagonists to look even better.
For instance, the antagonist could dislike children,
while the protagonist wants to be a mother.
So, you know, the antagonist is mean and heartless.
She hates love.
Maybe an inability to find or keep love could be what motivates her.
Yeah.
And also, the best part about having a female antagonist
is that it makes it easier for the female reader to hate her.
Yeah, and we can hate her too.
Because women hate women.
Am I right?
You bitch.
You whore.
While on the subject of the antagonist,
Christopher Emmett suggests that the Indian third wheel
actually becomes sort of an antagonist
by falling in with these evil cultists
and using the Nectric Namakon to banish the Eldritch Abomination.
My idea after that was that he gets brainwashed,
so there's no accountability.
So he's still like the good ethnic third wheel,
but he's been brainwashed by the evil cultists
and that becomes part of the plot.
She wants to save him.
Because they're friends.
He's like her best friend.
They're besties.
She would never be able to live without him.
They've known each other since the beginning of junior year.
Yeah.
Moving on to family.
I've been liking some things that have been thrown out
that the parents should be scientists.
I was seeing suggestions for should be an archaeologist.
Thomas de Grote mentioned that one of the parents
should be a marine biologist.
So it's kind of both.
I'm thinking that the father should be the marine biologist
and the mother the archaeologist.
The mother goes off on a dig.
Everyone thinks she's a little crazy, though.
Yeah.
Well, Elizabeth Smith suggests that
rather than just doing search and replace versions
of the parents of Twilight,
they're not divorced.
Rather, flighty mother is flighty
because she keeps running off for archaeology things.
So that's a good starting place with the parents.
Regarding the purity of our Lego brick.
This one is difficult
because it's really hard to define a character
without giving them any real definition
so that literally anyone, any white woman,
can pretend to be them.
Pavel Marek gave us one that I really liked.
And this came in the form of a scene
where our bitchy best friend, or a bitchy friend,
says or does something nasty to Bella.
And Cthulhu puts her in the hospital
in some way, shape, or form.
I did it. He started.
For you.
Then the problem will not be spoken of again.
The bitchy girl may or may not be
mentally debilitated forever and ever.
Bella will never question
that maybe she shouldn't be with this person
because of their Austen power.
No.
His devotion.
He loves her so much.
He can't help himself.
I enjoyed Catherine Rose's suggestion
that maybe Bella should have suffered
from night terrors from the time she was little
because of her being the only one
to perceive the real universe in her dreams.
I like this a lot.
She has a secret, unknown pain
and her parents were like,
well I haven't grown out of it yet,
so she keeps it to herself
because she's a teenager now.
She shouldn't be waking up for her nightmares anymore.
She just pretends it's not a thing.
And that's the second book of Twilight,
in that four months where she's waking up
with nightmares every single night
and Charlie just gives up on getting the shit.
As parents do.
As parents do, because it's like,
you're not dying.
They'll get over it, right?
Ghost Riddle Word reminds us that
Edward has to save Bella,
so Lego brick needs to be saved
from rape.
No less than two, maybe three times.
Three times.
Bless you, you signed into Yahoo
just as me.
You mentioned that,
me mentioned that
I like the idea of her being an artist
who works to get inspired by Cthulhu.
Now that gives her a little too much agency.
However, what we came up with
is that she does create
these artistic works
in a dream state.
Sort of like Shia in Transformers 2.
Just all of a sudden one day,
all these amazing abilities,
through no effort or agency of her own.
She never has to work for it,
it just happens to her one day.
So she's not actually an artist,
she's just a conduit for all these images
that control her.
And when she wakes up it's like,
but I can't even draw stick figures.
Anastasia Beaverhausen also suggests
that she needs a flaw that isn't really a flaw.
Like, she's too kind.
She's too nice,
and this only manifests
in the first person prose.
And Max Phillips also suggests
that Unbella throws around
the phrase beautiful insanity
every 15 pages or so.
I like that, it's so artistic.
Alexandria Lundelius points out
she was suggesting that the protagonist
should be an arts crafter,
like arts and crafts.
I think that should be her best friend,
like the fat one.
The fat best friend comes from
a Twilight knockoff called Hush Hush,
which is Twilight with fallen angels.
And the fat best friend is
real big in that one,
because, well, it's real big.
She eats.
Ideal women don't eat.
We don't need to.
We just drink.
Yeah.
Calories.
My life is hard.
And the thing about our Bella or Anna
is that
it's this that bitch lover.
I hate her guts,
but she's the greatest.
Gee, I wonder what she's doing,
that whore.
There has to be that judge love
that goes on in a teenage girl's mind
that is awful, totally awful,
and absolutely happens in real life.
But when you actually read it in a book,
it's the most heinous thing in the world.
Joe Drake's suggestion that we could have
just metaphors, like,
he was my totem, the altar, I wanted to worship that.
The cross I needed to kneel before
more than I had ever needed anything before.
At night in the mornings, on the walk home
from school, I would find myself whispering
little prayers to him.
To go into our, in using
great works of art,
to sort of
lead our stories without actually
influencing them. Genesis,
I'm looking at you. He suggests
we just go T.S. Eliot
The Hollow Men.
This is the way the world ends.
Not with a bang,
but a whimper.
So deep.
So deep. That's the beginning of our book
that we will never actually reference again.
Debra Elaine suggests that for
like a Briggs family, how about a father who's
spoken of as controlling, but never actually
does anything controlling.
She hates him for a stupid, possibly unexplained
reason. Do you want to explain
informed attributes
to those playing the home game?
So the idea of the informed attribute,
as many of our various
Duke commenters commented,
is that you bring something up,
you define a character
in the tell, don't
show sort of way,
and then never follow up on
it in any meaningful way, especially
in any meaningful way to the plot.
The important thing is the perception
of the reader.
My best friend is a bitch.
Best friend never does anything
bitchy. My father is
controlling. Father never does
anything controlling.
Cthulhu sets my spirit
free. Cthulhu controls
the shit out of her.
So on and so forth.
So what have we decided about our plot?
Well, I think the plot begins
with... In some way, shape,
or form, ethnic third wheels
family has the Necronomicon, right?
Yes. Somehow or other,
ethnic third wheel and
Lego brick read from
the Necronomicon, thereby
summoning the great old one.
Third wheel's
character development is he has
the Necronomicon, he's in love with her,
she meets the bad guy,
or the bad boy.
Third wheel gets shoved
aside, but he knows
that bad boy is the bad boy.
Okay. Proceed with like
20 scenes of them staring into each other's eyes
meaningfully. And also like the
what are you? I can't tell you.
No tell me. I can't tell you.
No one would believe you. I can't tell you.
Meanwhile, ethnic third wheel
knows what's going on.
So when eventually he becomes fed up,
he goes to the cultists,
gets brainwashed,
and we go to our third act,
which is effectively love saves the world.
That's our book.
So that's our basic
outline. Next week, with your
comments and help, we will
come up with a more concrete
outline.
But,
the big things that we need to start
thinking out are, what are
the names of all of these characters?
What is Lego Brick's name?
I really want to call her Blanche
Slate, but obviously that's a little too obvious.
No, my idea was that
her name is Tabitha
Louise Rasa. So we need
to find the names for
Ethnic Third Wheel, for Cthulhu
as boy,
and
for, of course
Lego Brick. Like I say, the Carlisle
is Uncle Neil, and he is
Neil. You're also a tip. Exactly.
Needs to happen.
I will hold on to this until my dying day.
Moreover,
we need to figure out
what our
pen name is.
Start throwing us ideas of
not only what our pen name could be,
but what the project name could be.
Alright! And our title for the book!
And our title for the book!
Start throwing us names for things for our Carlisles,
our supporting characters, our bitchy best friend,
our Lego Brick,
the mother, the father, the title
of the book, and of course our pen name.
Do all this
tweet at us, at Chez Apocalypse.
So after I finish this drink,
all my bad life choices come to fruition, right?
No!
Because we framed them as good.