In previous videos I've shown evidence of how the world around us was formed
but a fundamental question remains, how did we get here?
The void has always been filled by fanciful stories
the Chinese believed a dragon goddess needed someone to talk to
so she formed humans out of clay from a river bank
according to Jewish mythology a god made a man out of clay
and then fashioned a woman out of one of his ribs
Inuit mythology describes a raven god who filled the earth with pea pods
and one of these burst open to reveal the first man
but 150 years ago one book shattered these myths
and opened the door to a rational and evidence based understanding of our origins
But while Charles Darwin and Alfred Wallace
jointly came up with the idea of natural selection
they parted company on whether this evolutionary mechanism
could be applied to humans
Wallace formulated the idea that animals had evolved
but he couldn't compromise his belief that humans were the work of a deity
but Darwin caved to the inevitable conclusion and called it
My Little Heresy
The Little Heresy was first expounded not by Darwin
but by naturalist Thomas Huxley
in an 1863 book called Evidence as to Man's Place in Nature
Huxley and his supporters had clear evidence of evolution in animals
what they lacked was direct physical evidence to show that evolution also applied to humans
the search was now on for what became known as the missing link
a fossil that was half human, half ape
we are of course all apes according to classification
but for the purpose of simplification
in this video I'll refer to human apes as humans
and our common ancestor with chimpanzees as apes
It didn't take long for this new branch of science to find its first piece of evidence
just three years before Darwin published The Origin of Species
the bones of what looked like an oddly deformed human
were unearthed in the Neander Valley in Germany
Neanderthal Man wasn't the missing link
but it did seem to be one of our archaic ancestors
In 1891 fossil bones from the first real archaic hominid
later called Homo erectus
were found on Java Island
and 32 years later another Homo erectus skull Peking Man
was found in China
neither of these fossils were the fabled missing link
they were closer to humans than apes
but they did spark the idea that modern humans may have evolved in Asia
Africa was also beginning to yield some valuable finds
including the Taung Child found in South Africa in 1924
the problem was these didn't fit with another discovery
made 16 years earlier in southern England, Piltdown Man
but as more fossils emerged from South Africa in the 1930s
it became clear that Piltdown Man was the anomaly, not the Taung Child
Piltdown Man just didn't make any sense
either in its physiology or its geographical location
but it only made sense in 1953 when the hoax was revealed
by then the distribution of hominid fossils
had given rise to two schools of thought on human origins
an African origin and a multi-regional origin
the idea that humans evolved from archaic hominids in different parts of the world
but over the next 40 years
paleoanthropologists uncovered the mother lode of hominid fossils
the idea of a missing link
has long been relegated to the status of a quaint 19th century preoccupation
finding fossils that link humans to ancestral apes
isn't the problem
the problem is that East Africa has produced so many of them
that paleoanthropologists are having a hard time
sorting out which are our direct ancestors
and which are the evolutionary dead ends
we find what we find in most animal species
a wealth of relatives
some branched off and reached a dead end very quickly
others evolved for hundreds of thousands of years before becoming extinct
so our family tree turns out to be very rich indeed
it's a bit like trying to find the next of kin of an orphaned baby
and coming up not only with direct ancestors
but also their brothers, sisters, uncles and cousins
but together these hominid fossils tell a single story
as we work our way forward in time
just as expected, they become less ape-like
and more human-like
believers in an instant creation have a couple of explanations
for this wealth of fossil evidence
fake, fake, fake, fake
yeah, okay
I've heard that from a few conspiracy theorists
but even creationist organisations aren't suggesting anything so absurd
well, no one disputes that
but what species of ape?
there's evidence that some of these apes could light fires
and make tools and hunt with weapons
they walked on two legs
but they weren't human either
they had obvious ape characteristics
like arms longer than legs
what were they all doing in the Garden of Eden?
and why do we see a clear progression through time
of more ape-like creatures disappearing
and more intelligent and more human-like species
appearing in the sedimentary layers above
we never see a species disappearing
but we can see it by something less intelligent and less human-like
that might be true in some cases
but not in all
and skull shape is only one characteristic
that separates humans from apes
a more slender body form
larger brain size, walking on two legs
having opposable thumbs
these are all crucial human features
that we see evolving gradually through time
evolution from ape characteristics
to human characteristics
can also be found in the smallest details
from the shape of the pelvis
to the thickness of tooth enamel
when the field of DNA opened up
paleoanthropology got its first big break
this completely new field of science
would either confirm one of the mythical accounts
of our instant creation
or it would confirm the evidence of slow evolution
and guess which one turned out to be right?
or is it?
when geneticists investigated
they discovered that humans have only 46 chromosomes
and all the other great apes have 48
so we couldn't have evolved directly
from a common ape ancestor
unless
two of the chromosomes had fused
well there's only one way to find out
I'll let Dr Ken Miller pick up the story
so we can scan our genome
and you know what?
if we don't find that chromosome
evolution's in trouble
well guess what?
it's chromosome number two
it shows that our nearest relative
in the animal kingdom is
exactly as the fossil evidence predicted
a great ape
the chimpanzee
and when did we last share a common ancestor?
around 5 million years ago
just before the date of the first ancestral hominid fossils
mitochondrial DNA from a Neanderthal fossil
has also been analysed
it's completely different to every type
of modern human
and it shows that humans and Neanderthals
had a common ancestor around half a million years ago
mitochondrial DNA can only be passed
from mother to child
and it mutates at a fairly regular rate
let's say this woman's mitochondrial DNA
develops a mutation
and let's mark it red
her kids will share the same mutation
but only the girls will pass it on
several generations later
another part of the mitochondrial DNA mutates
let's give this one a blue code
then another one mutates
a green code
then more mutations
thousands of generations later we can see a clear pattern
closely related people share
a lot of similar mutation markers
the less closely related they are
the fewer common mutations they share
but everyone shares the red mutation
which means they can all be traced back
to a common female ancestor
and since geneticists know roughly the rate
at which these mutations occur
they can work out roughly when and where she lived
the result could be that
the result coincided perfectly
with the fossil evidence
around 150,000 years ago
in Africa
she wasn't the only woman around at the time
of course
and we have ancestors going much further back in time
but she is our most recent common ancestor
I've laid out the twists and turns
of the last 150 years
because science doesn't move in a straight line
ideas are constantly being refined
updated and amended
as more evidence comes to light
there are no foregone conclusions
and no preconceptions
instead we feel our way in a darkened room
collecting evidence
and getting closer and closer to an understanding
of the layout
when DNA analysis came along
it was as if a light had been switched on
almost nothing in the DNA evidence
contradicts what we find in the fossil evidence
together they give us the broad picture
of our origins
in the next video
the ancestry of humans made easy
I'll show evidence of who these ancestors were
and how they left their homeland
to conquer the world