The internet is like a breeding ground for conspiracy theories.
While some are just stupid and funny, others promote ignorance and an unhealthy distrust.
So we went to the Kurzgesagt lab and developed a foolproof system to destroy not all,
but a lot of conspiracy theories.
It's really simple.
Just ask yourself, does the theory affect really rich and powerful people?
Is the answer yes?
Okay, then it's most likely not true.
Let's test it on three examples.
Number one.
There's an easy cure for cancer,
but it's withheld because it would destroy the profits of pharma companies.
Do really rich people die of cancer?
Like, I don't know, say the former CEO of Apple?
Yes, there is no suppressed cure for cancer.
Number two, chemtrails.
The theory that airplanes spray chemicals in the air for population control
or some other crazy reason.
Do really powerful people breathe air?
Do Obama or Putin breathe air?
Yes, chemtrails are not a thing.
Number three, apocalyptic conspiracy theories.
The world will end soon because of the Antichrist, Myers, aliens, someone says so.
Do really rich and powerful people ignore the soon-to-be-upon-us and very imminent apocalypse?
Yes, the world will not end soon.
This obviously doesn't work for every conspiracy theory out there,
but it does work for some of the most stupid ones.
So the next time someone tries to convince you that the Illuminati put stuff in your water,
just show them this video,
and maybe be a bit more selective about your friends on Facebook.
Thanks for watching!