Wow, it finally snowed again in London.
Snow day? Not to be squandered inside.
I'm supposed to be working today, but does daily vlogging count?
I'm not a daily vlogger, but I think if I make a vlog that could totally count.
Come, join me as I do nothing more than look at beautiful things on this snow day with Grey.
Music
Man it is just beautiful out here.
It looks like the snow might stick for more than just this morning, so I'm gonna head over to the underground to get to the center of the city while it lasts.
Still be snow, still be snow, still be snow.
Yes, yes, yes!
In all my years in London, snow is so rare that I've never been able to get to the center while it still looks like this. This is amazing!
No fun zone around the lions, but whatever.
Okay, I'm going as far as I can before I freeze.
The problem with London not having real winters is you don't have a real winter coat and real winter gloves, so it's easy to get quite cold quite fast.
That was a cold walk across the Golden Jubilee. Coffee warm up required.
Uh, coffee?
Okay, powered up. Resuming snow exploration.
Ooh, the beach is open.
Music
Goodbye birds! Time to hustle, hustle over to the high viewing platform at the Tate Modern.
You've got to be kidding me. London cannot weather weather. This is not adverse weather.
The pigeon agrees with me.
Well, it looks like to get a view from above, I need to keep trekking to Baradur, which I'm gonna be really disappointed if Baradur is closed for adverse weather.
It's not adverse weather. It's glorious weather!
Music
Thank you.
It's open to the sky!
Music
I am the eye.
Well, in the time it took me to get back again, the sun has come out and the snow has started to melt.
But, I will not forget the gift of this day, and I'm glad I could share it with you.
Music