The 12,018 Human Era Calendar is out now.
You can order the limited edition for the short time of 10 days, and then never again.
It's like a regular calendar for 2018, but with one important difference.
It's for the year 12,018 of the Human Era.
We explained why this should be our current year in our A New Calendar for Humanity video.
Last year's calendar got a lot of feedback, and we listened to what you wanted.
The 12,018 calendar has much more room for notes, a spiral binding,
we got the shipping costs down, and it will arrive in time for Christmas.
It's printed on high-quality paper, has a gold cover, and it was produced in Seattle,
so we could ensure Kurzgesagt quality.
The calendar itself features 12 detailed illustrations of human cultures around the world.
Order it now. It's available for the limited time of 10 days until October the 20th.
The Human Era Calendar is a passion project for us that represents the idea of human unity and progress,
and that we need to work together to stay alive and to travel to the stars.
It's the second time we've made one, and we're trying to make this a regular thing.
Thanks a lot to everyone who loves the idea of a new history.
We couldn't do any of this without this group of like-minded humans around the world.
Bark, bark!