the first half of the discussion I had with Ben Davidson, aka Suspicious Observers. This came out
of his claims that I'd lied and deliberately misrepresented one of his videos, and his call
for a live debate on my alleged misdeeds. Two days before we were due to talk, Ben told me it wasn't
going out live after all, and I had no time to get that organised from my side. So I asked Ben to send
me the audio file, which he very kindly did, and I'd been matching it to the images I was showing
him during our discussion. Since the discussion I've also fact-checked some of his claims that
I couldn't check in the middle of the discussion, and also added a couple of graphics to illustrate
what we're talking about. I make it very clear when these are added, and pause the audio when
I add them, without cutting the audio at all. The only things I've cut out, with Ben's permission,
are where we had technical issues of no sound or no images. So if Ben wants to post this on his
channel without the fact-checks, he can do so seamlessly by simply cutting them out. Anyway,
here goes. Well listen, you go first, because you were the one who thought my video was
misrepresenting you, so I'm happy to listen to that. Alright, so I'd rather not hurl accusations
at you, what I'd rather do is sort of go through some of the things right now, and
you tell me where I'm going wrong, okay? Okay, sure.
And I'll start with the fact that where you had crossed off Ice Age and put Interglacial,
I kind of figured that all the stuff above that was what happened during the Interglacial. We're
in the Interglacial, and so the way I saw it is, you know, we're in the Ice Age for a long time,
there's glaciers forming at the poles, obviously, there's ice up there, and then there's ice also
at lower latitudes. Maybe not at what we would consider low latitude, but at least at mid
latitudes, latitudes that are lower. As I understood it, Earth was in an Ice Age and
had been in many Ice Ages where, unlike today where we see ice semi-permanently at the polar
regions or at some places of the poles permanently right now, there were glaciers at lower latitudes
as well. For example, in the Great Lakes region, and probably parts of Scandinavia, things like
that. And so what happens is it doesn't all just start to melt right away. What happens is the
glaciers at mid latitudes start to melt, but while that is happening, at the polar region,
there is much more accumulation of ice. There's a lot more, it's not like the whole planet starts
melting all at once. So we're in an Ice Age and that's how it is. And that 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 was
supposed to be the story of the Interglacial. And 5 was supposed to be a question mark as to how that
was actually going to happen. So as I saw it, as opposed to ice accumulating everywhere, the first
thing we notice in an interglacial is that the ice is accumulating only at the poles,
as opposed to everywhere. And that is what drops Earth's albedo. The fact that we went from having
ice everywhere to ice being accumulating at the poles. Now, because this is just apparently the
first video in this series that you've commented on, it is a bit like coming into Wednesday in
week 9 in a seminar class. And so we've been talking about the different phases of ice.
There's ice accumulating everywhere, there's ice accumulating at the poles, and then there's ice
melting everywhere. Those are basically the only 3 phases Earth has. And so as we come out of a
glacial period and we go into the interglacial, the story of that is we go from having ice
everywhere to ice accumulating at the poles only. When this happens, Earth's albedo drops.
The planet warms up even further. Eventually, that warmth overtakes the poles too.
CO2 is released, even more methane is released. While it's heating up, more water vapor is going
into the atmosphere. And yet, the question mark, number 5, always an ice age has followed. And that
seems to, we didn't attempt to give an answer to that. We just sort of said that is what has
happened. And correct me if I'm wrong, there was still CO2 and methane releases and water vapor
increases in the atmosphere during the previous interglacials, right? And something always throws
us back into an ice age. Okay. Right. Can I start with you there? Because I've been taking notes,
and there's a lot to get through on that. The first thing is, I did get the impression from
a lot of your subscribers that they saw some sort of hidden references behind all this,
that clearly, now that you tell me this is part of a series of things you've been doing,
that makes a lot more sense. Because taken on its own, this video did suggest that ice accumulate,
well, okay, I won't go into that. I'll show you the timeline a bit later. But I think what you're
not getting, let me ask you what you think, okay, what you don't get is why we go from an
interglacial. You can understand why we go from a glaciation into an interglacial. But what I
noticed was you said somehow we go from an interglacial back into a glaciation. That's
going from a warm interglacial like we have now back into what you call an ice age. Now,
you said somehow, which suggests that you don't think that there is any scientific explanation
for that. So first of all, let me just clarify, do you think there is a scientific explanation
for that? And do you know what that scientific explanation is? I have read it. And I think that
your video did a very good job explaining. You know, I sort of mentioned Milankovitch cycles
in a moment, and you just sort of did a much better job explaining what those are.
I have read a good deal about that. At the moment, you know, there's a big disconnect because
the same things that were happening in the atmosphere every previous time or the same
things that were happening in space with Earth every single time, those things are happening
again now. And so what is the disconnect? What is happening now that isn't just a faster version,
a more extreme version of what happened before? If you have a good answer to that.
Okay, I'll answer that. I'll answer that. The first thing I can tell you that's happening now
that never happened before is that we're getting carbon dioxide levels up to concentrations that
we have never seen in any interglacial before. So the first thing that's extraordinary about
what's happening now is the level of carbon dioxide. If you look back at interglacials in the
past, there was never this kind of CO2 concentration simply because there was never this kind of fossil
fuel burning. So we've had basically a 50% increase in the amount of CO2 in the atmosphere
because we've been burning fossil fuels. That's one thing that's different. But I want to bring
you back to one thing you said which was that what is happening now is what happened before
in the sense of, from what I understand of your hypothesis, your idea of how this works,
you think that ice melts at the poles, comes down to the lower latitudes, cuts off circulation,
ice forms at the lower latitudes, this causes us to go into an ice age or what geologists would
call a glaciation. That's not quite it. It's a larger process of things but the desalinization
is a big portion of it. I mean the the salinization level of the ocean could be as important as the
CO2 level in the troposphere. My question to you would be, do you believe that
everything we pump into the troposphere can just stay here at you know higher and higher densities
without bleeding more and more into the oceans and up into the stratosphere and in the ocean?
No no no because because the science now, look I can only follow what the researchers
have measured. 50% has stayed up there. 50% basically goes into the biosphere and the oceans
but can I, sorry, I don't want to stray away from this point because it's an important one.
I want to establish what it is you think that is happening now that also happened to bring an end
to the interglacials in the past. There's something you think that is happening now that also happened
that brought the past interglacials to a close. I'm trying to establish what that is. What I'm
saying is the only thing that is different is the is how much pollution humans have put into
the atmosphere. That's the only thing really that that's different. Just a quick fact check here so
you can see what we're talking about. The level of CO2 during most interglacials doesn't go much
above 280 parts per million. That's the blue line. In the last 200 years it's gone from 280 to over
400 parts per million in just 200 years. That's the red line. I mean if you look at the timing
you mean if you look at the timing of this interglacial this has been a fairly long
interglacial. Really? I mean compared to the last couple wouldn't you say?
Well the one that you pointed to when you did your second video rebutting mine you actually
clarified what you were talking about which was then clear that you were talking about coming out
of a glaciation. You were looking at termination 4. That was the example you gave of us coming out
of a glaciation. Well out of termination 4 the interglacial lasted about 50,000 60,000 years.
Now we're only about 11,000 into our interglacial so we have a long way to go yet.
Others are much shorter but you also get into glacials that are much longer. So I mean these
are not insignificant time periods. But again I don't want to stray away from the point that
I'm trying to get to. You said somehow we come out of this glacial this interglacial.
I'm trying to establish what it is you think scientists say because you're suggesting that
maybe scientists don't know. No I'm not suggesting that and it's not like every scientist in the
world says it's the exact same things and puts the exact same attribution on all of them.
You know I am not sure whether you fully understand what we were trying to do or what we
were trying to communicate there. But this is not always meant to be telling the exact line of what
peer-reviewed science is. Okay all right but let me just tell you what the science says and then
you can tell me why they're wrong. That would be the easiest way. According to the science
these cycles happen and they're very regular cycles. I mean they've got a periodicity of
about a hundred thousand years and they happen because of Milankovitch cycle. So we go into
a glaciation because the earth gets less sunlight because of the tilt and the wobble of the earth's
axis and its orbit. We get less sunlight and that little bit of less sunlight causes
the earth to cool a little bit which gives us more ice which gives us more albedo.
That causes the oceans to degas CO2 and carbon dioxide being a very powerful greenhouse gas
sorry to absorb CO2 because it's more soluble in colder water. That takes CO2 out of the
atmosphere and that continues the cooling. So there's a kind of a positive feedback
which accelerates this cooling. Now coming out of that is when we get the Milankovitch cycles
work in the opposite way where we get an increase in insulation and that causes less ice that means
less albedo. CO2 is degas from the oceans and CO2 is a powerful greenhouse gas so it warms the earth
even further and again we get a positive feedback. You suggested that that ought to cause runaway
warming but there's no reason why that should cause runaway warming. I did not suggest that
that would cause runaway warming. I put that at the at the end as a as a as like sort of like a
footnote or end note to the the very clear periodicity and one of your commenters hit me
hard and said hey look take a look during your supposed ice ages there's little spikes up here
and there and I had to explain that I wasn't suggesting that Milankovitch cycles were responsible
for every up and down on that chart but the very clear periodicity that I imagine a five or six
year old could say hey do you see the pattern of things going up and down spiking up and going
absolutely you know I said yeah what I was saying was hey if you wanted to know more about that
you could look into Milankovitch cycles that was all I said. Yeah and so there's no real mystery
then about why we're going in and out of glaciations or do you still think there's
no but but all right so so here's here's the point and here let me if I may run you through
weeks one through eight that you missed and you can maybe tell me if something's going wrong here
all right so sooner or later and I have actually read a couple different things about where we are
in the Milankovitch cycles but we are not exactly in the the favorable side if if you want a warmer
planet we are gonna you know basically from here on out we are going towards the colder period
now that's not something that's going to be playing in our lifetimes all right but it's
something that should be thought of when they're talking about you know hundreds thousands of years
ahead of time for right now here are the points that we have made that that makes us that make us
think that the planet is about to cool down and first and foremost is a combination of political
pressure continually worsening extreme weather and technological innovations are going to reduce
carbon emissions never underestimate human ingenuity or the power of disasters and propaganda
both good and bad propaganda there is almost no question in my mind that if you have any foresight
you can see the wild reduction of pollution of this planet it is not at all hard to see
if that occurs it's not like the desalinization of the oceans stops immediately those do increase
the freeze potential of the oceans in winter and they disrupt critical ocean currents they do help
stratify the ocean and partially incarcerate the sea floor methane releases now while that is
happening and it's not like if we stop polluting tomorrow the the warmth in the arctic that we've
been noticing anomalously is going to just suddenly disappear but we've learned that
the warm arctic is not the you know is another way to have a weaker polar vortex
early sudden stratospheric warming events and create more jet stream blocking that was what
i showed in in the actual video now what i brought back in during the discussion was the fact that we
had seen tons of articles about how low solar activity weakens the polar vortex increases early
sudden stratospheric warming events and creates more jet stream blocking and so what we will have
here is the sun entering a significant minimum the arctic will still be warm even if we stop
pollution and both of those things will force weaker polar vortex increases in sudden uh
stratospheric warmings and more jet stream blocking now specifically on the decreased solar
you know this idea of 0.1 change over the solar cycle being the sun's influence in climate is
absolutely preposterous and if you saw the solar forcing for cmip6 when that does come out it will
no longer be restricted to that 0.1 the solar scientists have stood up and said that is
uncharacteristically preposterous because there's also x-ray radiation and their solar energetic
particles along with the indirect connection to galactic cosmic rays the ionization of the cloud
layer etc offering less energy while earth's albedo profile goes up due to cosmic rays
and so that's going to be happening more and more as we enter into that significant solar
minimum this century all these things should be happening this century um okay and you know this
is this is all fine but i mean uh i really i thought we were here to to talk about my
misrepresentations of what you'd said so i'd really like to get back onto that i i mean all
your theories are great and i i have no idea how much uh evidence you've got to support this because
you know what i would need to do is look at your sources and go through them um so could could we
just go back um would you mind if i i talk about you know what we were here to debate which was
my misrepresentations of your video and what you said in that video i'm sure that you said a lot of
things in other videos and i'm sure that this is the eighth in a series and that one through seven
talked about all sorts of other things but i really can't get into those now because i haven't
seen those videos on it so let's just deal with this video what i want to know is why why and i
don't know if you did this in comments or if there was some other video or on or you did this on
facebook or whatever because i i don't understand how this happened but i got literally over 800
comments within the span of 24 hours all saying virtually the same thing
that i didn't understand what those papers were saying and that i didn't have any basis
whatsoever in talking okay then then let's talk about that because i suspect the reason they said
that was because you didn't understand what the papers were saying now if you want to say
you did understand that's absolutely fine with me and and that's what i would like to talk about so
um what i've got um is um is is what you what you said uh about um about my video i mean i'm
i'm happy to talk about one of the papers if you want to if you want me to talk about which paper
did you think i misunderstood well here's the thing i wasn't i was not attempting to represent
the conclusions of the papers i was not attempting to do that i know but let's go with what you
actually said you you were you were doing let me just play you this this clip and this is from your
your video okay cold fresh water and various atmospheric connections send us spiraling into
an ice age thereafter just this month we learned that part of that process may include that extra
cold fresh water creating a stratification in the oceans that halts convection not to mention the
golf stream so um all that this was all i was meant to do and um this may help you understand
a lot um i put i put huge faith in observations i put much less faith in interpretations and
conclusions based on those and um frankly i have the track record to back that up
um this the only thing i cared about was we have been looking and waiting for the story that says
that there is an increased freshening of that water and the reason we've been waiting for that
is because we've been waiting for the Beaufort Gyre to release we've been waiting for that for
three times longer than we've ever supposed to have waited for that before
and it's not like people are just stationed up there taking measurements of the current all the
time it's not like you can put buoys okay so basically this paper you're you're saying this
paper doesn't support what you were saying about uh the um this this cold water being part of the
process that leads into an ice age you agree that it doesn't support that it it supports my overall
thesis that we could have a mini ice age like event this century and all we were looking for
was the increased freshening of the surface water all right so this is your theory this
is something you've come up with this has been what this whole thing is about the notion that
hey look we are we're about to see pollution take a dive while there are everywhere you look
signals that cold is coming or at least cold yeah yeah but no no it doesn't it doesn't sorry
this is where this is where i'm i'm i can actually begin to disagree with what you're saying here
because um you say cold is coming you're talking about global cold i'm talking as you know are you
not i'm talking about another mini ice age like event we had in the 1400s to 1600s but something
like that okay that's okay that was called the little ice age which is global cold you are
talking about global temperatures getting cooler rather than warmer yes okay right now that we've
established that you agree that these papers don't support that but this is basically just your idea
we've already established in fact i did play in my video the part where you do say that they don't
support it so i'm not trying to misrepresent what you said but you did say that we learned
this month and um in fact you were showing this paper uh suggesting that we learned from this
paper so all i'm saying is well we didn't learn it from this paper this is something that you
have come up with and you would agree uh all this paper does is show that there will there is
cold fresh water coming down from the arctic and it's hovering above the saline water the
more saline water of the overturning circulation and possibly cutting it off so that's basically
what the paper says the rest of it is is all your interpretation i think we're agreed on that are we
yes but that has never been something i so is this whole thing going to be about like you didn't
realize that i was giving my my hypothesis and my things about this and you don't think i have
the chops to do it should we just skip to where i no no no no not at all not at all i'm just trying
to establish um uh that one of the one of the things you said was that somehow i had misled
people uh in to saying that you were claiming that these papers uh somehow uh did not support
the warming or something like that i can play you the clip but but basically what i'm showing is
that uh there was a slight misrepresentation in that you did say that we're learning from these
papers that this is part of the process that leads into it i think that was a very i think
that was a kind way of saying it if you were just to walk into this seminar week nine in this video
the whole thing seems like of a wild misrepresentation i think okay well that's
fine so i didn't misread anything no but what you did you you would agree but what you did was
even you would agree that if you just watch this video and you haven't watched the entire series
of which most people when they watch youtube videos they watch a video because it's got an
interesting headline they read they watch it and they get kind of taken in by it now if they
haven't seen the previous seven they wouldn't know uh what this video is saying so when you say well
you know you're misrepresenting what i said actually i'm just taking exactly what you said
now that maybe that there were a lot of thoughts behind that that you didn't put out in the video
there were a lot of things that you'd said earlier that were not in this video that's fine
uh i'm just saying that this is what you were putting out in this video which a lot of people
would see without having seen the entire series i i strongly disagree the only reason why so many
people are going to see this is because of what you did i am not discoverable easily unless you
type my name in i am intentionally hard to discover on youtube no no i've seen your name
before yes you've seen my name before because it pops up on on a lot of your videos and we've
talked about the same kind of thing a lot of times but it's not like somebody could
go type in climate change and my name would ever come up in a million years
but even so i think i think we we all have a responsibility to represent if that is the case
you had i think you had a responsibility to send me an email and say hey what are you doing or at
least go and try to find some of my other videos on on the climate because what ended up happening
is a bunch of people hundreds of people didn't know what happened and they came and my god some
of your viewers were so horrendously vulgar listen i can't i'm sorry i i had a lot from yours as well
so i can't be responsible for what people post on your videos but and i'm sure you can't be
responsible for what people uh know but but the idea let's not get in but can we talk about the
science yes because i'm not getting into an argument about what i was talking somebody posted
something that you found offensive what i was talking about and what offended me was the notion
that this was portrayed to be something it wasn't this was portrayed to be then that's what that's
what this discussion is about then that's what this discussion is about so let's get to the bottom
of whether this this was fair enough or not um now you you did say um you need to go to the studies
on this right uh uh the um the study that you're talking about is this one by altman's you've read
this study have you yeah if you're going to ask me to remember specific lines out of it i i'm not
i'm not but you did obviously read the study um you know because you're quoting the study and you
did advise people to go and read the study rather than just the summary so i'm just establishing that
you actually did read that study yes sir okay um now it doesn't and and i think we can agree it
doesn't concur with your idea that uh this is going to lead into an ice age we've already
established that how about whether it concurs that the cold water coming south is likely to freeze is
there anything in the paper that suggests that i did not suggest that that is where that information
came from that was something that people already you did no no i didn't say that i was just asking
no nothing in this paper says that but as long as people realize i didn't say it did
i didn't say this paper said that no but does it does it contradict that though um
maybe i i don't remember uh exactly that's not really the reason i was reading this paper like
for example i didn't pay much attention to the methods section of this paper okay no i very
rarely do either but um what do you think um i mean do you disagree with the paper put it that
way is there anything in the paper that you disagree with i think they got you know i i do
remember the answer is yes but i don't remember what that was exactly at this time and frankly
the the majority of my problems with these papers is the fact that you know because of how many
papers come out in the climate realm even though we have known what solar forcing is going to be
for cmip6 for a year now um and even though there have been hundreds of papers that are going to be
included in the next update when it comes out there is nobody who's using anything but cmip5
for these studies and it this is by necessity you couldn't expect you know even these three people
and if they had 10 students working with them to go and figure out what the what all the new
variables would be in their model between the time they submitted the paper and it got published
bunch of those variables would change you know okay what was the conclusion of the paper dude
i know it's been a while since you read it but basically what was its conclusion
um man i i'm racking my brain here this uh was this the one that was talking about um
the accumulation versus uh the accumulated retention versus the release amount
the paper we're looking at is the one ben mentioned here and that he's citing it's the
paper from which ben said we learned that part of the process of glaciation may include extra cold
fresh water creating a stratification in the oceans the paper does say that fresh water will
be injected into the atlantic but it does not say that that is part of the process of glaciation
so we did not learn this from the paper if you want to check this i've cited the paper
in the video description this is the one that was talking about an increased uh risk well are you
seeing the the screenshot in front of you i'm seeing it but it's a little blurry in terms of the
words okay the headline of the paper is increased risk of a shutdown of ocean convection posed by
warm north atlantic summers okay um which pretty much says it all you know that that was the one
that um i just played on your clip that you suggested showed that this would stop the
overturning circulation of the uh atlantic and it would keep the cool fresh water on top and and the
saline water underneath stop the circulation now your your theory is that that would lead to
freezing of this um top layer of cold water not all it's not like it's going to freeze down off
the coast of north carolina man but as more ice enters the water and as it loses its saline
its saline profile we will see spikes in ice i mean but how did we get record high Antarctic
ice all right all right let's deal with that then if we're going to see spikes in ice you do you
know that the conclusion of the paper was the complete opposite i am aware of that the reason
but we have seen the opposite happen in both the north and the south over just the last decade
in 2013 and 2014 there was record high Antarctic ice and then we didn't have record high arctic
ice but we saw uh what they called a record recovery of the arctic just a couple years
ago i think you you you misunderstand me when i say that its conclusion is the complete opposite
i'm not saying it's the complete opposite of your your theory i mean that's that's something else
we're talking about specifics you say that the uh the water on top will freeze now in fact what
the paper concludes and the paper is is quite clear on on the quantity of heat coming out
have you got um can you see now the middle of the paper which i'm showing you with
two red boxes one left one left and one right right um they talk about um regressing on the
left-hand side regressing the results on both summer indices we find that the salinity anomaly
accounts for an energy surplus of around 2.8 times 10 to the 8th joules per square meter
after fresh erminia sea summers and around 4.8 times 10 to the uh power of 8 joules per square
meter after fresh labrador summers now we can go on and and look at their conclusions
and their conclusions actually say that the that the reason uh the bit because we've got this
this layer of fresh water on top the reason it's not sinking is not because it's too cold
but because it's too warm and if it got colder it would sink because of course uh colder colder
water does sink and then the circulation would would be okay the reason the circulation is not
working is because the water is too warm so in fact those figures which um i haven't heard you
disputing uh show that in fact this water is too warm it wouldn't freeze it would simply drop and
cause the circulation to continue um this is not just my interpretation of the paper and i i read
the paper uh new scientist says exactly the same thing um and this is a clip from new scientist
which i'm showing you now um the fresh water poses the threat to convection it has been
water it has to be cool um so i'm very aware of this conclusion but oh you are okay
i thought you didn't know what the conclusion was
well i mean i i remember it now but that would be the part i disagreed with
because why do you disagree with them because we have actually seen observations of the physical
world that show the exact opposite i want to know specifically sorry specifically what do
you disagree with do you disagree that cool water would sink no i don't the fresh water got colder
it would sink you disagree with that no what i am saying is this same excuse of oh the the you know
this is the same thing that they said caused the record high antarctic ice back in 2013 and 2014
when all those websites were using the record high antarctic ice to try to slam climate science
what was the proper answer yeah but but you're talking you're talking about this paper and
you're talking about the north atlantic so can we get back to what i'm saying is and the north
atlantic and this is the thing that you keep cutting me off you keep cutting me off man i i'm
just trying to get the full thought out and you keep cutting me off and it's okay your accent your
accent is so charming that it's like i i'm thrown off i don't know what to do about it
but so what i'm saying is the reason given for the record high arctic recovery when it happened
a couple years ago was that so much cold fresh water had melted off into it the explanation
for the record high antarctic ice in 2013 and 2014 was that cold fresh water had melted off
into the into the water cooled it off slightly it changed the salinity those were the i mean
i wasn't part of that battle back and forth but i saw one side of the debate yelling hey like look
at this we've got record high antarctic ice back then and like hey look we've got a record recovery
in the arctic and i saw the other side saying well you just put a bunch of cold fresh water
in there chilled it off and increased i'm sorry and and decreased the salinity what did you expect
was going to happen and here we have this other paper that it observes the same thing and then
uses and then uses a you know what is i suppose very good math um you know repeatable you know
math can be replicated to show that something is going to happen but we have seen this exact same
thing and the exact opposite happens on the planet this was the that that that water the
the freshening on top and the melting of the ice that was what was supposedly causing that
and it will this not have an effect on the gulf stream as well i mean i actually don't know as
much about its effect on the gulf stream and the keroshe current but i mean would it not disrupt
those as well eventually first of all let me apologize for interrupting you um you you're
right that that was rude and i'll tell you why i did it because i i felt when we're on a track
and we're on a subject um i had the experience as a journalist and i've interviewed a lot of
politicians and i'm not saying you're a politician but but people do tend to to get away to other
subjects and the antarctic and the arctic are completely different situations completely
different so you can't say well no i wouldn't say they're completely different situations it's it's
both when what i'm talking about the surface freeze it is about the temperature and the
salinity profile of the water which is affected by the melting ice that is not i mean it's not
like you've got different chemistries at work and you've got different laws of physics at work in
the north and south poles right okay but but there is there is a difference in in ocean
circulation there's a huge difference in the amount of warming and and sorry but but i think
let's focus on the thing that we're talking about because once you start saying yeah but in another
situation it's completely different yeah in another situation it is completely different
i think we can both agree on that there are reasons there are reasons why things happen
in antarctica for example it happened in the arctic too let's deal with the arctic then and
the north atlantic and the paper that is now the one that's under discussion what i'm interested
in knowing is that you disagree with the the paper and i'm what i'm trying to get at is
what is it you disagree with when they say that the fresh water on top is staying on top because
it's warmer because it has a heat content whereas if it cooled as we know from basic physics cool
water tends to sink and so you disagree with the conclusions of the paper and i'm trying to find
out why you think that cool water would not sink and restart the ocean circulation what is it that
you know that these researchers don't know because this is the exact same thing that happened
when the arctic had its record ice recovery
with respect it's not um the the arctic doesn't have the same overturning circulation
we are talking about the other the other thing is the arctic is a lot colder the ant sorry i
wasn't sorry i might have missed something you you say that again i'm sorry that was probably my
fault all right so yes okay i did include that thing about the about the antarctic
but during that same time they had what up north what they called a record recovery
of the arctic ice there was a spike back up and during that brief period and of course it's all
gone now we're at record low now but if you'll recall and i don't remember if it was exactly
at the time when antarctica was at record high or it was slightly after but there was that period
where there was the uh the record recovery from the low point in summer to where it was in winter
and it had a great winter and the explanation for that was more cold fresh water melted off
into the ocean so i emailed him after the discussion and asked him to cite the study that
said the explanation for that record recovery was more fresh water melted off into the ocean
his response it didn't come from a scientific study it was on a social media site ben doesn't
remember what year it was but he remembers there was a post from michael man and some guy from noah
whose name he can't remember he doesn't remember which ice recovery was being referred to but he
says it was in the last 10 years and it was a record recovery so that can only be the record
ice advance of 2012-2013 unfortunately ben didn't keep a copy so i have no idea what was actually
written in that post or what study it was based on if any so let's go to the actual study which
shows the scientific explanation they don't say the recovery was due to ice melting into the ocean
they say the opposite it was caused by a lack of melt a definitive study published in nature
geoscience concluded that the increase was driven by the retention of thick sea ice northwest of
greenland during 2013 which in turn was associated with a five percent drop in the number of days on
which melting occurred so we moved on to other issues which i'll have to put in part two of this
conversation when i get around to mixing it with the graphics i go on assignment in the middle of
april which is why i had to get this done quickly i've got another timely video to post this week
plus my discussion with academic agent another youtuber and i'm putting the final touches to
a regular video that i hope to post before i leave it's going to be unusually busy on
this channel for the next couple of weeks thanks for watching