Was referred to a video by a youtuber called the academic agent in which he asked for my help in solving a mystery
So I thought this would make an interesting object lesson in how facts get distorted on the vlogger sphere and how to fact-check
Let me start by saying that I like academic agent and not just because he uses the wonderful George Sanders as his icon
He does repeat a lot of the nonsense about climate change found on the internet
But he has shown a willingness in the past to listen when evidence contradicts his assumptions
So I'm sure he'll do the same here
I have a question to ask you the question is about whether the Maldives are going to be inundated by rising sea levels
Scientists have been giving grave warnings about the Maldives for many years in 1988
They predicted that it may be submerged in 30 years time academic agent says scientists predicted
But this isn't a scientific paper, it's a newspaper report the article doesn't quote a scientist
It quotes a government bureaucrat
So if we're going to look at what scientists predicted then we need to look at what scientists predicted
remarkably in
After this prediction had not come to pass just a reminder. This wasn't a prediction by scientists scientists again
Predicted that the Maldives could become
Uninhabitable in 30 years, but again, this is a newspaper report
So again, we have to check to find out what scientists predicted because believe it or not tabloid newspapers
Don't always accurately report the contents of scientific studies
The mail doesn't even cite its source, but it does give a keyword and a date
so it's not hard to search Google Scholar for the word Roy Namur and find the relevant paper and
It's quickly apparent that it doesn't say the Maldives will become uninhabitable by 2030 at all
First of all, it was looking at the Marshall Islands not the Maldives
The study looks at two different issues. The first is the issue of potable drinking water
As sea levels rise saltwater is intruding into the fresh groundwater making it increasingly salty
the paper predicts that between 2030 and
2065 the groundwater in many atolls will be too salty to drink
The range of dates reflects three different scenarios depending on how much action is taken to curb co2 emissions
2030 is the least likely date because it envisages no action at all on climate change
The mail gave the correct range predicted by the study more or less but typical of a tabloid newspaper
The mail chose to put the least likely date in the headline because it's the most dramatic and
That's the date the academic agent picked up on scientists again
Predicted that the Maldives could become uninhabitable in 30 years
In fact, the study says a lack of potable water could be overcome by desalination or transport of freshwater from elsewhere
But a bigger problem will be storm surges which flood the islands with saltwater
As sea levels rise these will become annual events between
2055 and
2105 the conclusion is that many atolls will remain suitable for human habitation until
2100 or
This isn't just in the body of the study. It's right there in the title
but the mail took this issue of uninhabitability or
Human inhabitants as it calls it and applied it to the earliest date for salty drinking water
The study didn't look at the question of permanent inundation by rising sea levels
But it said that other studies had predicted this wouldn't happen until at least the end of this century
The academic agent however, not only said that the islands would be uninhabitable by 2030
He went on to claim they'd be completely submerged by 2030
Something even the Mail Online didn't suggest given that the Maldives may be under the sea by the year 2030
This is typical of the way information passes around the internet in a kind of virtual telephone game a
Study says water supplies on the island will become too salty to drink sometime between 2030 and 2065
then suffer increasingly frequent storm surges between
2060 to
2105 then become uninhabitable and eventually submerged by rising sea levels after 2100
The Daily Mail picks up bits of this to report that the Maldive Islands will be uninhabitable by 2030 to
2060 and a headline that says this is likely to happen in 2030
And the academic agent picks up bits of the mail story to report that the Maldives will be underwater by 2030
To cap it all the only mention of the Maldives in the study was among a list of islands for which the study's findings are
relevant
Now there are some confusing aspects to this for starters in
2015 in the New Scientist
Some experts walked back the claim and said that the assholes may actually grow in the coming years
Two years later in the same publication. They went back to the original claim that the Maldives was under
grave threat in
Phys.org repeated the claim that climate change may actually help to grow the assholes
But no one's walked back any claims
There's nothing contradictory about studies that show increasing salination and storm surges
alongside studies that show increasing at all sighs because they're all happening and they've all been reported and
predicted in scientific journals for decades
In fact I covered this in my video climate change hurricanes atolls and coral reefs
Dead coral either broken off by wave action or marine organisms builds up to form an island
And it's still building these islands today
This isn't exactly news the process was first postulated by Charles Darwin and a number of papers have been published over the decades
Documenting the continuing growth of these islands although research continues
There's as yet little evidence that the expected rate of sea level rise will reverse that in
2010 Arthur Webb and Paul Kench analyzed hundreds of historical aerial photographs and
Confirmed that 23 out of 27 Pacific atolls are indeed either stable or growing in size
including Tuvalu
So why do climate scientists insist that these islands face problems?
Well the problems are related to other issues caused by climate change such as storm surges coastal erosion and saline intrusion
Not total submergence from rising seas
But of course the stability of the islands depends on the continuing health of the coral reefs and as coral reefs
Continue to die because of rising water temperature the protection and growth they afford will diminish
In fact this is explained in the very articles academic agent sites and the studies on which they're based
It's just a question of reading beyond the headlines
So now that we understand the premise is wrong the rest is pretty easy to straighten out
This narrative is so well-worn that it has even made it onto the GCSE science syllabus
For non British viewers. That's a core curriculum exam taken by all
16 year olds in this country and quite right too because that's what schools teach science
We may not live to see the year 2060, but children of today will they'll be the scientists economists and administrators
Of the future who'll have to deal with salination and annual storm surges and the dislocation of island populations
So what could possibly be wrong with teaching this in school?
Not in an alarmist or emotional way
But as sound practical academic study foreign direct investment in the Maldives has more than quadrupled
since the year 2000
This is very strange behavior from people betting with their own money
Don't they know that their money will be under the sea before long, but of course anyone who checks this claim
Including the smart investor knows that that's nonsense
Before long is actually decades away and that's more than enough time to see the fruits of an investment
After all all assets will depreciate over time with or without sea level rise
So to reap the rewards of an investment you either need enough time to see profitability outstripped
appreciation or you need to know that when you sell the investment years from now even with the era of
Undrinkable water and annual inundation getting closer
You'll be able to offload it onto the second type of investor
People who don't bother to fact-check and who believe that this wild and implausible claim the Maldives
May be under the sea by the year 2030 is actually a scientific prediction
So 20 years from now
They'll be very happy to invest in the Maldives
Despite scientific predictions about salty drinking water on the grounds that predictions about the Maldives going underwater by
2030 turned out not to be true
Most of them won't even bother watching this video showing that no such prediction was made
Well, yes
But the real Maldives mystery is why so many self-professed
Skeptics who watched the video didn't bother to spend just a few minutes fact-checking
To find out whether any of this was true