Getting to space is hard. Right now, it's like going up a mountain on a unicycle with
a backpack full of explosives. Incredibly slow, you can't transport a lot of stuff,
and you might die. A rocket needs to reach a velocity of about 40,000 km an hour to escape
from Earth. To get to that speed, rockets are mostly containers for fuel, with a tiny
tip of payload. This is bad if you want to go to other planet, because you need a lot
of heavy stuff if you want to survive and maybe even come back. So is there a way to
get to space with less fuel and more payload?
A nice thing that solved most of our transport problems on Earth is what you call infrastructure.
Whether it's roads for cars, ports for ships, or rails for trains, we've made it easier
to get to places. We can apply the same solution to space travel. Space infrastructure will
make getting into orbit and out to the Moon, Mars, and beyond easier and cheaper. Great,
but what exactly is space infrastructure? Unlike an Earth space elevator, which is currently
science fiction, there is a simple yet promising technology that does not require new science
or magic materials or huge investments and that has been tested successfully in orbit
already. A cable and a weight, known as a tether. The concept is so simple, it's surprising.
What if we put tethers, hundreds or thousands of kilometers long, into space and had spacecraft
use them as ladders to climb to higher altitudes and gain speed? This concept is known as the
Skyhook. It works even better if we make it spin. The counterweight holds a long cable
in place while it rotates around a circle. A rotating tether slows down its tip relative
to the ground at the bottom and speeds it up at the top like a catapult. This means
that you can transfer energy from the tether and get a massive boost when released, more
or less for free, equal to twice the tether's rotation velocity. Specialized fibers already
exist that can survive the extraordinary stresses a Skyhook would be faced with. To
protect against cuts and collisions from debris and meteorites, we can thread our tether into
a web of redundant fibers. Since our Skyhook would pass over the same spot many times a
day, this would allow small reusable shuttles to catch up with it. Of course, it's not that
easy. At its lowest point, the tether's tip is dashing through the atmosphere at around
12,000 kilometers per hour. Because of Earth's atmosphere, we can't lower the Skyhook too
much or it will get too hot from air friction. So it will dip to a height of 80 to 150 kilometers
and no lower. To match this, we'll need specialized spacecraft that can get to the tether. While
this isn't exactly easy, it's still much cheaper than getting a big tin can filled with rocket
fuel to go 40,000 kilometers an hour. Catching the tip will be a challenge too. There's only
a short time window of 60 to 90 seconds to find a tiny thing in the sky moving at Mach
12. To make this easier, the tip could have a sort of fishing line a kilometer long with
a navigation drone that helps the spacecraft connect. Another challenge is keeping our
Skyhook in orbit. As more and more ships latch onto it and pull themselves up, they use up
the momentum that keeps it in place. If we don't do anything, it will slow down and crash
into the atmosphere. And here we can cheat the universe a bit. The Skyhook is a battery
of orbital energy. It's possible to balance the payloads coming in and being sent off.
Arriving ships bringing humans and materials home to Earth add energy to the tether, which
it can give to other ships departing into space. This way, the tether doesn't lose any
energy. The more we use it, the cheaper it gets. If we're still losing energy with each
boost, we can recover it with small electric or chemical engines that regularly correct
the tether's position. A set of tethers, one around Earth and one around Mars, could make
trips between the planets fast, straightforward, and low-cost compared to rockets. The Earth
tether would sit in low Earth orbit to grab people and payloads and fling them off to
Mars. The Mars tether catches them and slows them down for a landing on the surface. In
the opposite direction, the tether could pick up a vehicle traveling through Mars's thin
atmosphere at only about 1,000 kilometers an hour, not much faster than our airliners
on Earth, and fling it back to Earth to be caught and lowered down. The tethers could
shorten trips between both planets from nine months down to five or even three and reduce
the scale of the rockets required by between 84 and 96%. Even better, people may be able
to travel in relative luxury as we could afford to invest in passenger comfort. Tether travel
would be first-class seats to Mars. Together, tethers around Earth and Mars could provide
the rapid and cost-efficient transportation backbone that would make space travel affordable.
But let's go further. Starting from low Mars orbit, a tether could boost ships to the asteroid
belt. The first craft sent to a new asteroid would need rockets to slow down at its destination.
Subsequent arrivals might find a tether waiting to catch them and send them back for free.
Going to asteroids cheaply is a major factor in opening up the resources of the solar system.
Precious metals and valuable minerals could be delivered to Mars just weeks after they
were cut out of their asteroid. They would be the perfect building blocks for our interplanetary
civilization. But why stop here? Mars moons are very convenient. No other moons in the
solar system orbit that close to their planet. Phobos is so heavy that we don't need to
worry about slowing it down, making it the perfect attachment point for super tethers
just under 6,000 km long. The lower tip would fly just over the surface of Mars and be very
easy to catch. The upper tip can fling ships all the way to Jupiter and Saturn. The same
super tether can also bring the inner solar system closer. Venus and Mercury are a single
swing away. Unlike Mars, they're bursting with solar energy and are rich in minerals.
In the long term, nothing is stopping humanity from constructing a zero-propellant transport
network for the terrestrial planets centered on the Martian moons. Tethers are a comparably
cheap and sustainable solution to making space travel affordable and the rest of the solar
system accessible for exploitation and exploration. Considering that we have the technology to
build them today, there's really no good excuse to wait any longer. Parts of the solar system
are far away, but they could be very close. Speaking of stuff that's hard to reach but
doesn't have to be, knowledge. Our friends from Brilliant can hook you up to a universe
full of explosive ideas and fun courses. Brilliant is a website that helps you tackle science
in a practical way with interactive problem-solving courses and daily problems in maths, logic
and engineering. Each problem gives you all the tools you need to crack complex topics
all by yourself. It's learning by doing, but with your brain instead of your hands.
Use your curiosity to get to the bottom of puzzles and courses about things like classical
mechanics, astronomy, gravitational physics and much more. If you click the link in the
description or visit brilliant.org slash nutshell, you can sign up for free and learn more things
than you can imagine. And there's an extra perk for Kurzgesagt viewers. The first 688
people to use the link get 20% off their annual membership, which lets you view all
the daily problems in the archives and unlock every course. Brilliant helps you end your
day a little smarter. You might get hooked on the experience.