Our home is burning. Rapid climate change is destabilizing our world. It seems our emissions
will not fall quickly enough to avoid runaway warming, and we may soon hit tipping points
that will lead to the collapse of ecosystems and our civilization. While scientists, activists,
and much of the younger generation urge action, it appears most politicians are not committed to
doing anything meaningful, while the fossil fuel industry still works actively against change.
It seems humanity can't overcome its greed and obsession with short-term profit and personal
gain to save itself. And so for many, the future looks grim and hopeless.
Young people feel particularly anxious and depressed. Instead of looking ahead to a
lifetime of opportunity, they wonder if they will even have a future or if they should bring kids
into this world. It's an age of doom and hopelessness, and giving up seems the only
sensible thing to do. But that's not true. You are not doomed. Humanity is not doomed.
Despite the seriousness of the situation, for years, positive trends have accumulated,
and there is finally some good news and a clear path towards our collective climate goals.
Welcome to our TED talk. Please watch this video to the end. Check out our
detailed sources afterwards to learn more. Okay, let's start with the scariest things.
Canceling the apocalypse. Some of the most widely shared stories about climate change
are that it is an existential threat, the end of human civilization, and maybe even our own
extinction event, and that it is basically unavoidable now. But what does science actually
say? As of 2022, the global average temperature has risen 1.2 degrees Celsius compared to pre-industrial
times. Limiting warming to 1.5 degrees was the most ambitious goal of the Paris Agreement,
but we are not likely to meet it. Already with the warming we have today, hot places will get hotter,
wet places wetter, and the risk and strength of extreme weather events increase significantly.
Warming beyond 2 degrees makes all of these extremes more extreme. Extreme weather events
more common, with more ecosystems under major pressure. Some will not survive.
At 3 degrees, significant parts of Earth, especially in developing countries,
might become unable to feed their populations. Heat waves will become a major global issue.
Large-scale natural systems will break down. The scale and frequency of hurricanes, fires,
and droughts will further increase and cause trillions in damage. Poor regions and subsistence
farmers will be hit the hardest. Hundreds of millions of people will need to leave their homes.
In the 4-8 degree range, the apocalypse begins. The hot house Earth, where things change so
quickly that it may become unable to support our large human population and billions may perish,
leaving the rest on a hostile alien planet. A decade ago, for lack of action and perspective,
many scientists assumed a 4-plus degree world was our future, and a lot of public communication
focused on exactly this future path. Luckily, it's much less likely that this version of the
apocalypse will come to pass. If current climate policies stagnate, we're likely to end up with
warming of around 3 degrees Celsius by 2100. Which is scary and tragic and far from acceptable.
But this is actually good news. How? In the last decade, we've seen enough progress that
most scientists now think that we have likely avoided apocalyptic climate change. Although
substantial risk still remains, we can pretty confidently say that humanity isn't going
anywhere. Civilization might have to change, but it will endure. Which begs the question,
what has changed over the last 10 years? And is this really good news? The invisible shift.
You probably know this story. The last decade has been an immense failure for climate policies
around the world. Instead of passing comprehensive binding bills that would meaningfully reduce
emissions, we mostly did nothing. A lost decade with one negative record after another.
And this story is true, and it's one reason why so many people are giving up. But it is not the
whole picture. Despite the lack of climate policies and ongoing lobbying and misinformation
campaigns from the fossil fuel industries, there was a lot of progress. Let's go back 20 years
to see why today is so different. Between 2000 and 2010, greenhouse gas emissions had grown by 24%,
three times as much as the increase in the previous decade. Subsidies for fossil fuels
aimed at promoting economic growth caused a colossal increase in their consumption.
For developing countries like China and India, coal was the cheapest fuel for growth,
while rich countries showed little interest in changing their ways.
In 2010, many people expected these trends to continue. Instead of decreasing fossil fuel use,
its consumption would rise. The next decade turned out to be very different, though.
First of all, coal burning in developing countries like India has slowed down,
or levelled off, like in China. And it's plummeted in rich countries like the UK and US.
Since 2015, three quarters of planned coal plants have been cancelled, and 44 countries have
committed to stop building them. Ten years ago, that would have seemed like wishful thinking.
But today we can say with confidence, coal is dying. It's just not competitive anymore.
Because technologies we thought would remain expensive matured rapidly instead.
Renewable electricity has shown explosive progress. In a mere decade, wind energy got
three times cheaper. Solar electricity is now ten times cheaper. Cheaper than coal or any other
fossil fuel burning power plant, despite the massive subsidies and global infrastructure
propping up fossil fuels. 25 times more solar and nearly five times more wind electricity
is produced today compared with ten years ago, which is of course not nearly enough.
One of the biggest obstacles is the variability of their power output.
Renewables need a lot of energy storage to be a reliable power source, like expensive batteries.
Amazingly, battery prices have decreased by 97% in the past 30 years, 60% in the last decade alone,
which will serve all kinds of green technology like electric cars.
You might say, well that's great, but didn't Kurzgesagt's last climate video
say that while wind and solar are nice, we need nothing less than a fundamental transition of
our global industrial system? Yes, but luckily the shift goes beyond just the energy sector.
Throughout the economy, people are working on improving current technology to lower emissions.
We're rapidly replacing old incandescent light bulbs with LEDs that are ten times more efficient.
In 2020, about seven out of ten new cars in Norway were electric or hybrid. In 2021,
it was already eight out of ten. And the list goes on, from electric heating and better insulation
to ships traveling at half speed to save fuel. Wherever you look, you find scientists, engineers
and entrepreneurs trying to solve some aspect of climate change. Enormous amounts of human
ingenuity are being brought to bear on this problem, with more and more people deciding
to prioritize preventing rapid climate change. Solutions for low carbon production of cement,
electronics and steel, and innovations like artificial meat and carbon capture are in the
works. The more of these technologies we deploy, the cheaper new and better technology gets.
The cheaper they get, the more people use them, and so on. We can see the impact already. The
domestic CO2 output of rich countries is falling without a major recession. Since the year 2000,
the EU as a whole shows a 21% decrease, Italy 28%, the UK 35%, Denmark 43%. But the best news may be
that emissions are no longer necessarily coupled with the economic growth. In the past, this was
an inconvenient truth. To get richer, you had to emit more, which led to fierce arguments between
developing and developed countries about the fairness of reducing emissions while their
populations were still poor. But in the last decade, we've seen that it is possible to increase
prosperity without increasing emissions. Emissions in the Czech Republic dropped 13% while their GDP
grew by 27%. France reduced their CO2 emissions by 14%, while increasing GDP by 15%. Romania saw
an 8% decrease and 35% growth. And even the largest economy on earth, the USA, decreased
emissions by 4% while growing their GDP by 26%. Some of you may call this a numbers trick, that
rich countries are just exporting emissions to poorer nations by moving the dirty parts of their
economies like manufacturing. But even when we account for all of our imported goods, the numbers
still look positive. It's no longer a matter of having to choose between prosperity and the
climate as it seemed to be a decade ago. Developing countries will profit from that because as rich
countries pay for the expensive development of green technologies, they can adopt them more
cheaply. They can skip most of the high emission phase that today's rich countries went through.
We are at the point where not decarbonizing is a bad business decision. And we haven't even
really talked about solutions like carbon capture. In 2000, it didn't really exist. In 2022, that
technology does exist and costs around $600 to remove one ton of CO2 from the atmosphere.
As investment pours in and the technology matures and begins to scale, it's likely that these costs
will plummet over the next few decades. So everything's fine then. Well, let's not get carried
away. All of these processes are great, but not nearly fast enough. We're still doing way too little
and technology will not magically solve everything. We need to use fewer resources and use them longer,
design consumer goods that are repairable and durable and decrease our energy requirements.
We need much better infrastructure, agriculture and cities. It will still be hard work, especially
to get the right policies passed and enacted. But for the first time ever, there are a few trend
lines pointing solidly in the right direction. And now imagine if all of this was achieved without
proper financial and political support. And despite fossil fuel lobbying, just think what
humanity can do when climate change finally gets the political attention and funding it needs.
So is it okay to feel hopeful again? The situation is still dire and serious. So what's the point of
focusing on this side of the story? The trap of hopelessness. Climate change can feel overwhelming
and make your future seem bleak. The sadness and hopelessness that many people feel is real
and very destructive, because it causes apathy. Apathy that is only serving the fossil fuel
industry that is still delaying change however it can. In a sense, they have weaponized hopelessness.
We are now in phase four in the public debate about rapid climate change action.
Phase one was, climate change is not real. Phase two was, climate change is real, but not caused
by humans. Phase three was, climate change may be caused by humans, but it's not that bad.
Phase four is, climate change is no longer avoidable. We are doomed and it doesn't matter
what we do. If we want the world to change, we first need to believe that change is possible.
And we have an abundance of evidence that it is. Changes to our industrial system are gaining
momentum. Technology gets better and cheaper. Climate change has become a key issue in most
free elections. As more and more younger people move into influential positions, they prioritize
climate change and work on new solutions. In 2022, most governments not only acknowledge it,
but set their own net zero goals in democratic and autocratic countries. The results of years
of fighting a steep uphill battle are now clearly visible. The pressure needs to keep increasing
to make sure that the promises made today are actually kept. Climate doomerism is the
equivalent of giving up even though you can still prevent not just the worst case, but also mitigate
most of the bad things, make changes in time to adapt better and prevent the poorest from
suffering. That is why hopelessness and apathy are so dangerous. If the last in many ways wasted
decade has shown anything, then it's the progress is being made. And that dire scenarios are just
predictions, not our sealed fate. As of 2022, based on current global policies, we will end up
in a three degrees world. Now it's our job to yet again prove the predictions wrong, despite how
serious and urgent things are. To turn that three degrees into a two degrees, and then see where we
can go from there. For that, we need hope. And we hope we gave you that today, at least a little.
That you feel that things are serious, but also that you have a future. That you could have kids
without dooming them or the world. That taking action today is worth it. And that despite
powerful industries doing everything to delay it, society is changing. If you need a more concrete
roadmap of what you can do personally, we're working on a follow up video to talk about that
in greater detail. Doomerism, inactivity and weaponized hopelessness are the only trump cards
left for the powers that don't want change. Don't let them win. We're still excited about the future.
And we think one of the best things you can do to keep your optimism and curiosity up is to learn
new things. If you don't know where to start, our friends from brilliant.org have got you covered.
Brilliant makes maths and science accessible and fun with a hands on approach. More than 60
interactive courses like the joy of problem solving or scientific thinking, give you the
tools to crack problems in maths, science and computer science that are all designed to get
your intuition going and give you plenty of experiences. Lessons will surprise you with
storytelling code writing tasks and interactive challenges. Basically using whatever keeps you
interested and entertained. All the content is interactive. Instead of just reading and listening
to explanations, you drag and drop manipulate shapes and diagrams, make selections and answer
questions. This way you learn something almost without you noticing it. And tiny step by step,
you'll build up your long term understanding of science and get closer to your STEM goals.
To start looking at the world of science from a different perspective, go to brilliant.org slash
nutshell and sign up for free. And there's an extra perk for Kurzgesagt viewers, the first 200
people to use the link get 20% off their annual membership, which unlocks all of brilliant's
courses in maths, science and computer science. At Kurzgesagt, we love to create things that seem
impossible at first. Brilliant can help you acquire the skills to do that.
Thank you.