Hello, Internet.
Each final finished, precisely polished video you see stands atop a mountain of material you don't.
Books and papers and sometimes investigative travels,
time lost and confused in the infinite diverging paths of the forest of all knowledge,
writing a script to try to light the way.
The final video takes hundreds of human hours to carefully craft.
The whole mountain couldn't possibly fit in, otherwise there would never be a video.
But what has to be left out is sometimes heartbreaking,
not to mention the easter eggs and little details that are put in, but can easily go unnoticed.
So I'm going to talk about some of the behind-the-scenes in a more casual,
force-myself-not-to-prepare-too-much-otherwise-it'll-never-happen,
director's commentary for crowdfunders who make all of this possible in the first place.
If, when you clicked this video, the thumbnail said Live, then it's live right now.
I'm director commenting, and you can join the chat to ask questions about the newest video.
If there was no Live, then you can watch the archive of previous ones.
So, if you're interested, please click here to sign up and check out the commentaries.
I hope you like them, and thank you.