Hello and welcome everyone. It's time. It happens every year and we're here. It is Eurovision time. We're here for the semi-finals, the live official stream.
We're down to our final three competitors here. Representing Bosnia, Herzegovina. We've got Brad.
Hi. What's going on?
Representing Wales, we've got Drew.
Hi. Thanks. It's great to be here representing the country of Wales.
Yeah. And representing Tulsa, Oklahoma, we've got Dan.
Jeff, you're horribly mistaken. I like the enthusiasm. Let's carry that through to what we're actually doing.
You want to tell the people what we're doing, Jeff?
Eurovision is happening.
No, no, no. Jeff, you were wrong.
No live animals allowed on the stage.
I just saw Kachida Worst right over there.
There is a microphone here.
Yep. You guys are going to perform your songs for your given nation states?
There might be singing. I don't know.
And we are going to choose who moves on to the finals. It's a very exciting time. Of course, the finals are happening this weekend.
There will be a winner.
Yeah, there will, absolutely.
It is a competition.
The winner of Eurovision. And the voting is just a great time of year.
So we're watching the replay of the semi-finals. Is that what's happening here?
Semi-finals part two. We're going to get into this whole stuff here.
We just need to switch the TVs.
No, no. They got it on the right thing. This is the right audio here.
Is this one of the songs?
Yeah, Jason.
Which song is this?
Italy?
This is Italy's?
This is the story of Brighton and Twyla.
This is not a trophy-winning composition from what I'm hearing.
It's nice just to be nominated.
That's nice.
Laughter.
Giving my ten points to getting up and walking out of this room right now.
Oh, you can't.
What is the record here? I believe it's Brad has...
Zero.
One.
Drew has zero.
Dan has zero.
No, no, we played five of these. We played five.
I think it's two, two, one.
You actually do have zero, so this could be your chance.
Mathematically, there are ten of these.
So you could come back and win this overall thing.
Yes, mathematically there are ten.
That's math.
As far as the map, almost unanimously I've seen people tweet to me that we should do,
I think, the snow one, because that has some crazy auction system for getting stars.
That sounds like fun.
I know we have typically done the basic one...
Yeah, we've usually tried to stick to the basic one to try to establish a baseline of the Mario Party experience.
Yes.
But I suppose this is not ranking of Mario Party.
No, this isn't hard science.
Because they are all tied for fucking last.
Look at these guys. They're great. They're like the Snow Brothers.
Do you have these amiibos?
I would.
They're like the Snow Brothers. You take that back.
Look at this little scene.
Fucking Prince Nick and Tom are fucking real video game characters in real video games.
Not sun face and moon face that Hudson fucking cooked up.
Alright, let's do the snow then, I guess.
We're going to be here all night.
It's probably good this room doesn't have any windows.
Fifty turns?
Yeah.
Yes.
Are you sure about this?
This is your last chance.
I hear this is the best one.
Okay.
Yeah.
Here we go.
We're going.
Yeah.
Alright, Wario.
Ugh.
Why?
Because you've got on a race face.
Mike made a game.
Oh shit.
Cheat your mouth off.
Word heard.
Mike, oh it's Mike's.
Well, it's a mic.
Maybe you use the mic.
Does he need the mic?
Is he the solo player?
Probably.
Let's see what's going on here.
One player shouts orders to herd the goombas away from the other players who try to punch
them out of the corral.
Wario, you can say up, down, right, left, or scramble.
We move and punch.
Wait, am I directing the goombas?
Yes.
Okay.
You have a horde of goombas that you want to kill us.
What is it?
Up, down, right, left, and punch?
Wait, you want to give them orders to keep them away from the fence.
What were the terms, the directions, and what was the other one?
Let's see.
Oh god.
Up, down, right, left, and scramble.
Goombas won't listen to orders while they're moving.
Wait until they stop before giving them another command.
You want to keep them in, we want to punch them out of the corral.
If you guys can hear what I'm saying, that's kind of...
Up, down, left, right, and scramble.
Fun is what that is.
All right.
Fun is what they call that.
This is a really...
Yeah, I think you have to push the button on the mic as well.
This looks like Big Boss's Isagar.
All right, here we go.
Down.
Do I have to get all of them?
Left.
It's working.
Right.
Scramble.
Down.
No, down.
Down, you fuckers.
Right.
Up.
They're going right.
Scramble.
Right.
Down.
Almost got it.
Up.
Down.
Whoo!
Look at that little dickhead.
Goddammit.
This game's awesome.
Fuck.
Yeah.
Huh.
Goddammit!
Are you fucking kidding me?
Of course I do.
Dan, you should maybe move off that space.
I want to fucking move off that space.
Are you kidding me?
Oh, no.
It's fine.
Oh, no!
We're just building the Rocky story here.
I want the fire.
We're just building the underdog story.
All right.
Fuck.
Oh, fuck me!
What a piece of shit.
Yeah!
Fuck this car, man.
It is a piece of shit.
Goddammit.
Now do you eat the space that you landed on, or?
I don't know.
I think you go to Bowser's space, too.
Yep.
Give him back, Bowser.
Waluigi's always been good to Bowser.
Wait.
We got it.
You get that?
I thought we did a good job.
Finish!
See, I got a dominatrix printer.
Did you say dominatrix printer?
It's my dream.
I don't know how that works, really.
I'll show you.
Do you refer to your printer as daddy?
No, it's the network name.
I did not refer to it.
I'm not allowed to.
You always speak to your printer when spoken to.
Tells me the printhead is broken and that I'm a failure for not preparing it.
And then I lick the cartridge for an hour.
It tells you how very bad you are at maintaining a printer.
So, so bad.
This seems like a real video game here.
Little Koopa Raptors.
Fire.
That takes forever.
Laser.
Okay.
Missile.
This is so good.
Drop bombs.
So just the little green things we're trying to...
Fire.
What green things?
There's little green things on top of his, like to the right and left of him.
Missile.
They're only on the right now.
Fire.
Laser.
Missile.
Fire.
Laser.
Mario, it's up to you.
Cool boy.
Mario, you've played a lot of shooters.
Arcade shooters.
You can do this.
Fire.
No time limit.
Drop bombs.
I got one more to get, Jeff.
Look out for fire.
Laser.
What the fuck?
Get out of the way.
Yes.
So it's not the shadows.
What the fuck was with the bombs?
The fire comes up afterwards.
I love this microphone.
It's working for you.
Nothing but dodging, right?
Yeah, just move.
Really scary.
Eh.
There's like a blast.
Oh boy.
Oh, you fucker.
It's my way.
Yes.
Okay.
Do we all lose all of our coins?
Oh, that would be awesome.
Wait, what?
Why are we all in cages?
That would be great.
Because we're going to die.
Is this the Temple of Doom scene?
This is your life and it's ending one Mario party at a time.
Why are you fucking kidding me?
I hope it's everyone.
Do we all lose?
Fucking Bowser.
Man, Bowser's the great equalizer.
Wow.
Fuck.
Same as lame.
True.
The Mario party mantra.
They're all lame.
It's impressive if you're the only player to choose that button.
Your platform will rise.
Ooh.
You fucking.
Wow.
Man.
And we're also not going to use all of the buttons on the controls.
Top tier mini game design going on in Mario Party 6.
I don't know, what if we just had to even pick a button and if no one else picks it,
they win?
I don't know, man.
Don't look at my controller.
It's a psychological mind game.
Go.
Never guess what I picked.
Yes.
I'm going to pick A.
I bet he's not going to pick A.
He's lying.
I picked A.
So did I because fuck you.
I'm going to pick A.
I'm done with you.
I like how much time they give you to pick a button.
Yes.
Dammit.
Oh god.
Jeff, what are you picking?
A.
Yes.
Wait.
We should stop both picking L.
I would say.
We're good at that.
Yeah.
We're really good at that.
Mind games.
Alright, yeah.
Rock, paper, scissors for idiots.
I think this is a bad game.
Oh yeah?
Yeah.
Hiddifold.
You're both right.
Choose one of the three ropes.
Whoever chooses correctly,
swings to the platform with...
So if neither of us swing to the platform,
the fly guy will rescue one of us.
Sorry Drew.
So randomness on randomness in that case.
Can't call it random.
Both of you play randomly,
but if you're bad at being random,
we will randomly choose a winner.
Wait.
This is what I'm hearing.
Very dramatic.
Finish!
This was a mistake.
Risk no reward.
Video games were a mistake.
Good names.
Across the board.
Every one of these games.
No.
Not really.
Because it's like fucking...
I don't know.
What are those names again?
Bill Hill.
I don't know.
Done.
Do you think they come up with a name
and then they make the mini game?
What would Bill Hill be?
Bill Hill would be a fucking bunch
of bullet bill launchers,
and then there's a fucking hill,
and you want to stay on the hill,
but there's a bunch of fucking
bullet bills launching at you
to make it hard to fucking stay on the hill.
Alright, let's keep this going.
I think we can do this.
What's the next mini game?
You work at Nintendo, Jim.
Congratulations.
You guys are Mario Party developers.
In a perfect world,
we all could have shared
in screwing over Dan equally.
Don't worry, because now it's his turn.
Don't make the worst turn.
Waste one of his items.
Do it.
He's going back.
Don't do it.
I don't want to do that.
What are you doing?
Could you burn one and...
Oh.
That was a level of savagery
I was not prepared for.
Of course.
Oh wait, are you...
Is that the same one Brad tried to do?
Fuck.
Yes, we are losing stars.
That's a big number.
That's a really big number.
Yeah, but I mean, where's...
I think I'm pretty far away.
He's pretty far.
You're like...
That's a big roll.
You're all the way in the top right corner
where the chomp is.
Am I?
Oh my God.
Wow.
I take all y'all's shit.
Man.
Holy shit.
That was some run.
Dan, give me a sticker.
Here, I'll give you some money.
Hang on.
Oh, he's running.
While he's running.
I guess we'll be right back.
Golly.
Jeez, man.
Got some stuff.
Wow.
I'll say.
We've been breaking in your absence.
No.
People said you were playing Waluigi
and that you chomped a star away from me.
No, we didn't.
I'm with Twitter.
People are no fun.
Bring snacks for everyone
and you guys have betrayed me.
No actually.
No.
Are you kidding me?
No, actually these are not from me.
I got a tweet from SkullPanda1 on Twitter
saying there should be snacks waiting for you guys
in the lobby.
What?
I don't know what this is.
Really?
SkullPanda1.
Okay.
This is my stuff.
Man.
A lotta.
It's a strawberry and a lime-arita.
Here's your Snickers.
Thanks.
That's the stuff you bought.
That's the stuff I bought.
This is all SkullPanda1 here.
I don't know what we got.
I just feel like it's gonna be
just like a bag of fucking dog crap.
Here you go.
For use with Mario Party.
It's a bag of human skulls.
Oh boy.
Double Stuck Oreos.
Oh I see.
Yes.
Oh no.
Oh my god.
What a pleasant surprise.
Jason?
Oh wow.
Wait, what?
He knows Jason's order too.
Fuck.
Yes.
Jason into some pharmacies?
I'll take that.
Oh yeah.
I did not know that.
Oh man.
And then whatever this stuff is.
Some fancy water.
I don't know.
Fancy water.
Perrier.
Oh my god.
It's gonna be Oreos and nachos.
Slim cans.
Throw the lime slim cans in there.
I don't think I've ever had Perrier before.
It's sparkling water.
Is that it?
Wow.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Someone says Red Vines.
I say how high.
Yeah.
I'll have the Red Vine.
That's probably about it though.
Not even heating up the cheese, huh?
Nah.
Fuck it.
Oh no.
Oh.
Mm.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Well, let's see that cheese.
Keep going.
It's a Mario party.
I hate myself and want to die.
Fuck.
Yeah.
That's no good.
Yeah?
Yeah.
All right.
I get the mic.
Do I get it?
Should I put like three Oreos in my mouth before we do the mic game?
Yeah.
Probably.
This is my favorite air album.
I think I could do two safely.
All right.
Let's read the rules and I'll put the Oreos in.
One player speaks commands to reach the goal.
The other three will try to hit them with a spiny.
That's me.
Forward, move back.
I'm just back.
Right and left.
Forward, move back.
You move the cursor and throw a spiny ball.
So, okay.
So I'm just standing there.
All right.
Are you ready?
Whoa.
Oh.
Right.
Whoa.
Okay.
Just a decent amount of lag there.
Let's move back and forward.
Oh, man.
You got a chain reaction?
Diana Reeves?
Warner Freeman, right?
Warner Freeman.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anybody see that Point Break remake?
No.
I think that kind of came and went.
I've never really been a bit...
I was not a huge fan of the original Point Break.
I've never seen it.
I don't have a reverence for it the way some people do.
Yeah, there seems to be a real like cult following around that movie.
I dated the girl whose brother is named after Patrick Swayze from Point Break.
All right.
Bodhi is her brother.
Wow.
His parents must have really fucking sucked.
That's his name is Bodhi.
That's a fucking real like just...
Nope.
At a certain point playing this, I forget that we're actually like broadcasting this
to thousands of people.
Like it draws me in to that degree.
Yes.
I think that is a testament to the game.
It is utterly riveting.
I think it's a testament to the game.
And you're drinking.
Also true.
My game.
Yes.
Hooray.
Give me that goddamn microphone.
Do you want to do the Oreo challenge?
No.
It worked great for me.
What was that?
When you put two Oreos in your mouth and try to do this.
Is this fucking mine?
This one is dumb.
Up, down, left, right, scramble.
Hey, this is monkeys from Yoshi's Island.
They eat the watermelons and you can steal it from them.
Left.
Go left.
What do you mean?
How do you punch?
Go right.
You're just knocking them out.
Scramble.
This is tough.
Go down.
I'm wasting all my time on one of them.
Go right.
Go up.
Now we're making progress.
Scramble.
Go down.
Oh, we got this.
Go right.
We got this.
Yeah, we got it.
Fuck.
Go up.
I don't know.
Everyone take a goomba.
No.
Go down.
Fuck.
I'm about to sprint for it.
Fuck this shit.
You won.
Don't care.
You're just joining us.
We're entering the back third of...
Yes.
We could bring in commentary for one of these.
I'm Byron Saxton.
Stop.
Go.
Got some goombas.
Wow, you really only get one shot at that, huh?
Fuck.
I say blue.
Man.
Most fucking asinine way to fucking count this shit.
Are you kidding me?
Wow.
Fuck you.
You gotta pick up the mic, Jeff.
You gotta press the button.
Bite my ass.
Alright, game, mic, game, mic, game.
Good.
Three unplayed mini-games and Poke Punch-out.
That's...
Poke Punch-out.
Fosse & Poke Punch-out.
Poke Punch-out was alright.
That's fucking bullshit.
Memories?
Because that was the first one we did.
Fucked it.
Fuck you.
Oh man.
Oh my God.
I feel like I should text my girlfriend and tell her not to make dinner because I ate
too many orios.
Hurray the 5s are dancin'.
KellyHerox!
Dancing 5s.
Whoo!
Oh man.
I mean, Oreos are kind of like dinner.
Yeah.
You have to hit a button.
Or you just want to watch the 5s dance.
Whoo!
I mean, I'm okay with that.
55 spaces.
Here we go.
So your spaces, your bonus you got for being in last, puts you directly in front of a chain
jump hut.
Fuck that.
Wait.
No.
That.
What the fuck is going on here?
That's me taking your coins.
That's what that is.
Everything that happened sucked.
Getting coined up.
Oh.
What?
Mike.
Dang it.
Meh.
I guess that's my room.
It's like it knows.
What a shitty.
Laser, missile, laser, drag your goombas, fire, drop bombs, fire goombas, laser, missile,
laser, laser, drop bombs, drop bombs, fire goomba, goomba goomba, fire, fire, laser, laser.
All right.
Great.
Awesome.
Well, we're done.
You're a superstar.
First of three.
I'm a star.
Great.
Yeah.
Thank you for putting the game on, Twilight and Broodbree.
This is the final star count.
Just skip the score screen.
Yeah.
Completely.
Probably.
I don't know.
Can you do Mike games?
Who's ready to go again?
I mean, fair or square?
Wow.
What a day it's been.
Thanks everyone for joining us.
Wow.
This has been really fantastic.
I can only hope that you enjoyed watching this as much as we enjoyed playing it for you.