So, have you ever wondered who actually invented the internet?
Some people have become zillionaires thanks to the internet, but all they did was invent
clever ways of using the internet.
So the person who invented the internet should be a gazillionaire equivalent to say God,
shouldn't they?
Who should get the credit then?
Was it a British geek in a Swiss underground lab?
Maybe.
Clever Americans threatened with nuclear annihilation by the Russians?
Nice idea.
Or was it French scientists who decided to call their computer network the l'internet?
Interesting.
Or was it thanks to a myriad of smart scientists working on something they knew was useful
but didn't realize would be so big?
Well, let's try and get some facts straight.
There's the internet, a whole bunch of computer networks connected to each other, and then
there's the World Wide Web, a way of making it easier to share information using all those
interconnected computers.
The internet as we know it today was at least 40 years in the making.
One popular but wrong story is that the internet was developed by the USA, so they had a communication
network that would survive a nuclear war.
According to one of the founders of the first network, the ARPANET, in the 1960s, this first
network experiment wasn't about communication at all, it was about optimizing processor
usage or timesharing, which basically meant that scientists could share computer power
too.
That was because until the 1960s, there was basically no network, you had big machines
called mainframes, which sat in a room and processed computing tasks one at a time.
With timesharing, these behemoths could process several tasks at a time, which meant their
power could be used by several scientists at once.
And obviously, once you start connecting computers together, you start to wonder about
what you need to do to make communications between them easier.
Scientists around the world were trying to solve this problem.
So let's look at some of the other key concepts that were developed elsewhere.
Starting with packet switching.
In Britain, there was a commercial network developed by the National Physical Laboratory,
but which never really got off the ground because it didn't get funding.
They did come up with the idea of packet switching, a way of avoiding congestion in busy networks
by cutting up data at one end and putting it back together at the other.
The French also played a role.
They were working on a scientific network called Cyclades, but they didn't have a big
budget, so they decided to work on direct connections between computers as opposed to
working with gateway computers.
Now, as an aside here, this admittedly isn't very scientific, but according to one theory,
a spin-off of their research was the word Antacnet.
But you don't have to believe it if you don't want to.
So now it's the early 1970s.
There's quite a lot of computer infrastructure, but communication is awkward and patchy because
different networks can't talk to each other.
TCP IP solves this problem.
The TCP IP protocols form the basic communication language of the internet, which labels the
packets of data and makes sure that even though some pieces of the same data take a different
route, they all arrive at their destination and can be reassembled.
Networks really began communicating with each other in 1975.
So you could argue that was the beginning of the internet.
Email was also very important.
It was developed for ARPANET in 1972.
Most internet traffic in 1976 was email, because academics thought electronic post-it notes
were dead cool.
With networks that could talk to each other, communication was becoming easier.
But all this communication was just text-based, and it was pretty ugly to look at.
In the 1980s, a brick called Timothy Berners-Lee spent time with CERN, the European Organization
for Nuclear Research, where physicists are trying to work out what the universe is made
of.
He wanted to manage the scientists' information and make it possible for them to share and
interconnect their work easily, making progress more likely.
He did so by inventing an interface using HTTP, HTML, and URLs that made internet browsers
possible.
He called his browser the World Wide Web.
So he didn't invent the internet, but he did invent the web.
The first ever website which he created was at CERN in France in August 1991.
So once the initial infrastructure was in place, the key technologies had been invented,
internet message boards exploded in the 1980s, the phone companies saw the commercial potential
of digital communication, web browsers spread like wildfire in the early 1990s, and ordinary
people discovered email.
Then, the internet expanded rapidly and steadily and became workable for the masses from about
1995.
Hold on, didn't US Vice President Al Gore invent the internet?
Ah, no.
And if you read what he said exactly, you'd know he never claimed to have done.
But many people credit him with energetically pushing legislation that encouraged the spread
of the internet.
The internet exists because we need to communicate, and most of us like doing it.
That's why humans have become the dominant species on Earth.
You could argue that the internet is a natural evolutionary step and a manifestation of that
need.
It wasn't invented by anyone in particular, but when the building blocks were put together
by all those cool scientists from all over the place, the internet became a communication
tool, a retail tool, a research tool, a propaganda tool, a spying tool, a shopping tool, a dating
tool, an entertainment tool, and a way of skiving off work while making it look like
you're working or studying, which is what you may be doing now.
Ultimately though, you're communicating, especially if you leave a comment, and that
might make you a better human being.
Thanks for watching.