Good afternoon! I hope everyone is having a lovely war on Christmas.
If you're anything like me, you're all dressed up with nowhere to go.
Literally the first Christmas where I don't get to see my family
in all of my 36 years on this earth. Yeah, I'm fine with that.
This episode was brought to you by my publisher asking
when I'm going to do a content of promoting my book before Christmas.
Just under the wire. You can see it right here along with some other
gift ideas for the SFF fan in your life. It's only mostly
extremely nepotistic. I had a run-in with the oven if you're
wondering. So I wanted to do a Q&A for a while but
the thing about books is they take a lot longer to get through than
movies and generally when they're released it's not like everybody reads
it all in the same week. It's a very slow burn.
But it's been about five months so I figured I can
break this down into a no spoiler discussion or at least what I
consider no spoilers. Like if it's if it's in the
you know blurb on the jacket then it doesn't count as spoilers.
Spoilers section where I actually talk about the content of the book in a
spoilery way. Finally sequel stuff at the end and I
don't want to say it'll be spoilery but it would be like on the level of stuff
that you read like on the jacket blurb which incidentally has not been written
yet. So the way I did this was through
Twitter because that required the least amount of effort on my part.
What software did you use to write slash organize all the world building going on?
Is it a bunch of Google Docs? More specialized things with Scrivener?
Both. I use Google Docs for a lot of it like especially keeping track of like
timelines. Like there's like I guess sort of the
macro timeline of um you know alien civilization and when
we hit what milestone like becoming spacefaring becoming interstellar
you know becoming post-natural and then there's the micro timelines like
you know the human family trees and when so and so was born and what year they
were born and when they went to school and how they met.
But mainly I use Scrivener. I just have to have a really clear road map before I
actually do it and I use Scrivener for that and I find
Scrivener very good for organizing massive projects especially one
like this that is like a combination of epistolary novel and
uh regular prose novel because I have to categorize the different sections
especially in the sequel which has multiple points of view. In your video
talking about your book deal you mentioned reasons why it didn't sell in
it having to do with publishing trends. Would it be a spoiler for the sequel if
you went into those reasons now? No. But generally when we talk about
publishing trends publishers want something that is
similar to something that has already done well
because like Hank Green's book uh An Absolutely Remarkable Thing was like
the only comp we had when we had on submission. Besides his book there
weren't really any other you know best-selling sci-fi
novels that were also sort of contemporary
real world grounded type stuff. Publishers want to buy things that are
similar to things that have done well within the
last five years and um in terms of like commercial
science fiction there weren't a lot that were similar.
Did you deliberately set out to write basically the book Transformer should
have been? I mean if you're talking about the movie
uh maybe. I feel like so much of my adult life has
been shaped by frustration with Michael Bay and I
think like one of the things that like I kind of got obsessed with with the first
Transformers movie after it came out was that
it did kind of set up a really interesting premise which was that
okay aliens show up but the world doesn't end what now?
Especially after the second one um the the worst one
arguably no actually I think maybe they're all really bad but like the
second one ends with like the fallen being like we're here we're
queer we're gonna kill you but then you know the world doesn't end
so like what then and they kind of they kind of tiptoe up to like doing
something interesting with it like how in the third movie there's like
you know John Turturro hanging out with Transformer refugees in Cuba.
Buy my book! Buy my book! I think it is also very fair to say that
uh a lot of it was shaped by frustration with Mr. Bay's Transformers franchise.
When describing Korra's outfits did you try to create an iconic look
for a potential adaptation? Yeah sort of what I thought were the most
visually I don't know 50s b-movie scenes. I keep
describing this uh tiered chiffon maxi dress from the
1970s and um I don't know why I decided to go with
that and not something more like you know 1950s um
but I think it was just it was kind of like a janky
like a janky version of that um you know something white and flowing and damsel
but also like cheap and polyester in 70s. When will
you write an omegaverse novel? I don't think I need to someone already
wrote an omegaverse axioms in fanfic. It's on AO3. No I haven't read it I'm
not allowed. In regards to Korra's experience with linguistics in college
have you ever taken any linguistics courses?
Yes at NYU I had what they call a um concentration
which is what it is when you don't have enough credits for a
minor but you had enough where they're like
ah we could put that on the degree somewhere whatever. Axioms in ready read
very much like the natural disaster films of the 90s. How much of this was
intentional? I didn't really set out to do that but I guess
some of that was inevitable because so much of like the plot and the structure
and the character dynamics was very much inspired by movies like that
and like towards the end of the process like after the book sold and while we
were in revisions like I kind of allowed myself license to
just like go all in on it. I've seen Independence Day probably more times
than I've seen any other movie. Let's just own it you know and it's like
there's a lot of Men in Black in there um
there's a lot of Invader Zim in there it's sort of like which is which is
funny because I saw that Jonan Vasquez posted like
check out my book haul and that was in it and I was like oh no
Pathetic humans fleeing in terror at the sight of Zim!
Nobody even looking at you! It's a show of respect!
Their stupid eyes can't handle all these!
Because I was watching the new Invader Zim movie uh
Enter the Florpus and as I was watching it I was like holy shit I forgot
how much Invader Zim um kind of crept into like the world
building it's almost sort of like uh Invader Zim played straight like
which I'm sure Jonan Vasquez would be horrified by
like even even uh Kaylee Donaldson of Pajiba pointed this out
it's sort of like ampersand is almost like a if Invader Zim
was competent but where are the flames I can't rule the world without cool
flames shooting up behind me
now that it's out can you talk about what it was like watching bumblebee with
this in your pocket bumblebee came out right before
the book went on submission I loved bumblebee because it was you know
the Transformers movie so the only good Transformers movie but it had a lot of
similarities and when I was watching it with uh Lisa for the first
time this one um she we were in the movie
theater and she just kind of like whispers to me like
this is a lot like your book and I'm like oh it's
they stole my idea not the other way around but the but the really funny
thing was uh when we were um the first blurb
Saint Martin's Press sent me that was like the cover copy
this thing it basically like it read it read
like the plot of bumblebee so much that it included things that were
in the movie bumblebee but were not in my book
for instance like we are being pursued by
like evil John Cena it's like but no that's not the plot that's not what
happens oh my god if the Axiom Zen series was adapted for
tv would you rather see it made into live action or animated
I don't know it depends on who's making it if it was animated I feel like it
would have to be like either anime or anime style you know
because it should feel a little aged up but yeah I
don't know I think I think that really depends on who's at the helm
and what the budget is because I think the thing is like if it was animated
for the content that it is it would probably be cheaper than live action
because like geez I I kind of doubt we're ever going to see
a live action version what language slang phrase do you use often that was
off limits due to the period setting that you chose
the truth is um I was a lot more careful about that for the sequel like I have an
entire thread that was neologisms that I started to write but had to cut
and I guess they would tend to be like internet thing like
uh you know like we can't use doge like much alien very invasion or stuff
like that even though that's already dated I also
kind of had a problem of like sort of in the opposite direction of like language
that was a really common then um but is like considered super
problematic now like as a for instance um like I think I had a
uh a scene where Felix Cora's brother calls something gay
in like a derogatory way which you know a 13 year old in 2007
absolutely would have um but like you know
we had these conversations about like do we want to be true to the period or keep
in mind who's reading it now and you know defaulted to the who's reading
it now even though it is accurate that doesn't mean it needs to be there
do you think your history of doing video essays will influence more folks to make
video essays analyzing your work is that an exciting prospect or a
dreadful one I mean I guess it's not really relevant to me because I
wouldn't watch it I don't I don't think it's
fair I get that not all authors are like that but I think just from an ethical
standpoint I shouldn't engage with stuff like that
like that's not for me that's for other people to have
discussions that said I think it would be more
likely for me if only because the type of viewer I have and the type of
audience I have is more likely to be interested
in video essays how much of your theories did you have done before it
queried I mean I had definitely had it mapped out by the time it sold
and we pitched them five and they bought one and they bought two more after the
pre-sale numbers for the first one came in so
thanks for that so basically three out of five are under contract and whether I
get to finish it I guess is contingent on how well the first three
do so a question for everyone else who has
read the book does everyone envision Lindsay as Cora while reading this
and if so what is Lindsay's opinion of this that sucks honestly
you know this is like something that most authors don't have to deal with
so I guess as an author I would like to die I would
like for people not to be thinking of me and other things that I've done
while they're reading it but obviously like you know like I say death of the
author for the most part is not a very applicable to the real world
theory that's just not realistic where do we send fan letters
um here this is my business email super early but what's your dream cast and
director for an adaptation Christian Slater would make a great
Nels oh yeah that would be I never thought of that yeah he'd be
perfect the only casting that I thought was kind of a good idea was
Pedro Pascal as Nels but you know we probably couldn't afford him
what build is Cora and Oblivion dark elf
uh mage but also she doesn't really like Oblivion because Oblivion sucks she
prefers Morrowind because it's better
should I read Axiom's end no it depends on what you're into
in your how to get a book deal video you said your agent pinpointed the issue
with why agents thought they could not sell this
and you fixed and suggested that you might share one day are you ready to
share it now are you ready one weird trick that
was keeping me from getting a literary agent was
Cora's age in the original draft she was 19 not 21 and you might be
thinking oh well really what
so the first chapter in the final version she's at work she's a temp
uh and she's dropped out of college but in the first draft she was in school she
was like it you know in college rather than
at work and so that first chapter felt a little too ya curious so it's not
really a deal breaker for like character age in genre fiction
it's more just like how it's presented and so the fact that she was
a little she was young and the first chapter was at school
felt a little too ya curious and so we aged her up
and that was it adding two years to her age
what advice would you give to beginner slash novice writers
for one thing don't make my mistake and over revise
i think another is um once you get to the editorial phase
except that most editorial notes are suggestions they're not mandatory
and editors don't expect you to incorporate
all of them let alone even most of them depending on the notes would you agree
that axiom sin falls within the horse girl genre
yeah since the setting is irl does that mean that lindsay ellis exists in the
universe of the setting you know i'm gonna go with no i'm just
gonna keep it simple no i was never born in this universe
the green brothers exist though what part of axiom sins were you unsure about
but you found turned out really well i guess sort of the dynamic between the
two leads i didn't know if people would buy into it
and that was kind of another reason why i was so
squirrelly about the actual content of the book um
because i didn't want to market it on almost sort of like this
borderline romance because publishing be sexist and i
but you know by that same token it's not for everybody
like it is a hard definitely not for everybody
and so i think the result is that a lot of people read it based on this sort of
like government conspiracy thriller blurb
that probably would not have if they knew that the
main substance of the book is not that and i guess the people that
did like it you know responded to it in the way that i was hoping so
i guess that but by that same token again
not for everybody the physicality of the aliens feels very vivid and visceral
while thinking of their anatomy what kind of visual and material references
did you make for yourself did you settle on their general shape
from the start or was it a longer process
it was kind of both because it's like i always had an idea of the
general shape that was always there from the very beginning but the details
um changed a lot and kind of only really settled towards the end
with the various characters having different opinions on the truth is a
human right debate where on that spectrum do you fall
uh regrettably i think i'm probably a centrist
what i think is what is true matters not as much as how the truth is
framed because any truth can be weaponized
but on the whole i think like it's it's more complicated than just
full transparency because you know again any true thing
can be framed in a way that ultimately furthers a uh completely
unrelated political agenda are you a pantser plotter or in between
hard plotter um outlined a lot do you naturally write in third person
or was this a choice made specifically for this book
was first person ever considered no i don't know i think in a weird way
first person feels more stylistic to me than third person for some reason
i guess if it's if it's in in my head anyway if it's in first person i feel
like there needs to be a narrative reason
like who is this person telling this story to and why
and i know logically that doesn't make any sense like third person is
just as much of a stylistic choice but i guess if i was going to write in first
person i would need there to be a reason like a narrative reason of like why this
person is telling their story how do you think your experience in
screenwriting influenced the novel well i feel like it has a very
screenwriting style i i feel like my prose is very utilitarian
and you know that's just a taste thing some people like that some people don't
um also just like in terms of structuring it
i think more than anything the structure like basically like
um points of attack inciting incidents act breaks
um different sequences taking place in different things and having different
tensions um framing it like that was very
influenced by screenwriting and apparently that is
becoming increasingly common what would you change about the first book
and how will you be adapting what you learned in the second book there were
times when i i kind of deferred to um
editorial um i think maybe to the book's detriment where
you know they'd ask for certain things and i'm not gonna say what they are
because then you're gonna be like oh where is it
but like i do it and then i you know in hindsight would realize like this feels
kind of forced but then i'd kind of leave it
i think the other thing is reading it too much like reading
it too many times and revising it too many times i think
that is i think that's definitely a trap first time authors
fall into whereas you know it's your first time and you want it to be perfect
but then like uh the result is you read over the same
sentences over and over and over and then they just start to lose meaning and
then you stop being able to contrast construct a sentence that
um you know is is flows well i noticed a lot of criticism
about like the writing style especially like in the first
third um and i think part of the reason it does feel kind of clunky is because
i read it too many times and i revised it too many times
and the result was that like you know the the words just stop
carrying meaning so for the sequel for the most part when i finished a draft i
would just put it away and do not look at it until it came
back from editorial with like here's what you need to do
the thing is like when you're doing revisions if you've looked at the
sentences too many times each time you look at it it becomes
harder and harder to restructure it into something that like
flows better or sounds better
what was the biggest most surprising change from your original draft book one
i guess it depends on what you consider the original draft
when i compare the trunked version to the final version
a the trunked version was like way too chicken shit about the you know primary
relationship therefore it was very sterile
and very no emotions allowed and the other biggie was where the
exposition happened and um there would be like these big
exposition dumps towards the beginning um which i you
know upon reflection i was like holy shit this
you know it works so much better if like when she meets ampersand she knows
nothing you know and so she kind of has it's a
journey of discovery rather than having all the information ahead of time
but i guess also like in in those super early drafts
what kind of ended up being the meat of the book wasn't really there at all
so like all these sort of getting to know you chapters that happen like in
the middle and in the bunker just did not exist like
even a little with regards to the ending when
ampersand goes but i'm not human i was like smiley face and then frowny face
can't decide which feeling to have how do you view it
i think that's correct that's the correct response to have
did ampersand lie about the known number of space faring species
no but absolutely take everything he says with a grain of salt he obviously
tends to omit truths if not outright lie and there are definitely some things in
the first book that he lied about stop fucking lying our amygdalins and
their super organism the great filter no ampersand was
telling the truth about that there's a lot of talk in the first book
about like the great filter and why in a sort of statistical likelihood
standpoint this other intelligent civilization
popped up relatively close to earth like only about 100 light years away which
you know in the grand scheme is like really unlikely
but no he was telling the truth about that the superorganism is not the great
filter although that will be elaborated on considerably in the sequel i remember
that ampersand said he had two sim files was that chefo and obelisk or was he not
including chefo because he's dead uh that was not
including chefo because he's dead he has two one is obelisk the other
that is a really good catch of a throwaway line because it is a
very important throwaway line and yes that will be explored considerably
what were the amygdalins evolutionary ancestors like and how do they get their
energy since they don't eat um well they do eat a little
christopher pauline's new book talks about this concept of like a
a human shit mind which is basically like a brain that is
you know kind of fed nutrients constantly
um and in this case they can kind of almost have like a star trek replicator
inside their own bodies so it's kind of like that basically like
similar or those that exist in the bodies of a similar get their energy
differently from everybody else because like you know espress and all the other
ones they don't have like these grand superpowers then that's basically
uh because they uh have a different form of energy
but it's it's kind of same ish and the simple answer is
i went with uh matter antimatter fusion and as for their ancestors
um i don't know if i'll ever really get the opportunity to go into this because
i have this whole like you know what kind of star did there's
planet well not because like in my mind it was like a moon that
ordered like a gas giant around like a um like a like a k-type star a red giant
um so the atmosphere would look very different and the greenhouse effect
would be very different the air pressure would be different
um and that's sort of being like why our sun is very like yeah you know it's just
like way brighter than they were evolved for
and that's part of why their eyes are so big
um that and that and big eyes is cute and alien
i guess it's like kind of a complicated question that i always kind of have in
the back of my mind while writing but i don't know if it'll ever actually make
it to the page because it may never be relevant to
the actual prose but the simple answer is like
you know ampersand mentions that it like the social group
being very more similar to gorillas than like monogamous humans
and their ancestors were also like strictly herbivorous which is part of
why humans are so like ah okay just like i kind of imagine like
if humans had evolved as like strict natural vegetarians and then
coming in contact with aliens that ate animals that would just
be like oh my god that's awful but i guess that's more subtext than
anything at the beginning of part four korra mentioned she can hear better
infliction even a slight accent with ampersand's voice
uh why does she hear it clearer before the bond i think that's just because
that doesn't really have anything to do with bonding that's just he improved the
the text to talk speech to sound more natural
he did not create that software that's just mac and talk and he figured out how
to like you know apply it to an earbud that he made but
really it's just over the course of the novel he improves his serie that
doesn't really have anything to do with uh any mystical et soul bonds
having gotten to the end and read the special thanks i have to ask is this
novel a low-key starscream fanfic i get that a lot and it's kind of a
weird question to me because i think on a personality level ampersand and
starscream have nothing in common i'm stupid i'm stupid
i guess they are both kind of jerks but like they're you know they're very
different characters um ampersand was not in any way
inspired by starscream i'd say obelisk was a little though there is a hidden
starscream in there i've seen one person catch it
how much of you is in korra and what other sources did you draw inspiration
from her personality i guess off the top of my head not a lot
to be honest like i guess we're roughly the same age
but her mid-2000s experience was very different from mine
and and like the way she handled things was very different from mine like she
was very unambitious her family is nothing like mine
i was extremely ambitious and like honestly
borderline entitled like i did not know how to deal with failure like i still
don't i also i also like to think i'm a lot funnier than she is
like i'm more witty than she is i guess in a weird way i think
i have more in common with ampersand and this sort of combination of being
really controlling really emotionally unavailable and borderline authoritarian
it in a weird way it's easier to pick out your similarities with an alien
character because he is representing something more
symbolic than just like a human character who has a regular
human personality and that can be a little more difficult to suss out
did you base nils off of any whistleblower in particular
yes it's julian Assange he was like i could try to be like oh you know he's
a combination nah it's julian Assange sorry
let me backpedal that a little bit his function in the world as celebrity
whistleblower is based on julian Assange his
personality is not or at least it wasn't intentional whenever i was
writing it way back in the day i like went way out of my way to
not research just on his life or i didn't want to read any interviews he'd
done i didn't want to know about him as a person because i didn't want
nils's personality to be based off of julian Assange
but inadvertently they definitely ended up having a lot in common
bless you for not killing the dogs and also for letting us know they were safe
i'll say this i will never kill a dog in a book that is the lindsey ellis
promise did you intentionally starve korra so she had to eat the whole plate
i ate the whole plate someone on twitter was like if there's no whole plate joke
in there i'm gonna be really disappointed and i just kind of was
like oh yeah that'd be funny so i just push it put it in there on a whim i
didn't really think about it and so now half of my twitter mentions are about
how you put the whole plate in there the whole plate the whole plate
what was the inspiration for ampersand's appearance would you ever consider
official art getting made i keep wanting to the inspiration is
sort of like this combination of um like just things i like to look at
things i find inherently like appealing not necessarily beautiful like
just striking i guess like i really like spiders
um i really like praying mantises we have a bunch of pet spiders and mantises
and also this sort of like hypothetical evolutionary ancestor of like
what does a bipedal herbivore look like because um
and maybe you'll have things like kangaroos or iguanodons
so i guess like structurally it's sort of a combination of like an iguanodon
and a dragon also because i just i like dragons
like if there's a dragon in a book there's a dragon in a thing
i'm here i'm here for that dragon is the is it a good dragon is it a bad dragon
is is it are we dragon shifters or are we are we riding dragons are we fighting
dragons i don't care i'm i'm i'm here for those dragons that's
part of why there's there's something a little draconian
in the way that they look not draconian dragon like
that was another word i got dinged for like no that's not what draconian means
and there was also incorporating like insectoid and arachnoid
characteristics not because they felt alien well yeah because they felt alien
but also just because i i i like them like they are appealing to
me personally but i got a mantis in my panties
okay from what i can tell korra is kind of a self-insert so in what ways is
korra different from you besides her dad of course
do male authors get this question i don't think she's a self-insert any more
than any like everyman style protagonist is i guess as
i mentioned earlier i don't really have much in common with her
personality at all like she's good with kids i am not you
know despite being an oldest her way of coping with the world is to kind of fade
into the background you know she's a she's more of a water
sign i guess she's kind of conflict averse i am very
confrontational i guess she's she's latina i'm not she's
catholic i'm not um never had any problems you know
supporting myself never had to move back in with my family
never had this sort of contentious relationship with my parents
certainly never called them by their first name
like you have everyman characters that are kind of a fish out of water because
like they need the world explained to them
some of the time and you know that is a really common thing especially in genre
fiction you know but that doesn't mean they're
self-insert it just just means that the reader needs an entry point and i guess
i kind of wonder like if if if if korra in commercial
fiction is considered a blank slate what wouldn't be how many dicks does
ampersand have
that's a complicated question um bex living in a post natural body and
being born sterile um he doesn't have any um reproductive organs but if he
did he wouldn't have a penis it would be a novapositor
but i guess the corollary to that is uh he does have some limited
shape-shifting ability obviously so i guess it depends on how
creative he wants to get he could have infinite well not
infinite but as many as you can fit did i imagine a parallel between the
hospital scene at the end of axiom's end and
the end of twilight well i mean you can make all the parallels you want
like you know and i have seen this a lot it wasn't intentional but i guess the
other thing i would say about that is uh you know convalescent scenes are pretty
common at the end of thrillers um because you know if someone gets hurt
a lot of times the denouement will take place in a hospital
um like you know even bright ends in a hospital
uh like uh the prequel to this uh futuristic violence and fancy suits
ends with a very similar convalescent scenes like very actually
similar um so i just say like yeah but i would
also argue that ending thrillers in hospitals is not at
all uncommon was it always the plan to end the first
book in the way that you did i thought the last line was fantastic and it left
a really strong impression you know that's funny because i get
really mixed reactions on the on the ending
i i was kind of surprised by that because i yes the ending was always
exactly what it was like there there was always a bondy moment at the
end of act two beginning of act three and this conversation that they have in
the convalescent stage in the hospital basically you know
where normally you know et leaves at the end of the book he decides to stay
and yes that was even from like super early first draft that was always the
ending um and i guess the thing that surprised
me is like some people really were like yes
what a great ending and some people were like wow that was so abrupt that just
ended and i was like yeah i guess i you know i was i was kind of surprised by
the people who thought it was abrupt because i in my mind i was like
it was very very set up
my friend's ex-boyfriend's roommate had a pug named monster truck and i
thought that was funny
sort of so a civilian is not going to travel
your friend or group is kind of an outlier and should not be counted
generally similars or in emperor stan's case an individual that is
stolen from basically the body of a similar are the ones that
explore because those are the bodies that are built to
withstand different planetary like gravities and air pressure and stuff
like that but being these sort of cyborg things
they don't need a lot of room they can just kind of go into stasis for you know
years and decades on end so yes they do have starships but they
kind of would more look like you know an apollo capsule like they're
really really small means that you know requires less thrust
to get up to light speed and and that is its whole own complicated thing if you
want to talk about like you know thrust and energy and getting up to
light speed and why that is impossible and why that would need so much energy
after a certain point so yeah despite the fact that their
bodies are pretty big their starships are
pretty small the majority of the mass is going to be
devoted to uh energy and energy production
the actual living spaces are really really small but the ones that are here
are not on earth they are safely away in orbit where humans cannot fuck with them
aside from ampersand who is your favorite monster boyfriend
i mean come on it's the beast he fell and i landed on my ampersand was
surprised at the speed humans had advanced in a few hundred years
was the precursor species to amygdala slower than humans in that regard
they were definitely slower they were way slower and uh
part of that is sort of like nature related
one of the sort of dynamics is uh ampersand being really surprised that
we go to space not because we have to do it to survive which is what
their ancestors did they only kind of started exploring um space as a as a
need for survival um meanwhile humans do it because it's
there you know because and that's just very like why would you
do something so dangerous if you didn't absolutely have to
and they're also kind of like naturally less competitive they're much more
risk averse you know meanwhile humans are just so dumb like
so it's not necessarily that they were less
problem-solving but like the things that make humans
the things that made our technology turbocharged like
being really competitive and being really risk-takey
um they didn't really have so that's part of why
they were a lot slower uh advancing wise why they would have
advanced over a period of like from developing writing to you know
cracking the space barrier would be like 20 30 000 years as opposed to our
six-ish five six thousand years was the genome's fake plan from the start or did
you side on it later yes uh very first draft genome died
do you have an era appropriate song for your couple ship i don't know
my instinct is like some cheesy 80s song like
this who funds nils or does he sell merch like
gay frog pills um he's not to the gay frog pills
stage of his career yet i wouldn't put it past him but right now he's funded by
donations i'm curious about the moment ampersand and korra's feelings changed i
have a solid idea for korra but less solid for ampersand
was it realizing she was also afraid of her own government yeah
actually i think yeah because i think that is like uh the most
traumatizing thing that ever happened to him was like being expelled from the
body politic you devoted your life to how do you feel about fan fiction and
fan art of your work which fan art has been most like your
vision um i feel positively about it i support it but i also feel like i
shouldn't comment on it because um you know i don't want to be like this
person is correct but you you know i think whatever you have in
your head is valid like you know your vision of the thing
that i wrote is it's not wrong although i guess my main
differentiation from in the fan art that i've seen it's like
the little i've seen of obelisk has him darker than um the rest of them like no
they're all the same color they're all kind of this silvery white thing
um and uh ampersand has a really big head
relative to like the rest of his body who are some of korra's favorite music
artists and songs um which of them would ampersand find
interesting or intriguing well to the latter half of the question
none of them they'd all kind of sound the same to him but for korra's favorites
i actually have a playlist for that and i'll link it in the description is
the similarity in concept between awoken and axioms and coincidental
did you find that your experience writing a human girl eldritch horror
romance translated well i get yeah i guess it's sort of like
awoken was the i was when you do an ironic version of a thing you kind of
want to take seriously and not just me because i think like
you know lisa's book is has similar to mine in a lot of ways
especially with its relation to awoken we had a jokey joke version of a
thing where we eventually wrote a book that
took a similar concept and took it seriously
would you like to write a meeting between korra and her dad
they will meet eventually will a member of either of the two absent
space-faring species sister species species x appear in the sequel
and will we acquire names for those species yes and yes
well they'll appear in this series let's leave it at that
will korra's linguist skills become relevant in the sequel it seems a little
odd that the protagonist is a linguist and yet she never has to do any of the
translating thanks to ampersand's auto translator
well a linguist is not a translator first of all those are two
very different things but the main reason i had her
like have a very rudimentary understanding of linguistics is i wanted
her to be able to put words to just how
little we understood and how for the most part
the study of human linguistics doesn't really apply to alien linguistics like
for instance a huge component of human linguistics is
just mouth sounds and um the way uh words are constructed or syntax so it
was it was less about her having a skill set that she could apply
so much as her being able to put words to
the sheer limitations of being able to apply
human language to this hypothetical alien language
i had the pleasure of experiencing your novel through the excellent audiobook
reading performed by stephanie willis and oliver thorn will they be reprising
their roles in the sequel um probably although the sequel will
have uh three readers i hope i think is there anything you had
to cut from axiom's and that will be in the sequel
um it's mostly world building stuff there was some stuff in earlier drafts
that was a reveal in the first book but i realized would be a more powerful
reveal in later books and then there's just some like world
building stuff like the conversation on gender
got shunted into later books so yeah i mean
not a whole lot it was mostly world building is there smut in book two or
are you going to make us wait longer yes
but whatever you're thinking you're probably wrong
since bush resigned who's the next president going to be
well it's dick cheney it was kind of surreal because i had to
type the words president cheney like at least a dozen times would irl kaveh get
along with book kaveh um yes uh but
mostly because both iterations uh kind of get along with everybody joke
question when is korra gonna get it in already
so let me just say of like the uh beta readers editors and agents who
have read the sequel um eyebrows have been raised is it
easier to write a sequel having established a core cast and
concept are the answers to narrative questions or problems more obvious
in my experience it was so much easier part of that was because i kind of came
up with the concept for the sequel before i came up
were really nailed the concept for the first one because in my mind
the first one is mostly set up to me um i know i know like the meet cute people
will always kind of like that the most but like really the
first one was like set up for where i wanted to go
the sequel has two point of view characters instead of one
and um i for some reason found that made it
so much easier like being able to hop from different points of view and also
just having done it before you have a much better idea of your process
so yeah i found the sequel so much easier to write than the first one
will sloop john b make an actual appearance in the future
yes could we expect a sequel to follow korra and ampersand or some new
characters both straightforward question are we
looking at a time skip between books if so how long
yes small time skip uh about three months when did you start planning
and writing the sequel to axiom's end again before the first book was even
written and i guess after the second one comes
out i guess i could talk about like what it was because primarily it was like it
was a character dynamic thing but mainly it was just this sort of
like broad premise idea of how does society cope
with this first contact scenario um where the world doesn't end but also
nobody really has any information like how does society cope with that and i
guess that was the thing that interested me more
than um anything that's really in the first book are we going to be seeing
more of that asshole journalist kave uh
i guess yeah here's the biggest spoiler of all yes
um kave is not only a major character in the second book he is also the second
point of view character and that's my big reveal and yeah and
so i guess for those of you who listens to my podcast
i guess we'll talk about that next year i did not know i was going to have a
podcast with a guy named kali oh you've seen cloud
alice right unfortunately oh my god do you love cloud
cloud oh my god no wow so that was a lot like that went on
long enough that the sun has completely changed
places but anyway thanks for watching you can
buy this for your uh monster lover friend in your life for christmas or
hanukkah or new year's or persian new year whatever whatever you
happen to celebrate or for the hell of it
it's not like we're going anywhere anytime soon if you don't want to
support the big box sites you can buy it from bookshop.org which
gives part of its proceeds to help support
independent bookstores during the pandemic you can also get the audiobook
on audible or libro fm or wherever you get your fine audio books or consider
any one of these fine potential christmas
gift for the sff lover in your life or yourself and
that's it for this year uh at least in terms of video content
and the sequel is called truth of the divine it'll be released
there is it's in the fall all right that we they don't have a date officially
it's sometime in the fall probably and yes so here's here's to a
better 2021 it's own it's only uphill from here
right