Black hole stars may have been the largest stars that ever existed.
They burned brighter than galaxies and were larger than any star today or that could ever exist in
the future. But besides their scale, what makes them special and weird is that deep inside,
they were occupied by a cosmic parasite, an endlessly hungry black hole. How is that even
possible? Black hole stars take the weirdness of black holes and go beyond to break everything we
know about how stars form and grow. They were only possible during a short window of time
in the early universe, but if they existed, they would solve one of the largest mysteries
of cosmology. Black hole stars were excessive any way you look at them. The most massive stars today
may have about 300 solar masses. A black hole star had up to 10 million solar masses of nearly
pure hydrogen. Let's take a moment to look at what this means visually. The Sun, Wesson,
L.L. Pegasi, the largest star, and finally the black hole star. Its scale is beyond words,
over 800,000 times wider than our Sun, 380 times larger than the largest star we know today.
And far below its surface is a black hole, growing rapidly as it devours billions upon billions of
tons of matter per second. Normally, stars are born from gigantic clouds, collections of thousands
or millions of solar masses of mostly hydrogen. In these clouds, matter starts to accumulate around
the densest spots inside. As the spots get denser, their gravitational pull intensifies and they grow
faster. Eventually, they generate so much heat and pressure that they ignite fusion reactions
and a new star is born. But this puts a limit on their size. Nuclear fusion releases enough
radiation energy that the surrounding gas cloud is blown away. The new baby star can't gather
more mass. From now on, the star is living on the edge between two forces, gravity pulling in,
trying to squash the star, and radiation created by fusion pushing outwards, trying to blow the
star apart. After millions or billions of years, the core runs out of fuel and the balance breaks,
destroying the star. But black hole stars were very, very different. The beasts of the early
universe. A few hundred million years after the Big Bang, when the universe was much smaller,
all the matter in existence was much more concentrated. The universe was much denser
and hotter. Dark matter was a dominant player, forming giant structures called dark matter halos.
These dark matter halos were so massive that they pulled in and concentrated unimaginably gigantic
amounts of hydrogen gas becoming the birthplaces of the first stars and galaxies. Epic clouds of
hydrogen formed, some as massive as 100 million suns, more than the mass of small galaxies.
In this unique environment that will never exist again, the enormous gravitational pull of the
dark matter halos drew gas into its center and created extremely massive stars. As we said before,
when a star is born, it blows away the gas cloud that created it. But these titanic gas clouds in
the early universe was so large and massive that even after their birth, more and more gas piled
on the newborn star, making it grow to unbelievable proportions. The young star is
forced to grow and grow and grow, getting more and more massive until in some cases, it reaches up to
10 million times the mass of our sun. Crushed by gravity, its core gets hotter and hotter,
desperately pushing outwards, trying to blow itself apart, but to no avail. There's too much
mass and too much pressure. The balance is impossible to uphold. Like a supernova on
fast forward, the core gets crushed into a black hole. Normally, that would be the end. Today's
stars go supernova, a black hole forms and things calm down. But in this case, the star survives
its own death. A tremendous explosion rocks the star from the inside. But it's not enough. The
star is so large and massive that not even a supernova can destroy it. But now it has a black
hole for a heart. It's tiny, a few tens of kilometers in the center of a thing the size of
the solar system. The monster grows. Stars are born from ever faster spinning and collapsing gas.
And so they also spin. When a black hole is born from the core of a star, it keeps its angular
momentum. This means that matter that gets drawn in doesn't just fall in a straight line,
but instead begins orbiting the black hole in smaller and smaller circles going faster and
faster. The result is an accretion disk where gas orbits at nearly the speed of light. Only a small
amount of gas actually falls in at any given moment. Basically, black holes put a lot of food
on the table and only nibble at it. But the matter trapped in the accretion disk doesn't have a good
time. Friction and collisions between particles heated up to temperatures of millions of degrees.
Actively feeding black holes have accretion disks that are incredibly hot and powerful.
This heat from the disk further restricts how much a black hole can devour just like the core
of stars. The super hot material creates radiation that blows away most of the food within its reach.
So even if a black hole had access to as much food as it designed, it can only grow slowly. A black
hole embedded inside a black hole star is different. The enormous pressure surrounding it
pushes down matter directly into the black hole, overcoming all restrictions on how fast it can
consume. This process is so violent and releases so much energy that the accretion disk becomes
hotter and releases more radiation pressure than any star core ever could. Enough to push back
against the weight of 10 million suns. An impossibly dangerous balance has been created.
Millions of solar masses pushing in, the angry radiation of a force-fed black hole pushing out.
For the next few million years, the black hole star is consumed from within.
The black hole grows to thousands of solar masses and the bigger it gets,
the faster it eats, which heats up the star even more and causes it to expand. In its final phase,
the black hole star has become over 30 times wider than our solar system, truly the largest
star to ever exist in the universe. The intense magnetic fields at its core spew out jets of
plasma from the black hole's poles, which pierce through the star and shoot out into space, turning
it into a cosmic beacon. It must have been one of the most awe-inducing sites to ever exist in the
universe. But this also marks the end. It becomes too stretched and the accretion disk within too
powerful. The parasite destroys its host, blowing it apart. A black hole with a mass of 100,000
suns rips its way out to hunt for new prey while leaving behind nothing but a star carcass.
The supermassive question. If black hole stars existed, they could explain one of the greatest
mysteries of the universe. The supermassive black holes we see at the center of galaxies
are just too big. They shouldn't be possible. Black holes born from regular supernovas can be
a few tens of solar masses at most. And because of the process we explained before, they grow
slowly after that. If black holes merge, they can form slightly larger black holes of over 100
solar masses. It should take billions and billions of years to make black holes with
hundreds of thousands or even millions of solar masses. And yet we know that some supermassive
black holes already had 800 million solar masses only 690 million years after the Big Bang.
Black hole stars are a sort of black hole cheat code. If they formed very early in our universe,
and the black holes that emerged from them were thousands of solar masses,
then they could be the seeds for supermassive black holes. These seeds could take root in the
center of the earliest galaxies, merging with others and drawing in enough matter to grow
quickly and reliably. Very soon, we may be able to verify their past existence. The James Webb
Space Telescope is turning its sensors to explore the farthest reaches of the universe, looking back
in time, back to the early universe that we couldn't see before. So with luck, we might be
able to witness glimpses of these tragic Titans in the brief moment between their formation
and destruction. Until then, let's do the visual journey again, just for fun.
Stars are big, black hole stars, bigger.
Planning a long term project like the James Webb Space Telescope requires some serious budgeting.
But even personal finances are a nightmare to manage on your own. That's why we want to
introduce you to Rocket Money, the sponsor of today's video. Just as space exploration
projects are planned by professionals, your finances deserve professional attention too.
Rocket Money is an all in one finance platform that helps with managing expenses and saving
money. You can use it to cancel unwanted subscriptions, lower your bills, create budgets,
monitor your credit score and create smart savings accounts. The feature we like best is
canceling subscriptions. The platform identifies recurring charges and helps you cancel the ones
you no longer want. No need to go through long hold times with customer service, you just click
cancel within the app. You can also upload screenshots of bills that you want to lower
and Rocket Money will get to work negotiating your bill for you. Join the 3.4 million members using
Rocket Money to optimize their finances and download the app today. You can get access to
features like budgeting for free and unlock all features with a premium subscription. Rocket Money
makes it easier than ever to spend less and save more. Basically, managing your money doesn't have
to be rocket science. We know you've been waiting for a long time. Let's reveal the next limited
edition pin. It's our universe to scale. About 10 to the power of minus 35 seconds after the Big Bang,
the observable universe was only the size of a marble before it expanded. Pre-order is available
for only 72 hours, so you can order it now and then never again. Add it to your pin collection
or start a new one. Pin number three will be revealed soon.
And as the year 12,022 is slowly coming to an end, just kidding, time flies by way too fast,
we'll take a short break to recharge our batteries. Thanks to all of you out there
for all the love and support. We wish you a peaceful and cozy turn of the year.
See you back at full throttle in January.