Let's try a quick quiz. These pictures show the aftermath of four different disasters
a tornado, an earthquake, a hurricane and a flood
question is which is which? Just pause the video for a second to figure it out
okay not too hard was it? answers will be at the end
what this quiz tells us is something that Bible preacher Kent Hovind
has yet to figure out about the history of the earth
you're right Kent
I wasn't there. The problem is you weren't there either
none of us was there so how can we best work out the earth's history
follow Bronze Age beliefs, follow our hearts
make it up or do what you did with the photos
and look at the clues that these events leave behind. After all
deducing what happened in the past is a process we go through every day
if we weren't there we have to work it out by observation and deduction
each sedimentary rock on earth for example
tells the story of how it was formed and under what conditions
geologists can identify ancient earthquakes and floods
just as you can identify recent ones but this knowledge wasn't gained overnight
for centuries people didn't question the biblical version of creation
but in the 18th century the Age of Enlightenment
curiosity led some leading thinkers to take a closer look at the rocks that God had made
and the more they looked the more things didn't add up
many of the rocks they saw were in layers and made of the sort of material
you'd find at the bottom of the sea
okay but why was some of these sedimentary layers
at odd angles or on mountain tops or bent out of shape
why were the layers made of different materials
underneath the top sedimentary layers the picture got even more complicated
in 1788 the man called the father of geology
James Hutton saw a geological formation that seemed impossible
at Siccar Point in Scotland he found this set of almost horizontal sedimentary beds
sitting directly on top of an almost vertical set
and this formation wasn't unique it's called
an angular unconformity and geologists soon found angular unconformities all
over the place
by the mid 19th century two principles had been established
it was clear that sedimentary beds that were once at the bottom of the sea
must have been uplifted of course the effect of these uplifts
and their opposite number subsidence's are enhanced by the rise and fall of sea
levels
as polar ice caps grow and melt but a rise in sea level alone doesn't explain
how sedimentary rocks can be folded
and lifted several miles high some unseen force was acting on them
once uplifted the rocks are subjected to erosion by wind and water
silt sand and mud are washed into the rivers and out to sea
where they're deposited slowly building up the sedimentary beds that will become the
rocks of the future
so angular unconformities weren't that weird after all
the lower beds were laid down under the sea with material eroded from the land
over time and under pressure water percolated through the deposits
precipitating minerals that cemented the grains together
then the solid beds were lifted up and deformed
now above sea level wind and rain eroded the rocks
forming a soil at the surface after a period of time sea levels rose
and covered the beds once again more sediment was laid on top
and the sea levels fell and the beds were exposed
nearly every feature they'd seen in the rocks of the past can be seen in the
deposits that are being laid down today
showing that this was a long and continual process
that took millions of years so early 19th century geologists had to forget
their preconceived ideas of a 6,500 year old world
and a 4,000 year old flood instead
they followed the evidence but although they understood erosion and sedimentation
the frequent uplifts were a puzzle by observing and analyzing the rocks of the
Appalachians in the 1850s
American geologists deduced that a deep trough in the ocean floor
had accumulated sediment over millions of years and then been violently
uplifted
they called this trough a geosyncline and they soon found
other mountain ranges in the world that had been formed in the same way
but they still had no clue as to what caused them
then in the 1960s researchers made a discovery that transformed our
understanding of the earth
and its geological history the theory of plate tectonics concludes that we live
on pieces of crust
floating on partially melted rock as they drift around the earth's surface
it's likely these crustal plates are driven by convection currents in the
earth's upper mantle
thicker crustal plates made mostly of granite
make up our continents the oceans mostly fill the lower and thinner crustal
plates made of basalt
in some places these plates are moving apart
and new rocks well up from the earth's mantle to fill the gap
in other places they slide alongside each other
and elsewhere they collide buckling at the crash site and throwing up huge
mountain chains
now the uplift could be explained and it fitted exactly with the geosyncline
model
the deep troughs were in fact the boundaries between
oceanic and continental crustal plates accumulating sediment over millions of
years
as the ocean closed it brought two continents into collision
thanks to precise GPS measurements geologists can now see the process
happening
the continents are indeed moving at about the speed your fingernails grow
as Africa and Europe collide the Alps rise about one millimeter a year
and as India and Asia collide they force up the Himalayas five times faster
plate tectonics also showed that earthquakes
aren't the action of a vengeful God they're the buckling and jarring along
the edges of the crustal plates
so if we look at the earth today we see processes that fit perfectly with the
rocks we find from the past
we can see and measure uplift identical to the uplift of the past
we can see how material is slowly eroded and deposited
and it matches exactly the deposits of the past
we can even see the same patterns and layering of the rocks today
as in rocks millions of years old sometimes the sedimentary patterns are
repetitive
if for example deposits are laid down in a seasonal cycle
sometimes currents are gentle and the sediments show distinct rippling
shifting ripples in stream deposits and sand dunes
lead to a structure called cross bedding and we can see the result of floods
annual floods catastrophic floods local floods
each type of flood leaves its mark and leaves clues as to how strong it was
how long it lasted and what sort of material it carried
we can see a number of different floods at different times in the past
going back hundreds of millions of years if a global flood really had happened
just four thousand years ago
it would not go unnoticed and finally take a look at this place
the Peak District of Derbyshire in Britain several meters down this coal
which is the compressed remnants of a hot swampy forest
go further down past a layer of hard grit
and we find a coral reef which means that further back in time this cold
moorland
was once a warm tropical sea the reason is simple
the evidence shows that around 350 million years ago
the European crustal plate was much further south
and low-lying areas were covered by a warm coral sea
then sea levels fell the area became a river delta
and the coral was buried under sand and gravel millions of years later sea
levels dropped further
and the Delta turned into a swampy tropical forest
over the next hundred million years the European crustal plate
moved slowly northwards to its current position so to geologists there's no
puzzle as to why we find the remnants of three completely different environments
in the same location it fits perfectly with what we know about crustal plate
movements
erosion and sedimentation faced with two hundred years of solid and well
researched evidence
creationists have come up with a few theories of their own to counter it
I wanted to do more on the wild theories of these Noah's arkists
but was so staggered at the outlandishness of their claims
that I decided I couldn't give it adequate treatment in the time I got for
this video
so I'm going to make another video especially for them
now let's go back to the quiz at the beginning
unless you recognize these pictures I can assume you weren't there when these
disasters happened
and neither you nor I witnessed them but just like the geology all around us
each of these photos has clues and by using our frontal lobes
the reasoning parts of our brain we can indeed work out what happened in the
past
you