Citizen Kane is a film many scholars will tell you is the greatest of all time and some of them have even seen it
So they must mean business. It was genuinely quite revolutionary
It's credited with inventing or at least popularizing many cinematic techniques that are still used today, including the jump scare
Everybody remembers that one scene where you suddenly cut to a cockatoo screeching just before it was to wake up the audience
It's the entire significance of the cockatoo and a lot of it really holds up
What's weird is you expect it to be a stuffy old thing vintage and prestigious and made for the amusement of old-timey people who?
Don't think like we do today, but it can get properly funny and energetic at times hot take just putting this out there
Citizen Kane
Pretty good movie. It was the feature film debut of writer director and wine salesman Orson Welles
Even while it was being made Kane was something of a rarity
Despite being made by a first-time director the production company he was under contract with RKO pictures the studio famously behind King Kong and
Citizen Kane had given Wells final cut privilege
This is a movie term referring to who gets final say over the film that actually gets sent to theaters
This is a level of artistic control not normally given to first-time directors
If a director doesn't have this privilege the executives and producers at the company often make their own changes for commercial
Personal or other reasons and can override the creators wishes for their work
Wells used Final Cut to make a film seen by many nerd betas as the greatest ever when Wells next film with the same studio
The Magnificent Ambersons had mixed test screenings Wells made small changes
But remained confident the work was good and would be received better on a full release
However RKO felt otherwise and due to various contract negotiations
Wells had given up Final Cut privileges while Wells was working on another film in Brazil
RKO made extensive edits to the film including reshooting the ending to be completely different and cut 40 minutes out in Wells own words
What's left is only the first six reels
My whole third act is lost because of all of the hysterical tinkering that went on and it was
Genuinely lost too to save space in the film archives the removed segments of the film were destroyed
the creators ideal version of The Magnificent Ambersons is gone forever the released version of Ambersons is regarded by all four people who've seen it as
One of the best films ever and perhaps even better than Citizen Kane, but that only makes the whole thing more horrible
We can only imagine what it could have been
This was the beginning of Wells long fight for creative control over his projects a fight
He seemed to lose most of the time Wells went on to make lots of other films during his career and some of them are
Still really good, but in many ways a lot of them were never truly his
Wells was open about things he wished he'd done differently or more ideal versions of his films
He even considered doing a new ending of Magnificent Ambersons 30 years later with the surviving actors
But these truer versions of his films never surfaced
Wells I argue was ahead of his time here what he was yearning to do was make
Directors cuts in the modern era the idea that a film will get a director's cut is almost taken for granted
In fact, it's so widely accepted that the director's cut is the most authentic version of a film that some fans of the DC superhero
movies are asking specifically for a Snyder cut of Justice League under the impression that this would
Inherently be the better version of the film than the version that some other later
Director would have made tens of thousands of dollars have been raised for charities in the process of fans
Demonstrating their desire to Warner Brothers now. I quite like a lot of Zack Snyder's films myself
The first step is admitting have a problem
And I'd love to see his version of Justice League and also unsee the version that Joss Whedon witty
Dialogue to himself all over
But I can't help but notice that we seem to now be living in an age
Where you can't just dislike a film and move on with your life
It's an opportunity to become even more engaged to give even more of your time to something you didn't even like in the hopes of
Getting a newer better version. So how did we get here and
Our directors cuts all that different that much of the time or isn't it somewhat bizarre to expect a director to relive a finished work?
In order to make a slightly better version of something that was already completed and released
And as a director really the main authority on the most ideal version of a work
Let's look at
let's look at some examples of directors cuts and how they're different from the originals and if they're actually that much better and
Just generally go on an adventure of discovery for what all this means for how we think about art in the modern era
That's that's pretty good. Doesn't it? Welcome back to scanline
Put succinctly a director's cut is a version of a motion picture that is edited according to the director's wishes and that usually
Includes scenes cut from the version created for general distribution
Wikipedia says Blade Runner was the first film to ever use the phrasing directors cut in marketing
But but the page doesn't actually cite a source to confirm this. So thanks Wikipedia
It's excellent excellent work there as the questions of creative control grow increasingly culturally pertinent and profitable
It's become more and more common for films to have a second release as a new
alternative version one more in line with the directors original wishes a sort of final cut privilege in retrospect a
Shocking amount of films have directors cuts now, which gives the impression they serve a creative need that goes unsatisfied in the original process
But creative control is more of a vague conceptual idea than a thing whose effects are truly measurable
Let's look at some tangible examples of differences between cuts and why they can be important
We might as well start with Blade Runner since it apparently started all this cite your sources. God damn it
Ridley Scott's
1982 sci-fi dystopian speculative fiction science fiction film blade run everyone knows what Blade Runner is
Why am I explaining Blade Runner is a very good movie? I think I've heard it's good
I've got a copy here in my editing program and I'm skipping through it looking for footage to use and wow, it seems great
It's got flying cars and a cool gun explores complex questions about personhood and what it even means to be human
It's got music. It's good. There's
some eyes in it and
Some eyes here and here this guy loves talking about seeing things with his eyes and then later he tells this guy
But all the stuff he's seen
Whoa, if I didn't know any better, I'd say there's some kind of theme going on here foolish Ridley
Don't you know themes are for book reports get all these images and ideas out of here before you poke someone's eye
Yeah, oh no
I'm doing it the movie had mixed reception upon its release to quote Brian J
Rob's guide to Ridley Scott critical reaction was decidedly mixed the New York Times called it muddled yet
Mesmerizing Time magazine said the film like its setting is a beautiful
Deadly organism that devours life and the Los Angeles Times complained blade crawler might be more like it got him
Oh fuck him up Sheila the film while good had some confusing choices and strange problems
There's a lot of beautifully subtle
Storytelling and world-building where the viewer is given the chance to think for themselves and pick up on what's happening by paying attention
You know the score pal. You're not cop your little people and yet there's this terrible voiceover
And I'd rather be a killer than a victim and that's exactly what Bryant's threat about little people meant the voiceover
Explains away everything even remotely subtle and it sounds like Harrison Ford is bored out of his mind
there's a lot of really beautiful storytelling like when Deckard retires a female replicant and
Looking at her body feels genuinely awful about what he's done
The audience can see plainly what hunting down creatures who are effectively human and have done nothing wrong except want to live longer
Has done to him
But then the voiceover comes in just to make sure you know that's happening
Just in case you don't like being trusted to think the report would be routine retirement of a replicant
Which didn't make me feel any better about shooting a woman in the back. Oh
Deckard feels sympathy. I wouldn't have known
It's not like there's an actor in the frame showing me or anything by far. The worst one is legendary
We get this incredible moment of humanity from Roy Batty
Theoretically the antagonist of the movie as his lifespan runs out and he talks about the beauty of all the things he's seen
It's one of the greatest moments in film history. But hey, guess what decides to ruin it?
I don't know why he saved my life. Maybe in those last moments. He loved life more than he ever had before
Oh
I think that guy likes being alive
Deckard and Rachel prepare to escape together and in a very tense moment
Deckard finds proof gaff has been in his apartment a calling card of his is left in there
then they leave and it's incredibly tense and suspenseful as the doors close and
Then suddenly after all this noirish tension and dystopian storytelling and eternal night and rain and neon BAM
upbeat music bright skies clean air
Deckard and Rachel are taking a nice drive in the woods and that crappy voiceover tells us actually Rachel was a special replicant who doesn't have
a built-in death date
Tyrella told me Rachel was special no termination date. Oh
Sure. Yeah, this ending doesn't feel weird at all in the last 30 seconds of the film
It all turned out to be okay, just a complete whiplash and why is that unicorn there?
So it was fine really good even but clearly flawed soon after its release
There was speculation that the studio had meddled with production
I mean that ending is literally just b-roll borrowed from The Shining a so-called work print of the film not entirely finished version made during
The editing process had been shown to test audiences and was speculated to have been significantly different and then edited down and in the early
90s, it started being shown in a limited theatrical run branded as a director's cut though
Scott had no actual say in this version's release either and publicly disowned this version the work print wasn't a finished version of the film
For example, it was missing the horrendous voiceover, which is obviously a positive thing to miss
There are no closing credits and it just ends on the words the end
But more importantly it doesn't the end with a horrible story ruining tacked on happy ending
It ends in the elevator with Deckard and Rachel with all the horrible feelings of uncertainty and doom that come with not knowing what happens
Next and that Rachel probably doesn't have long to live even if Gaff spared her the unicorn thing is still weird, though
I guess Gaff is just a quirky guy who likes to spare people and do origami to be fair
I'm a pretty big fan of sparing people
I even showed Kurt mercy even though he showed me no gratitude for it
The work print was surprisingly popular and the differences were lauded as positive ones
This caused Warner Brothers to begin work on a proper director's cut
Well, not actually a director's cut someone else was put in charge of doing it and Scott just got to provide notes and consult on it
Warner Brothers seemed to be banking on the idea of releasing a director's cut and all the ideas of creative freedom that
Implied to fans and film buffs but not in actually giving the actual director that actual freedom
The director's cut is so much better than the original when trying to explain what the differences actually are
There aren't exactly that many major changes if you just list them out largely it's about what's not there anymore
There's no voiceovers whatsoever and the happy ending has been removed
It's amazing what bigger difference the lack of voiceover has though
It lets all the actors and performances breathe instead of being told what to think about something
They're simply being shown it and expected to think for themselves and that's really powerful
Hey Shannon
Yeah, okay when you're editing this bit
I want it to slowly digitally zoom on my face
While I get emotional about how good Blade Runner is and you know
We can play like some knockoff tears in rain music. We can get Zoe blade to do it. It'll be great
It'll be really funny reference Harris. I don't I don't think that works in a video essay
Yeah, but I want it and I'm the director. Yeah. Well, I'm doing a lot of the editing and I might not edit it like that
Maybe in the final cut of this video 20 years later, you can finally achieve your dumb vision. Oh, I get it
That's very meta
And I mean honestly he's like speaking as your co-writer the parts of the video that you wrote are full of holes in your research
Like the cockatoo scene in Citizen Kane isn't the first jump scare
It was most likely popularized by cat people in 1942 with the lootin bus. There's a scene with a bus
It's the first ever like well-known jump scare
Yeah, but it's a funny joke in it and we get to explain the cockatoo and that's pretty good
It's a it's a very light-hearted opening. It doesn't have to be completely true. Oh
Now I'm explaining my joke. I spent ages convincing myself. That bit was funny now. It's ruined
By the way, what happened to the footage of me driving to McDonald's for 15 minutes and talking about how much I love tapes for
The last video. Did you just take it out?
Am I gonna have to start a petition to release the Harris cut of the VHS episode of Scanline
Is that really gonna have to happen now? You know what?
Forget it. I'm cutting this whole part out. It interrupts your explanation of the director's cut and honestly, it's a little bit indulgent
What no, you can't do that. My overly indulgent directors intent is being violated. You can't just
But most importantly and I can't stress enough how cool a change this is
Midway through the movie while Deckard plays idly on his piano. He begins to have a dream and he dreams
about a unicorn
Holy shit. I mean, holy shit. What a small simple change and yet the difference is amazing
I mean firstly finally someone in the movie based on the book do androids dream of electric sheep has someone having a dream in it
But more importantly now the origami unicorn gaff leaves behind means something because how could gaff know Deckard's dreams?
This implies that maybe Deckard is also a replicant who believes he's human with implanted dreams and memories. It's still ambiguous
Obviously, I mean maybe gaff also dreams about unicorns humans do don't they this ambiguity to me
At least is the point of the film ultimately
It doesn't matter whether Deckard is a replicant because he would still be equally a person
human in all but name and it's only in this cut many years after its release that this point really gets to be made and
All this stuff is brought up by the simple inclusion of a daydream about a unicorn
It's kind of amazing how much a simple change just a couple of seconds of new footage
Can impact the overall meaning and value of an entire film?
I think this better than anything else in any other film can demonstrate the sheer power
Editing can have on a movie quoting here from Rob's book again ten years later in
1992 with the release of the director's cut the film received the welcome it deserved according to the Washington Post
The film is great on every level the poignant screenplay about a man's futile quest for immortality
Scott's tremendous direction the incredible futuristic sets designed by Lawrence G
Paul Sid Mead and the others the phenomenal special effects and the touching performances
Especially from Hauer a replicant fighting against the ebbing of his life
His swan song is one of the most touching in modern movie history quick aside
Maybe people would have been more willing to recognize his performance if there hadn't been a fucking voiceover right after it
What's interesting about this director's cut though is that it wasn't actually the director's cut
it's ironic that one of the most famous examples of a director's cut is not actually a director's cut and
Studios were already capitalizing on the idea of a director's cut to sell a movie, but we'll get back to that later
15 years later. There was a final cut of Blade Runner, which was made with Scott finally in complete control
It's essentially a version of the director's cut with slightly different editing better effects some changes in color grading
Harrison Ford's son came in to reshoot a few minor things to make mouth movements that fit the ADR
Oh and most importantly the shot of the bird flying away at the end finally matches the rest of the fucking scene
It took 25 years, but we did it everyone
It's not really a necessary version of the film
But it's nice that Scott finally got to make a version he properly had control over
After the success of the director's cut of Blade Runner
Director's cuts became increasingly common the most famous other example of this is also by Ridley Scott
Kingdom of Heaven's original release was very divisive and pretty poorly received overall
Critics and audiences generally found it unsatisfying often boring and lacking in depth
It was so bad that Roger Ebert a film critic from opposite land who says the wrong thing almost all the time because he's a hack
Gave it three and a half stars out of four and said it was better than gladiator
Three and a half stars. I'm not saying Roger Ebert's taste is questionable, but just putting it out there
That's the rating he gave to The Phantom Menace
Okay, actually I take it back Roger Ebert's great people are really uncharitable to The Phantom Menace
It's actually pretty good Kingdom of Heaven then got a director's cut released on DVD with 45 minutes of new material
Which massively expands the story alters the roles of the main characters and turns the film into a genuine masterpiece of historical epicness?
And fleshes out Orlando Bloom's role so much that it transforms into his best ever
Performance and also frankly his only performance there are hundreds of directors cuts now many of which arguably improved the movie
Most of them have much less drastic changes than these
But it's clear that even small changes can make a big difference and as with the final cut even if there's next to no difference
The point is the creator getting to achieve their vision unsullied by previous meddling. That is the point right isn't it?
Well, not all alternative cuts of films exist for this reason artistic intent and creative ambition
Aren't set in stone
Okay time to get personal as a creator who's got a lot of stuff out there that he can't
Meaningfully go back and change without releasing it as a whole new thing
There are tons of things that I would do differently now in retrospect or
Mistakes that I genuinely would love to go back and fix when I make YouTube videos for my own personal channel
I inherently have final cut privilege. No one can tell me what to do
There is no executive producer with any oversight or control and when I work with a sponsor
I tell them I'm not gonna make any changes even if they ask and they just are gonna have to live with what I make
so
Basically, I am at all times free to unleash my unmitigated
Creative vision upon the world, but what if my unmitigated creative vision isn't perfect the first time around?
what if I make genuine mistakes or change my mind or
Couldn't afford to do something or just didn't have the talent to creative the things I
visioned
That's got to be pretty
Unmitigating right there. Most of the time directors cuts for me would be things like
Rerecording voiceover to sound a bit less echoey or a bit less mouth clicky that sound
I hate when I hear myself making that sound it's awful or remove jokes that I realized weren't actually very funny in retrospect or
Worse are actually casually ableist and I just hadn't noticed or fix that time
I accidentally left an arrow at 2% opacity at the top of the screen by accident
So fully fading it out and it's there for half the fucking video
So getting another run at the project isn't always fully about control
It's about making improvements that you feel you could do now and a lot of directors cuts are more in line with this way of thinking
One director is famous for changing his mind about something after releasing a film that he thought was fine at the time and that
Director's name is Paul Thomas Anderson when Magnolia came out it was well-received but considered by some to be a little on the long side
Anderson defended the decisions he made for his film and seemed pretty happy with it
And I was really upfront, you know saying it's gonna be three hours and you know, they were wonderful in saying, okay
We're not gonna tell you what to do. We'd love it if this was shorter, you know
But but so just make it as short as you can
But the interesting thing about time is it makes you rethink your work a little sometimes this movie at this moment
The one that is in the theaters today. Yeah, it's the movie you wanted to make exactly
Is it the movie you set out to me exactly?
But if you were given the opportunity to do another cut of it, oh, I'd slice that thing down
It's way too fucking long good. Oh, no, it's it's it's unmerciful how long it is
No director's cut of Magnolia has been released
But it's useful knowing directors might have made their own films differently with the benefit of hindsight
Even when they defended them at the time Sam Raimi had complete control over Evil Dead his first film to the point
He places the failure of his next film Crime Wave on there being too much oversight compared to Evil Dead
They replaced my actors. They threw Bruce Campbell out of the lead. They threw out my musician Joe LaDuca
They recut the picture. They had their own say with the sound effects and mix they
Did everything they could to make it what it is today. Do you see Crime Wave?
I
Saw that movie on an airplane and people still walked out
Edie was independently financed largely by whoever Raimi and his friends could get to give them money so they could do whatever they wanted
We didn't have nearly the freedom as our first film because investors aren't gonna come on the set
Dennis isn't gonna say are you sure that camera angles, right?
But this freedom doesn't mean Raimi was necessarily going to be happy forever with all aspects of the film he made
There's a controversial segment in the film where a woman is sexually assaulted by demonic trees
the scene is far more gruesome than anything else in the film and it's definitely a
Contributing factor to it being regarded as one of the video nasties in the UK and getting an NC-17 in the US
Plus it was banned in other countries with different releases subject to various different cuts over the years in
Retrospect Raimi isn't happy with that scene and talks about this openly
well, I think it was unnecessarily gratuitous and a little too brutal and I finally because
People were offended in a way that I did. My goal is not to offend people. It is to entertain thrill scare
Make them laugh but not to offend them
Regret putting it in I do I do
Piers Haggard felt precisely the same way about his folk horror film the blood on Satan's claw the rape scene now
I think it's probably too strong and it's interesting that I wasn't bothered at the time. I think you
Will find most directors
If they get their teeth into a sequence, which is going to be really powerful
They become completely seduced and I was seduced by the sheer dramatic power
Directors have these kinds of regrets or change their minds about stuff all the time
Although of course no studio has helped them re-release these films with the sexual assaults cut
I guess adding in more unicorns is more important than ameliorating excessive sexual violence on film
Some directors actually do get to make their ideal changes though
The Coen brothers who did some work on the editing of Evil Dead and later worked closely with Raimi on other projects
Got to do a director's cut of blood simple despite also being in charge of the original cut blood simple is awesome
It's very different from the rest of their films, but not tangibly worse just different
It's a very stripped down thriller. The director's cut is even more streamlined. It's about three minutes shorter
No scenes have been outright cut but a lot of shots have been trimmed down in length
So the feel is much tighter. These changes are very small
The director's cut is arguably tighter and better edited
But also not different enough that I don't think anyone who didn't like it would like it that much more
And I don't think anyone who really likes the movie thinks that much better of it because of this version either
I'm reminded here of Orson Welles complaining about hysterical tinkering
What exactly was the purpose of all this? The film is theoretically better
But I find it strange that people would go back to create a slightly better version of something that already existed and was fine
Now I love the Coen brothers as much as the next pretentious white nerd boy
But frankly if there's any evidence that director's cuts are actually a bad idea
This is exhibit a aren't mistakes something we ought to accept rather than hope to eventually see slightly touched up later in one
Of the many documentaries about Blade Runner one called all our variant futures
A lot of attention is paid to all the mistakes being fixed in the final cut
But a lot is also made of the charm of some of the mistakes
Gaff's eye color changing things like that and it's clear a lot of thought went into when one mistake is something to be
Corrected to improve the quality of the work and when other mistakes bring their own
Character to the film and ought to be left alone aren't all these mistakes part of the film though
Should an artist be allowed to
Perpetually alter their work once it's been handed over to the public in a 1993 article in the journal film comment
Film scholar and critic Greg Solomon wrote uncertain glory directors cut editions the redemption of an art or the first step on a slippery slope
He said viewing film art as perpetually subject to update and correction
Political or other says something about the directors relationship to their work in a way
They redress artistic grievances by treating movies as mere product in this country and an alienable right to change as an
artist doesn't extend to changing art and
therefore art history rather than artistic deliverance the DC trend represents a significant disturbance of film history and
Equally important the popular cultural memory of the original audiences even kitsch merits protection
The directors cut means the practical elimination of a film record and that the market
Valorizes the new to the point that it supplants the old version and despite what the misnomer directors cut implies
This movement augurs poorly for the rise of the Hollywood auteur
There's certainly no amelioration of the compromise between strict studio and enterprising director
Essential to evaluating their personal commitment to circumvention of studio Philistines in the end the same old commerce here
Masquerades as the aesthetics of creative freedom the ending to his piece is appropriately dramatic
Our film culture faces a future in which old movies will not just seem different from how we remembered them
They will be the theatrical release is fast becoming a work in progress
Original versions soon will exist only in the fragments of our collective memory
Then to quote the authority all those moments will be lost in time
like tears in
Rain in a much more recent piece Alex roses or tears gone wild why the directors cut often turns into an axe murder in the American
Scholar from 2010 Rose says directors couldn't leave well enough alone
They redressed their early classics in ever gaudier clothing and attempts to reclaim their youthful eminence since corrupted by years of compromise
Rose calls directors cuts an indulgence saying even the subtleties while peripheral and seemingly innocuous
Have their effects an extra cutaway here a quick reaction shot there and suddenly the gags aren't quite as funny
The sex scenes aren't as breathless the fights lose their drive the dialogue drags
Just a little more padding and primping and the intangible gestalt of the original is lost
Indulgence is a death sentence a reliable antidote. However is the adoption of
Constraints and what other medium would colossal vanity be permitted much less encouraged
Solman says typically the commercially successful rather than the artistically worthy enjoys studio benevolence
Same as it ever was in a reader's response section in a film comment from later in the year
Gordon Hale from Philadelphia has a prescient comment on Solman's piece
He describes Tom Richardson re-editing Tom Jones then says as films grow older and their copyrights expire
Both the artists and the moneymen will have the same incentive to prepare new editions
Qualifying for new copyrights original versions will then be withdrawn completely new improved
Editions will abound just like toothpaste and detergent and the example Solomon cites will seem like a drop in the bucket
So even though I like blood simple, I really quite like that. There is a director's cut of blood simple
I love the Coen brothers and I'm glad that they have the power to go back and do that if they want
It still manages to pose a lot of difficult questions about how much power a director should have over their art and
Whether or not directors cuts are actually as anti-commercial as they seem to be. Maybe there's a certain confidence or
Honesty in not going back and making changes
Anderson and Ramey have criticisms of their old films as anyone who gets years to look back on their work ought to do
But they aren't going back and making changes to things that are already a part of history in order to satisfy those criticisms
It's okay to learn and move on for things to not be perfect
it may well be that the ability to go back and change something if you want to
Poses just as much of a threat to the integrity of art as any meddling studio
Sometimes the directors changes don't just not make the film any better
But they actively make it worse and what director's name springs to mind better than Francis Ford Coppola
Apocalypse now is a really good film and it better be because it took forever to make and would have destroyed Coppola's
Coppola's
Coppola's career if it hadn't but it was good. So it meant Coppola kept his career and was free to go on to make
Apocalypse now is a really good film but in a very interesting way at nearly two and a half hours
It's pretty long
But the pacing of the movie is so good all the scenes flow so perfectly and the dreamlike
Descent into madness is so well-defined that it's pleasant to sit through you kind of slip into it
It doesn't feel its length at all. If you showed me the movie and told me it was 90 minutes
I would probably believe you in 2001 Coppola released apocalypse now Redux
Redux Redux Redux an extended cut with reworked editing and more scenes added in this new version is three hours and 22 minutes
More content squeezed out of the content tube onto the conveyor belt of cinema. Yes, please
apocalypse now good film great film arguably a
masterpiece
apocalypse now Redux
Garbage the whole thing is fucking terrible. He ruined it. I hate you so much Francis
When you shoot over a million feet of footage to make your masterpiece
Which yeah, I guess is an achievement
It turns out that most of that footage is piss and you probably shouldn't put all of it in the film
The additional scenes utterly destroy the pacing of the original so while it's technically only
Almost an hour longer. It feels five hours longer
I've seen the Redux version twice and both times
I had to pause and do something else for a while like take a nap or watch a different better film
The long-ass plantation scene adds so little to the film
It effectively takes away from it by distracting from what the film had successfully focused on more by being shorter
Just because some of the stuff in a film is good doesn't mean you can put an entire kitchen. Oh fuck
All the tiny scenes of humor or light-hearted escapes from the darkness are washed away by the sheer scope of the thing
It just keeps on going and it's boring and drags to the point of being actively painful
Ha I slapped my meat too hard against the walls of my set
They're all hurting now
Luckily since it turns out that directors intent is a super malleable concept
It appears that Coppola has changed his mind yet again about what his film is supposed to be this year for the 40th anniversary
He's releasing the apocalypse now final cut
Directors cut number three at this point, which is actually 20 minutes shorter than the Redux version
I'm curious if this version of the film manages to maintain the amazing feel of the original but honestly, I doubt it
Coppola already made a really good version of his film 40 years ago. He had his final cut take it away from him now
He's done. It was fine. I haven't seen this version of the film because I don't
Care, but it is coming to a theater right next to me in September
So I basically have no choice to eventually see it and in the director's cut of this video. I will
Put my impressions of the film here and let you know what I thought of it
And that video will come out in 20 years
Or when I hit a million subscribers
Whichever comes first
Incidentally years ago when I was talking to one of my many
Pretentious film friends who I secretly hate I studied documentary production at uni you run into these people
It's an occupational hazard and I was explaining to her how much I hated apocalypse now Redux
But then she asked me have you heard about the work print?
She then went on to explain that there is a leaked work print of the movie, which is five hours
Long the ten minute long song the end by the doors
Plays in its entirety in the opening in this version of the film
What were they thinking was the intent to make a film that long at some point?
Did they think people would watch it were they developing an experimental new torture device?
Don't watch it even if you can find it leaked online somewhere. Just don't watch it
It's not worth stealing this draft of apocalypse now much like the actual draft is something that you're morally obliged to dodge
So here's an even more evolved version of the blood simple problem directors are going back and re-re-editing
Their films to try to undo some of the damage they did in the first re-edit
The slippery slope was real and one of the best directors ever is actively tumbling down it right now
Hysterically tinkering with his film again
But there's actually an even more egregious example of a director making a silly edit to their film and everyone wanting the original back
That's right. You all knew it was coming. I'm talking about Steven Spielberg
ET the extraterrestrial is a pretty good movie, but 20 years later Spielberg decided some changes were necessary
The kids in this scene are in way too much danger look some of those cops have guns well now in this version
They have walkie-talkies
Phew now the kids are never in any danger as they fly hundreds of feet in the air on fucking bicycles
It appears that even Steven has gone on to regret this decision or at the very least makes sure the original is still available
So this is an example of a director deciding they want something changed going to great
Technological lengths to get it changed and then having second thoughts
This whole directorial freedom to go back and change your films as important thing is
Starting to look a little bit flimsy in the face of directors making changes that they then decide were bad
There's probably an example of a director being even worse than this, but whoa whoops. Oh look
We're out of time for this episode of scan
fine
We all want to talk about him
It's time to talk about Federico Fellini fine George Lucas George Lucas is amazing and revolutionary science fiction film
THX 1138 is an ass-kickingly depressing and bizarre prediction of the future that makes some really incisive comments about modern consumerism
Characters literally buy weird plastic shapes just for the joy of having purchased something then throw them in the trash in
1977 George Lucas predicted Funko pop the original theatrical version had five minutes taken out against Lucas's wishes
After the success of a couple of above-average fantasy films
He made a bit later Lucas got to release a restored version with that footage added back in which is nice
He got his movie back in line with his vision
But then George started deciding that his films couldn't just be brought into accordance with his original vision
No, they could be retrospectively
improved
I'm sure you all know about this already, but in 2004 George Lucas released the director's cut of
THX 1138 I'm doing another fake out this director's cut adds a bunch of CGI and some new shots and effects
It's two minutes longer, and it's just kind of needless
It's nice that his film got to be properly mastered and restored I guess
But the level of meddling with a thing that was really finished decades prior is unnecessary
The film doesn't need some more CGI scenes added in years later
It was already great if an old thing has flaws or isn't perfect or you change your mind about it
Sometimes it's okay to let it go. Well that about wraps it up for this episode of
GEORGE
George
Mr.. Lucas, I
Love your films. I love you as a person. I love you as a thinker
I think you're an amazing man and Star Wars is an absolute blessing
I love all of them even the prequels have some great stuff in there my contract with Shannon obliges me not to defend the
Prequels too hard in a video attached to her name, but you know how I feel
You've read my emails, but come on
What were you doing?
did we really need hand to be marginally less of a scoundrel by making him shoot second and
Then did we really need him to shoot second while also awkwardly CGI dodging a close-range laser blast
Did we really need R2 to be hidden slightly more behind the rocks?
Making it a little more believable that he couldn't be seen but making us wonder how we even got in there
Did we really need to remove a cool scene from Return of the Jedi just to show off the amazing new CGI?
You could do now did we need this this part looks better on VHS by the way
I wonder if someone has done a video about why that would be but come on, bro
Even you think the hand stuff is silly now George
I loved your work genuinely and completely
But it's on you that it's such a hassle to see the original unedited versions people saw and loved in the theater
And that's just not fair even if those versions don't line up with your vision
Spielberg did the right thing making sure the versions people loved are still available
Because movies don't just belong to directors to their supposed auteurs. They also belong to culture
You can have your version of the movie, but the people ought to have theirs
I genuinely find you and your work hugely inspirational
But the way access to the originals was deliberately obscured by you was really disappointing
All these different kinds of directors cut with differing resulting effects, well, they really complicate all this don't they?
So yeah studios mess with films often irrevocably
It's nice that sometimes an unmessed version can manifest but the problem is
Artists and audiences have been enamored with the concept of this
Directors run the risk of falling down a rabbit hole
Continuously re-editing their work once it's already out like it's in early access or something
Changing their minds about what their own visions even were and sometimes even helping to obscure the versions people know and love from history
Worse than this what makes a director an authority on what the film should be?
Directors are a small part of a project the producers writers editors actors
Artists set designers all these people are so important and valuable on any project
That it seems almost rude to pretend the director is the one who should decide what the film they all made is
It takes a village to raise a child and the mayor of the village shouldn't get to say that child belongs to them
This problem hits me on a personal level
In fact, the last scanline video did surprisingly well and made it into some lists of best video essays
But often it was credited directly to me when scanline is a collaborative show between me and Shannon Strucci
Whose name was above mine in the credits we share writing editing and other creative duties. She's editing this part right now
I'm just doing the voiceover. It's really nice that we got recognized for our work, but it's our work not mine
I'm not trying to call anyone out here, but being credited for work. That wasn't simply mine makes me a little uncomfortable
It's an easy mistake to make the video is posted on my channel where most of the videos are purely my work
But I think this misunderstanding is also an extension of how we relate to art right now as products of central
Individuals and not the many other people who work on something or the surrounding situation that led to it on that note
I think what people like is the idea constructed by the concept of directors cuts
We like to imagine films as a struggle between true creators and the false moneymen as a battle to realize
Someone's vision. It's a compelling narrative and maybe it's a little true
The idea that there's an authentic version of a film is kind of beautiful and that makes the struggle to try and get that version
Seem almost romantic
But this narrative has been repackaged and sold back to us in the form of special editions of Terminator 2 with a couple more
Scenes and box sets of every version of Blade Runner for us to compare and contrast
Think about that Warner Brothers are responsible for the theatrical cut and here they are
Selling us the fixed version of a film that was broken by them
We like to think of works as made by one person
products of their own vision
When nothing is that simple the tears in rain monologue the best part of Blade Runner by far
Wasn't made by Ridley Scott
It wasn't even written by the writer not completely
Rutger Hauer modified the monologue the night before making it shorter and feel more human and added the most famous line
And then you know I came up with the line all those moments will be lost in time like tears and rain
Knowing this the idea that it's all up to some sole creator and their mystical intent
Only obscures the reality of filmmaking and trains us to desire a purity of vision
That's completely unattainable
Makes us go out and buy more products for the joy of obtaining an even more perfected version of one person's idea
even if that idea was bad and keeps changing even
necessitating more versions and then
Unbroken versions so that you still have the original and it just goes on and on forever
When does the consumption end and the art begin there are no easy answers to questions about art the best
I can muster right now is
Directors cuts are certainly a valid idea and they can arguably improve the quality of a film
But this idea is also easily co-opted into the exact same commercialism that necessitated them in the first place
The idea that the director is the one person who should have final say on the most ideal version of a work is a highly
Ideological assumption which says more about how we think about film than it actually says about the medium itself
But that's a whole can of worms that we'll have to get into at a later date
I guess at some point we should maybe explore what
Authorship actually is and whether the author is alive or not and what the hell or term means
Join us on the next scanline when we discuss how meaning is constructed. Oh
Great. I'm gonna have to read books
But if anything what all this examination of cuts seems to relate is the power of editing
we've seen just how much very small changes can affect the feel of a whole sequence or the meaning of a story an
Editor can make a bad film great and a really good film
terrible and boring
Editing is such an important part of the process
That some people spend years of their lives or an awful lot of money learning how to do it too much money
Frankly, luckily we here at scanline have put together a functioning simulation of a film school
Hi Shannon here this cut here where the sound starts first is a great technique for drawing people into your film to do it
You just you you you just have the audio start first. See it's under the video on the timeline
So it looks like a J. It's called a J cut J. That's how you do a J cut. Okay. Thank you
That's film school. That'll be
If only there was a cheaper way to get someone to share the skills required to learn editing
Well, wait, hang on Skillshare is an online learning platform for creators
If you want to learn how to be an editor
Don't do what I did and try to teach yourself for ten years fellow youtuber Jordi van der putt has a class on editing in
Adobe Premiere that takes three hours and 22 minutes the exact length of apocalypse now Redux and a much better use of your time
Jordi's cutting animating and color correcting tips are like the decade
I spent teaching it to myself only in fast-forward and actually taught me a couple new things
I hadn't realized you could do so easily
I'm a little embarrassed about that and better yet
It didn't cost an entire college tuition an annual subscription to the entire platform is less than $10 a month
But if you click on the link in the description or go to skl.sh
Slash hbomberguy you can get two months of free access to these classes and over
25,000 more I talked about time management skills in a video a couple months ago and on that note Thomas Frank's productivity master class
Genuinely improved my life in measurable ways. Hold on. Do you hear this?
That's my filing cabinet, which I have now
I used to keep all the invoices for music and art and stuff in a big pile in the corner and leave to-do lists
everywhere and now I have a system that actually
Works and getting things done is much less daunting if stuff like that might be of interest to you
once again, that link is
skl.sh
Slash hbomberguy
So yeah director's cuts can be good
Often they aren't Francis
But on the whole it's clear why this is an aspect of film worth focusing on
Because as we've seen films really can be greatly altered by even tiny
Removals or additions cinema is often as much in here as it is on the screen. But what we see on the screen with our
eyes
Facilitates our emotions and beliefs and imaginations our collective reverence for alternative cuts
Reveals our understanding of the power films hold over us by learning just how differently the same idea can be expressed
We're learning more about how to express ourselves
Cinema is a powerful thing
Because it is an extension of the human soul. I've seen things that you people would believe because you've seen them, too
I've seen the addition of a daydream
Change how I feel about personhood and my entire understanding of a story. I've seen the addition of more things to something I like
Transform it into something I hate and I've seen thousands of people
Criticize a few scant frames of digital puppeteering because the original meant so much to them
And I'm glad that none of these moments will ever truly be lost because we have the power to share them with each other
Thank you for watching and that's when I realized that this guy might like
movies
I
Know this video is dedicated to the memory of Rutger Hauer who passed away this year
Incidentally 2019 is also the year in which Blade Runner was set. I find myself wondering
Which 2019 I'd rather live in
But frankly in both there are plenty of people who aren't being treated with the personhood they deserve
Go do something nice for someone today