My channel doesn't ask for money, and unlike most YouTubers I don't make these videos for financial
gain. But since people have frequently asked if they can contribute something, I've suggested
they send money to an innovative charity called Health in Harmony. I'm in the process of trying
to monetise my channel, and I've nominated Health in Harmony as the beneficiary. So I have some
important news about their work. The charity's unique system of trading healthcare for forest
protection is now the subject of a peer-reviewed study from Stanford University just published in
the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. It confirms that the model has resulted
in 70% less deforestation in an important national park, saving over 27 square kilometres
of rainforest. The study also found that it's provided cheap medical services for over 28,000
people who would otherwise have been cutting down trees to pay for healthcare. The model is now being
extended from the forests of Borneo to Madagascar and Amazonia, funded in large part by contributions
from my subscribers. Before I show you the figures I'll explain briefly how it started
and how it works. For years people living along the Gunung Palung National Park in Borneo
have been cutting down trees devastating the forest of the national park and threatening
endangered wildlife. An American doctor working in the area discovered that many of her patients
resorted to cutting down trees not out of greed but to pay medical bills. Here's how she tells it.
We could hear chainsaws all the time illegally logging in the national park and now
you can't hear them anywhere. The reason is we did something crazy. We actually listened. They told us
that what they would need would be access to high quality affordable healthcare so they wouldn't have
to log to pay for healthcare and they needed training in sustainable agriculture particularly
in organic farming. So that's what we did. We had an 88% drop in logging households
and we've had a drop in under five mortality.
The environment is healthier and the humans are healthier and happier.
We are so excited about replicating this model. There are many other places we would like to work.
The doctor Kinari Webb co-founded a clinic next to the national park with an energetic
Indonesian dentist Hotlin Ompasungu. Young doctors and dentists in Indonesia were more
than willing to come out and help and gain much needed medical experience in the process.
So now anyone from a village that's joined the pledge not to cut down trees gets treated by the
clinic for 30% of the normal cost of medical care. If they can't even afford that they can pay that
30% not with cash but in the form of tree saplings or compost. The compost is given
to another of the charity's projects which is teaching sustainable agriculture to local farmers
who traditionally practice slash and burn. That takes pressure off the forest and gives the
villagers a healthier diet. The tree saplings are taken to areas of the national park that have been
heavily logged and replanted. That not only helps restore the forest it gives the charity
carbon credits which pays for running the clinic. I first came across this innovative charity when
I was invited to the Whitley Environmental Awards in London when it won top prize. I pitched the
story to the BBC and they commissioned a 30-minute program from me. When I went out to Borneo I was
so impressed with what I saw that when people kept wanting to sponsor my YouTube channel
I told them to instead give the money to Health in Harmony. And this is the result. To date you,
my subscribers, have generously donated over $100,000. These are all the contributions that
have mentioned my name or the channel name in the last three years. And I was delighted to discover
that many of you opened standing orders for recurring contributions. Others put money in
every time they watch one of my videos. These contributions have helped Health in Harmony expand
its activities into Madagascar and the Shingu National Park in Brazil. If monetisation happens
all of the money, not some of it, all of it, will go directly to Health in Harmony's PayPal account.
So please let the ads run if they appear and don't let that stop you supporting the charity
with your own contributions. If monetisation doesn't happen then your contributions will
be more important than ever. Because they've made a big difference not only to Health in Harmony
but they encourage me to get off my backside and make these videos, even during times when I'd
rather be doing something else. So whether you want to support a charity that protects forests
or one that saves animals or one that improves healthcare, now you can do all three. There's
something in it for everyone. And even if you want all the forests to be destroyed, you hate
animals and you're not bothered about the health of people you don't know, hey make a contribution
or watch the ads anyway. After all even you misanthropes are getting a free platform to
vent your rage and tell the world how much you hate me.