Okay, so this week we are going to do a mini-canon for characters who don't have very many iterations
But have been revamped nonetheless. I was originally going to launch these mini-sodes later this year for certain, you know, movie event
Corporate, you know, interest vertical integration type things
But I think like most people in the last few weeks who saw Mad Max Fury Road
Loved Mad Max Fury Road more than I or probably anyone expected to so we're going to talk about the many
portrayals of
Mad Max all two of them
Mad Max is one of those franchises that most of us absorbed through cultural osmosis or late-night cable reruns
But they were highly influential not on the ubiquitous level of say an Indiana Jones movie
But the Mad Max movies were big precursors to high testosterone
Late 80s and early 90s actioneers like Die Hard though Max himself is more of a subdued antihero type
Neither muscly nor obtrusive Max
Rokitansky is a much more withdrawn sort getting forced into communities and stories that are not his own but shit needs to get done
So hey Mad Max is in town four movies and two different versions the original that made Mel Gibson famous and the 2015
Revisitation starring
Masculificent grunt machine Tom Hardy for Mad Max the canon is a lot more
You know loose than we're used to seeing in other franchises continuity kind of being an afterthought
Are the Mad Max movies officially in the same continuity? Well?
Mad Max is basically a feature-length act one
Civilization in Australia is not doing so hot though. It hasn't exactly crumbled either
We still have infrastructure and a police force and biker gangs are flourishing, but you know
Civilization still stands Max and his partner goose are cops trying to get to the police station
While the name Max Rokitansky has a sort of John McUnconvincing name vibe to it
He's actually named after Baron Karl von Rokitansky a bohemian pathologist and likely nod to the director George Miller's time as an ER doctor
Max is one of those archetypal best at what he does type
You're a winner Max
You're on the top shelf
He's good at shooting and better at driving and in the wake of the deteriorating
state of things here in almost post-apocalyptic Australia
He's beginning to fear his darker side, especially after his partner goose gets killed
Look any longer out on that road, and I'm one of them, you know a terminal crazy
Only I got a bronze badge to say I'm one of the good guys
So does Max get mad?
Nope, he goes on vacation
Seriously, he is on vacay for a
Shockingly huge chunk of this movie
If you've seen Fury Road or any of the other two
You know what's about to happen to the wifey and the baby
And the preamble to a wifey getting fridged
Which in turn is the catalyst for Max getting mad
Is most of the movie
Max doesn't really get mad until the last 20 minutes
When the baby gets killed and the wife gets
Maybe killed
We actually never find out if she lives or not
Max goes on his vengeful rampage
And then the movie ends
Budget being what it was
Max is nowhere near as effective
At exacting revenge as he would be
In later entries
He gets shot in the leg almost immediately during his rampage
And as a result has to wear a brace
That we see in all three of the other movies
Even the exceptionally
Continually wonky Fury Road
But given that Max is now mad
And exacting revenge on these biker gangs
Is he supposed to be the hero?
Or even an anti-hero?
George Miller was not a very experienced filmmaker in 1979
Which comes across with issues of pacing
And structure
And the simple cliche interactions of the characters
Especially between Max and his wife
Plus the budget was basically non-existent
But he already had a good grasp
On theme and character
You're mad, bitch
You think I look silly, don't you?
Max's turn to the dark side
Such as it were was a sort of unsympathetic turn
You could get away with in the 70s
Especially for an independent Australian film
That accidentally made a lot of money here in the States
The audience not knowing whether or not Max's wife survives
Is in a boo-boo on the part of the filmmaker
But it doesn't really matter
Max has by the end of the movie
Basically given up on humanity
And his own humanity
Finishing the movie by roasting one of his enemies
Who is, by the way, helpless
And begging for mercy
And this is also like
A young kid who's a toady
Of the bad guy
And that's his arc
Max isn't just mad, he's gone
But after that first movie
Max more hits his stride in becoming a player
In other people's stories
So for the people who complained about that aspect
Of Fury Road
I have to assume they aren't terribly familiar with this franchise
Mad Max The Road Warrior
Or Mad Max Hooray A Budget
Is where Max
The post-apocalyptic wandering loner
Gets set as his archetype
Max gets caught up with this peaceful-ish
Little community that has some gas
And then the bad guy, Lord Humongous
Yeah
He wants to kill them to get the gas
Max keeps doing these people favors
In exchange for stuff
People keep begging him to stick around
He keeps wanting to leave
And is forced to stay
He just wants his stuff
Stuff is a big theme in these movies
No wifey to get Fridge this time
But he does have a cute
Well-trained dog
And you can guess how that ends
Max defines himself
More in his relationship to his stuff
Than to other people
In Road Warrior he's all about gas
And then he's all about his car
Once he finally lets go of the stuff
He finds out that he'd been duped
By the very people he'd risked his life to help
Turns out that maybe Max was right
To want to go it alone
That was the last we ever saw of him
Stupid, disappointing other human beings
Thunderdome, how do I get in there?
That's easy, pick a fight
And now we get to the infamously bizarre
Beyond Thunderdome
Where once again, Max's primary motivation is
Stuff
It's a few more decades on after what appears to be
A worldwide nuclear war
Where in the last one it was his macho car driving
In this one it's his macho face punching
And not dying in the face of probably dying
Congratulations
You're the first to survive the audition
In looking for his stuff
Max falls in with the evil Tina Turner
And goes along with what she wants
Until he's basically punished for not being
A total monster and refusing to kill
A mentally disabled man
Before long he escapes, barely survives
And then gets thrust into
This lost boy's nightmare
Fly Walker, fly!
And he's not thrilled to be here
But you know, whatever, they're kids
So while always with a mind
To get his stuff back, once again
He's reluctantly drawn into a sort of
Eh, I probably shouldn't let these children
Get killed situation
In the end, Max brings some misfits together
Sacrifices his own well-being for some of those kids
And while Thunderdome
Is the goofiest, it's also got the most
Complete arc for Max as a character
Of those first three movies
In that he actually does something somewhat selfless
And then doesn't regret it
But at the same time he ends up being alone
Now for a while this was
Supposed to be the last entry in the series
In part for that reason
But then 30 years later
Mad Max Fury Road
Is the hardest to pin down in terms of
Continuity. Max alludes to
Having been a cop at the very beginning
But it's pretty obvious that it's been at least
A couple generations since civilization fell
Max is now portrayed
By Pitbull-Elf hybrid Tom Hardy
And when we're first introduced to Max
He's haunted by memories and even
Hallucinations of people he could not save
And no, this doesn't
Appear to be a clear reference to any of the
Previous three movies. The most frequent
Of these accusing dead is a little girl
And she's definitely not in the previous three
So is this his daughter?
Some kid? I don't know. There's several
Other characters who weren't really there in the previous three
Again, in terms of continuity
The thread seems to be
Don't worry about it
So is this the same Max?
Max in Fury Road is the lowest we've yet seen him
At the beginning of the film he's been alone
For so long he's almost forgotten how to speak
Horribly traumatized and suffering from
Intense post-traumatic stress
Where Gibson's Max was controlled
Calculating Hardy's Max can
Barely keep it together
Part of what makes Fury Road so compelling
Compared to the other three is the thing that's being
Fought over is not stuff
Like gas and cars
But personhood. For the first half hour
Not only is Max stripped of all of his stuff
But also of all agency
Strapped to the front of a car as a blood bank
For the war boy Nux under the belief
That this will make his blood more
Adrenaline-y
I mean
He is pissed about the whole ordeal but
Mostly he's mad that they took his stuff
Namely his car and his blood
But as far as the plot proper
Max is not motivated by stuff ever
As in the previous two
But like Furiosa and the wives, by survival
And the movie wastes very little time
Getting our heroes to get over themselves
And work together because it's just the logical thing to do
Because the world is harsh and awful
And really hard to survive in
But when they work together, dammit, they don't waste any time
Being surprised at the abilities of the other
It's just like, oh, you can do the thing
Good, do the thing
That is surprisingly rare with
Male and female co-leads
Almost immediately after Max escapes
Captivity he gets the shit kicked out of him by a one-armed woman
But there's never any
Egotistical butthurt about it
And that does set him apart from most action movie heroes
He doesn't need to reassert his masculinity
There's just no time for that
But the real brilliance of Fury Road
Is the way it thematically examines
Its own predecessors
Especially in regards to characters
Being motivated by stuff
In Fury Road, the stuff is people
That's my child!
I want them back!
They're my property!
Human objectification is a huge theme
The wives are Joe's property
The war boys are Joe's disposable war fodder
Their unborn children are Joe's property
And Max himself, basically an organ and blood donor
Is also property
So while Fury Road is awesome and fun as hell to watch
It's also a fascinating re-examination
On the themes of the previous three
Max was never an ideal
More of a fall-from-grace sort
Than an honest-to-god anti-hero
Maybe in the third one, but yeah
But the first three films are more thematically complex
Than idealizing Max's either running away
Or violence-is-the-solution-to-everything
Approach to masculinity
I don't think it's any coincidence
That Nux bears a strong narrative resemblance
To the young brainwashed Johnny
Who Max killed in Cold Blood in the first movie
Modern Max has zero interest in vengeance
Or even comeuppance
Just survival
And as a result, we have the highest stakes
We've ever seen in a Mad Max movie
And of course we're talking about sequels
And honestly, I
I don't
I don't know how they're going to follow this one
As it was very complete
But hey
If we can go from here
Here to here
In thirty years, who knows
We will be back next week
With a real full episode of The Loose Cannon
Which is death
And it's coming, I promise
Hang in there, thanks for watching
Patreon, Twitter
Go see Mad Max Fury Road, you'll love it
And if you don't