Hello Internet. You know I love me some voting videos. These, however, are mostly about how
organizations can improve their elections. But normal people need better voting too.
Say a group of you are trying to decide what to have for dinner. There are three options.
Steak Shack I'll meet all the time, Veggie Villa hope you like lettuce, and Burger Barn
every burger ever including the ones made from not meat. Just asking people to pick
their favorite as normal results in three starved carnivores. Now you could use one
of these better methods I've talked about before, but seriously who wants to break out
the pens and paper and nerd to crank the algorithm for a question that should be answered
in under 30 seconds? No one. So here's the fastest way to vote in a group. None of that
stuff required. Don't blink or you'll miss it. Hands up if you're good with Steak Shack.
Hands up if you're good with Burger Barn. Hands up if you're good with Veggie Villa.
Boom. Election over. Burger Barn domination. This time everybody gets to live. The difference?
Letting people vote more than once. If you're in a group and picking from several options
quickly this is the way to go. It's a world changingly great at stopping arguments like,
for example, in a classroom. Hey kids we're going to watch a movie today because I just
can't anymore. So let's go. Hands up for Terminator 2. Hands up for Spirited Away. Hands up for
Wally. Done. Wally it is. Lazy bonus. If you're in charge of the vote, no need to keep an
eye out for those aspiring dictators who subvert democracy by voting more than once. Voting
more than once is the whole point. So next time you're in a group trying to decide, don't
just ask for the favorite, ask for all the okays. Best way to decide quickly. No pen
or paper or nerd required.