The fundamental currency of our universe is energy.
It lights our homes, grows our food,
powers our computers. We can get it lots of ways,
burning fossil fuels, splitting atoms, or sunlight striking photovoltaics.
But there's a downside to everything. Fossil fuels
are extremely toxic, nuclear waste is, well, nuclear waste,
and there are not enough batteries to store sunlight for cloudy days yet.
And yet, the Sun seems to have virtually limitless free energy.
Is there a way we could build a Sun on Earth?
Can we bottle a star?
The Sun shines because of nuclear fusion.
In a nutshell, fusion is a thermonuclear process,
meaning that the ingredients have to be incredibly hot, so hot
that the atoms are stripped of their electrons, making a plasma
where nuclei and electrons bounce around freely.
Since nuclei are all positively charged,
they repel each other. In order to overcome this repulsion,
the particles have to be going very, very fast. In this context,
very fast means very hot, millions of degrees.
Stars cheat to reach these temperatures.
They are so massive that the pressure in their cores
generates the heat to squeeze the nuclei together until they merge
and fuse, creating heavier nuclei and releasing
energy in the process. It is this energy release
that scientists hope to harness in a new generation of power plant,
the fusion reactor. On Earth, it's not feasible to use this
brute force method to create fusion, so if we wanted to build a reactor that
generates energy from fusion,
we have to get clever. To date, scientists have invented two ways of
making plasmas hot enough to fuse.
The first type of reactor uses a magnetic field to squeeze a plasma in a
donut-shaped chamber
where the reactions take place. These magnetic confinement reactors,
such as the ITER reactor in France, use
superconducting electromagnets cooled with liquid helium
to within a few degrees of absolute zero, meaning they host
some of the biggest temperature gradients in the known universe.
The second type, called inertial confinement,
uses pulses from super-powered lasers to heat the surface of a pellet of fuel,
imploding it, briefly making the fuel hot and dense enough to fuse.
In fact, one of the most powerful lasers in the world
is used for fusion experiments at the National Ignition Facility
in the US. These experiments and others like them around the world
are today just experiments. Scientists are still developing the technology.
And although they can achieve fusion,
right now, it costs more energy to do the experiment
than they produce in fusion. The technology has a long way to go before
it's commercially viable.
And maybe it never will be. It might just be
impossible to make a viable fusion reactor on earth.
But if it gets there, it will be so efficient
that a single glass of seawater could be used to produce
as much energy as burning a barrel of oil with no waste to speak of.
This is because fusion reactors would use hydrogen or helium as fuel,
and seawater is loaded with hydrogen. But not just
any hydrogen will do. Specific isotopes with extra neutrons
called deuterium and tritium are needed to make the right reactions.
Deuterium is stable and can be found in abundance in seawater,
though tritium is a bit trickier. It's radioactive,
and there may only be 20 kilograms of it in the world,
mostly in nuclear warheads, which makes it incredibly expensive.
So we may need another fusion buddy for deuterium
instead of tritium. Helium-3, an isotope of helium,
might be a great substitute. Unfortunately,
it's also incredibly rare on earth. But here,
the moon might have the answer. Over billions of years,
the solar wind may have built up huge deposits of helium-3 on the moon.
Instead of making helium-3, we can mine it.
If we could sift the lunar dust for helium,
we'd have enough fuel to power the entire world for thousands of years.
One more argument for establishing a moon base if you weren't convinced already.
Okay, maybe you think building a mini sun
still sounds kind of dangerous. But they'd actually be much safer than most
other types of power plant.
A fusion reactor is not like a nuclear plant,
which can melt down catastrophically. If the confinement failed,
then the plasma would expand and cool, and the reaction would stop.
Put simply, it's not a bomb.
The release of radioactive fuel like tritium
could pose a threat to the environment. Tritium could bond with oxygen-making
radioactive water,
which could be dangerous as it seeps into the environment. Fortunately,
there's no more than a few grams of tritium in use at a given time,
so a leak would be quickly diluted. So we've just told you that there's nearly
unlimited energy to be had at no expense to the environment
in something as simple as water. So, what's the catch?
Cost. We simply don't know if fusion power will ever be commercially viable.
Even if they work, they might be too expensive to ever build.
The main drawback is that it's unproven technology.
It's a 10 billion dollar gamble, and that money might be better spent on other
clean energy
that's already proven itself. Maybe we should cut our losses.
Or maybe, when the payoff is unlimited clean energy for
everyone, it might be worth the risk.
Videos like this one take hundreds of hours to make and are made possible by
your contributions on patreon.com.
If you want to learn more about global energy, here's a playlist about nuclear
energy,
fracking, and solar power. Let us know in the comments if there are other
technologies you want us to explain.