I saw these angels taking up positions everywhere in the day what to the real
I didn't really know you nearly holding on Sunday huge mighty angel over the
Pacific Ocean Pacific Samara Samara Kim a the South China Sea region there could
see in a couple of you let me accurately tell you where exactly in geographical
position he station who all are really young they adapt in the day what to the
if you guess that these angels have something to do with the end of the
world of course you'd be right YouTube profits have been working overtime to
explain that an increasing number of earthquakes taking place around the
world is a harbinger of end times now it's easy to ridicule these people and
make fun of their sincerely-held beliefs so here we go
preparing for this whether you believe it or not you know the Bible warns us
of course of the increasing number of earthquakes right as the return of the
Lord draws near as the day of the Lord draws near right that you're going to
see increasing number of earthquakes now we've already seen the quake and then
we've had a second quake now right with a different epicenter in Japan okay
that's two so the obvious question to ask is are we really seeing an
increasing number of earthquakes not one single creationist televangelist or
self-proclaimed profit bother to even ask this question or check to see if
their premise is correct so I suppose I'll have to do it for them the United
States Geological Survey keeps tabs on the number of earthquakes worldwide and
no surprise it turns out that earthquakes of magnitude 7 or greater
have remained fairly constant the perception that there are more
earthquakes may be the result of more numerous and accurate seismometers as
the USGS suggests but it may also be because the worldwide reach of satellites
and television news means creationists are more aware of what's going on in the
world beyond the moonshine still and the hay barn it would help if their
understanding of the past equally extended beyond the most recent hoedown
while instruments weren't around to record the Shenzi earthquake in China it
killed eight hundred and thirty thousand people on that scale this should have
been the mother of all harbingers of the end of times except that the world
didn't end the earthquake happened in 1556 230,000 people were killed in an
earthquake near Aleppo Syria and the world didn't end then either in 1138
around 200,000 died in an earthquake in Iran in 856 a hundred thousand in China
in 1290 none of this seems to have ended the world and the activity has not got
any worse earthquakes are caused by the movement of tectonic plates when two
plates get jammed stress accumulates and when the jam is broken the plates move
suddenly and cause an earthquake that isn't to say there isn't some pattern to
all this earthquake activity because movement along one section of a plate
boundary will put stress on the plate borders either side of it a phenomenon
known as stress transfer a very clear example of this pattern was found by
researchers Stein Barker and Dietrich along the North Anatolian fault line in
Turkey an earthquake at the eastern end of the fault line transfers stress
further west triggering another earthquake years later over years and
decades these earthquakes March inevitably westwards there may even be
an external cause that triggers seemingly unconnected earthquakes in
different parts of the world because although the cause of large earthquakes
is crustal movement many faults around the world are under great stress and
close to rupturing so it doesn't take much to trigger them telesysmic waves
for example which travel through several plates and even global weather patterns
research shows that a sudden drop in atmospheric pressure can trigger
earthquakes but it still doesn't mean Danny Glover was right when he said the
Haiti earthquake was caused by global warming there's also the tidal effect of
the moon's gravitational attraction which moves the Earth's crust as well as
the oceans there are still a lot of unknowns that may cause earthquakes to
cluster in different parts of the world over a period of years but according to
the USGS there's still no unusual pattern of earthquakes occurring so far
this century compared to the long term we just have to give thanks to God that
there's no one did I mean there's lots of damage to property
everybody agrees normally when you when you hear of earthquakes you look at
people going through rubble looking for dead living persons and dead persons and
this has to be one of the wonders of the world
that of course was after the so-called miracle earthquake that hit Christchurch
last year a few months later another earthquake hit the city and nearly 200
people were killed for some reason Bishop Jones didn't go on television
again to talk about the wonders of the Lord or his pious interpretation of
seismic geology Glenn Beck on the other hand well here's what he thought
President Obama should say when the Japanese earthquake struck in March
my fellow Americans I know that you like me are heartbroken over what the people
in Japan are enduring right now it was a massive earthquake 9.0 you know it you
can't avoid it you've seen it everywhere it's one of the largest earthquakes on
our planet's history of course it's not our planet has been through much bigger
earthquakes but no one can fault the sentiment anyway that's what Beck said
when pretending to be the president here's what Beck said about the Japanese
earthquake when he was playing himself I'm not saying God is you know causing
earthquakes well I'm not saying that I'm not not saying that either God what God
does is God's business I have no idea but I'll tell you this whether you call
it Gaia or whether you call it Jesus there's a message being sent and that is
hey you know that stuff we're doing not really working out real well maybe we
should stop doing some of it I'm just saying well Glenn if earthquakes are a
punishment to mankind for our sin then why are the only people being punished
those who live near seismically active fault lines does human wickedness only
happen along the edges of crustal plates if earthquakes are a sign of anything
they're a sign that crustal plates are continuing to move just as they have for
millions of years and the Earth's geology is pretty much the same as it's
been since the Cambrian if anything was going to herald some supernatural end of
the world it would surely be if the Earth's crustal plates stopped moving
and we got no earthquakes but earthquakes aren't the only sign of
impending doom apparently all sorts of nasty things are now going on in the
world we have these natural disasters we have people murdering each other we
wow that's a hurdle the parents killing their children you can't even keep up
with what's going on anymore we have this economic problems all over the
world yep this never happened before these things are going to get worse
spill it again worse and again worse okay okay that's enough
signs of judgment day the end times the Sean Connery impersonator is right just
listen in the near future ignoramus is amongst profuse knowledge unjust wars
and earthquakes will increase wealth promiscuity and unheard of diseases will
spread and good manners and family ties will cease a slave girl will give birth
to her future master the moon will appear bigger women will outnumber men
50 to 1 and wild animals will speak foot odor will become a sexual pheromone bird
crap will become bigger and white up the Italian Prime Minister will grow a new
body part but no one will know what it is a man will scoff and say look I've
got nothing against these prophecies look I've got nothing against these
prophecies anyone is free to prophesy anything they like but don't piss on the
roof and tell me it's raining if the end of days is supposed to see an increase
in war pestilence and famine then we've seen the opposite happening in the last
2,000 years we've never been healthier better fed and more at peace if you
can't accept that then here's a challenge read a history book then find
any decade in the past 2,000 years when war famine and disease were less
prevalent than the last 10 years find a time when we were more at peace find a
time when average life expectancy was higher when disease was lower or when
the world was better fed we may have conflicts in Afghanistan and Burma and
elsewhere but we have nothing to compare to the 8th century and Lou rebellion
that killed around 15% of the world's population and while we have the threat
from Al-Qaeda for two centuries Western Europe was terrorized by the Vikings and
a few centuries later most of Europe and Asia lived in fear of Mongol invasions
you think AIDS is a sign of increased pestilence what about the Black Death
bubonic plague that wiped out a third of the population of Europe in the
Middle Ages or the depopulation of the Americas from introduced diseases what
about cholera measles polio typhoid and smallpox that were once prevalent but
have now either disappeared or been brought under control now the average
life expectancy of the world's population is the highest it's ever been
ironically in this age of science and reason it's easier than ever to set
yourself up as a sagacious prophet all you need is to have a basic knowledge of
seismic geology and an audience that doesn't choose an active tectonic plate
boundary and prophesy a major earthquake and I recommend going for the region of
the world that's more seismically active than any other the Western rim of the
Pacific I guarantee you'll be able to hail yourself as a prophet the next time
the crustal plates move but don't just take my word for it listen to this
little fakir
the rumors of things going astray and there shall be a great confusion as to
where things really are and nobody will really know where lieth those little
things