The universe is magnificent and vast, hundreds of billions of galaxies, trillions of stars,
and even more planets. If even the tiniest fraction are habitable, then the universe
should be teeming with life, and yet we see nothing, only vast emptiness. Where is everyone
else? The answer to this riddle could be as exciting as it is creepy. We are early,
born before almost all other life. But very soon, this may change. Not only might aliens appear,
they could quickly surround us. An irreversible competition for the universe might be about to
begin. While this video is based on scientific papers, we're presenting interesting ideas based
on little data and lots of extrapolation, so take them with a grain of salt. Okay, we need to look
at three essential questions to understand the galactic competition. One, how fast can bacteria
build spaceships? To become a star-faring civilization, life as we know it needs to
master a number of very hard steps. It starts with dead stuff turning into the building blocks of
life. Then it needs to organize into self-contained cells. Those cells have to learn to work together
to form multicellular organisms. This keeps going until complex creatures with big brains learn to
use tools and language. Civilization has to be formed from cultures that value progress
and technological development, and then they need to actually venture out beyond their home planet.
On Earth, life appeared basically as soon as the oceans formed. But then it took two billion years
to make the step from single cells to multicellular organisms and two billion more for us to appear.
Culture, civilization, and space travel developed super quickly though. Do things always take that
long, or was this actually exceptionally fast? Also, passing one step does not mean the next one is
guaranteed. Multicellularity evolved over 25 times independently on Earth, but there's only one
species that builds spaceships. We don't know how many steps life needs to pass and how long they
take to give rise to a technological civilization, but there are probably many, and it's likely that
on trillions of planets, life has been trying for billions of years. Since we don't see any other
technological civilizations out there, it might well be that we are a rare exception. We might be
among the first, or even the first technological civilization in the Milky Way. But this is just
one piece of the puzzle. On top of that, we may have just hit the perfect time window.
Why does humanity exist now? The universe is already 13.8 billion years old, but it's unlikely
that many other technological civilizations had a chance to appear before us. Because in the earlier
universe, life would have had a pretty hard time to emerge, let alone thrive, because it was such
a hostile environment. Early stars constantly blew up, galaxies crashed into each other, and
supermassive black holes vomited massive amounts of radiation. Enough to sterilize galaxies over
and over again. Our sun was born right at the end of this cosmic death show. The universe has never
been more welcoming to life than it is now. So humanity has arrived at a very convenient spot in
time, maybe the earliest reasonably possible for life to thrive. What about the future? The sun
burns brighter than 90% of the stars in our galaxy, and will keep getting brighter. In about a billion
years, it will boil all of Earth's oceans and then become a giant that swallows it whole.
So in the galactic context, the sun is very short lived. Most stars are red dwarfs that can sustain
habitable planets for tens of trillions of years. Life on these planets has an incredibly long time
window to appear and pass the hard steps. Even knowing nothing about how rare or common life is,
this makes it way more likely for technological civilizations to appear sometime in the future
than in the past. Because if civilizations appear at random in the Milky Way within a time window
of a trillion years, then very few, if any, would appear before today. Then a couple more arrive in
this period of a billion years that we're in, before all starfaring civilizations that could
ever exist emerge altogether. This weird tsunami like distribution is the result of both the hard
steps model and something else. A sort of deadline for any spacefaring civilization.
Any civilization coming after will find it hard to have room to survive. So all potential life
has to cram in before it. Humanity exists now, because otherwise, we might have missed this
deadline. What or who creates this deadline? Why aren't aliens already on Earth?
Humans are curious, expansionist, and hungry for energy. We've spread over the world and made it
our own. Our technology has been improving over time, first slowly, then breathtakingly fast.
If these things don't change drastically, and our descendants want to prosper,
they will expand into space. We could construct a Dyson swarm for endless energy and transform
planets into new homes. We could cross interstellar distances, allowing us to reach for planets around
distant stars. If we have the motivation, we can become a galactic civilization. A civilization
that does this sort of stuff can be called loud, because its activity creates noise,
signs that can be detected from far away. Imagine someone in a forest, cutting down trees,
starting fires, and laying down roads. The more intense their work, the easier they are to notice.
An expanding technological civilization would probably be hard to miss. Our telescopes would
pick up all that energy, and we would clearly identify artificial interference with stars and
planets. Another consequence of this business is that it's very disruptive to the environment.
Clearing a forest means the end of its wildlife. Human activity has left no chance for a squirrel
civilization to appear. Not because we hated squirrels, it's simply that the thought that
they might want to do that at some point never crossed our minds, and we needed word. Similarly,
if loud civilizations were running around the galaxy in the past, terraforming planets or
harvesting the energy of stars, they may have prevented our existence. Had aliens started
colonizing Earth while we were still sludge in the oceans, that sludge would never have
turned into humans. This is how loud aliens create a deadline for new civilizations appearing.
The galaxy may have trillions of years to create life, but there may only be a short window for it
to spread and thrive. Even if a loud civilization respects planets with naturally occurring life
and expands around them, like humans do with wildlife reserves, any civilization on such a
planet would not be able to expand ever, trapped forever on a tiny island. But here we are, so loud
aliens were probably never here. What about aliens that don't expand? They would be quiet aliens.
They're probably limited to one star system and don't have a noticeable impact on their
cosmic surroundings. Humanity is like this right now, we wouldn't be able to detect ourselves from
the other side of the Milky Way. If they stay quiet forever, maybe because of their culture
or abilities, then they are not really a concern for us. We only have one sample to draw from
humanity. And right now, we are on the path to becoming loud. If we're not special and succeed
anyway, then any other civilization with the motivation and resources to would eventually
expand beyond its planet of origin. Okay, what are the consequences of all these assumptions and
ideas? Grave consequences, race to the stars. If we are really early, then eventually, others will
catch up with us. Civilizations will emerge all over the place. And these new aliens will look at
space, see no signs of life and come to the same conclusion. They exist because loud civilizations
have not yet taken over everything. But it only takes one loud civilization to crowd them out of
the entire galaxy. They like us will face an important decision. Do they stay quiet, take it
easy and tend to their planet for as long as possible? Or do they start expanding to take a
chunk of the galaxy before someone else arrives? mating others does not necessarily mean war or
conflict. But it means that new borders will arise limits that may persist forever. In the worst case,
a civilization could be completely enveloped by the empires of others, eternally doomed to be a
galactic backwater without control over their fate. So if we want to see to the galactic adults table,
we best get to work. If we really are early, we have an incredible opportunity to mold thousands
or even millions of planets according to our vision and dreams. And one day when we meet
others, we can greet them and meet them as equals. Wouldn't that be nice? If you want to explore the
vast universe from the comfort of your own home, we've got a lot of amazing space and science
inspired products for you. All of our products are designed and produced with love and care by us
here at Kurzgesagt. They're an integral part of the science story we try to tell. So start your
journey on our channel and continue it with one of our posters, notebooks or plushes. Every purchase
directly funds what we do on this channel. Thank you so much for your support. And never stop
dreaming of space adventures.
you