Hi boys, it's me again, just your average girl.
Look I may be a biological female, but I do hope that just for this video, we're able
to converse as men.
I want you to think back to 2016, which I know in internet years is like halfway between
now and the decline of Rome.
Do you like history boys?
How did Rome fall again?
Was it the gays?
Tell me all about it.
Back in 2016, the big internet culture war was between feminists on one side and men's
rights activists on the other.
Whatever happened to that?
These days it's as dead a meme as, I don't know, Harambe.
I did want to do the fedora though.
Every YouTuber who's ever covered the men's rights movement has done the fedora and I
wanted to put my own little twist on it.
My wardrobe notes for this video say MRA femme fatale and fedora but make it fashion.
School shooter realness.
I feel like I'm also serving a little, oh, red-pilled Carmen Sandiego.
In this video, I want to ask, in all seriousness, what are we going to do about men?
Because no offense, but as a group, you guys kind of seem like you're not doing okay.
Could a group of people who are purchasing uncooked alpha yogurt possibly be subsisting
in a state of psychological balance?
Fellas, are regular bowel movements gay?
I guess, yeah, kind of, you don't see a whole lot of psyllium husk in heterosexual
medicine cabinets.
I'm losing my target audience here.
Listen, my dudes, let's just say I'm kind of worried about you guys.
And I'm not saying I'm any better.
To be clear, I'm not okay either.
There's like 15 jars of urine in my refrigerator right now.
Yeah, that's right, women pee too, okay?
Get over it.
I'm so sorry if this offends your male notions of feminine delicacy, but I for one will not
be shamed by your patriarchal bullshit.
🎵
Ugh, you boys, you're very rational, aren't you?
Ugh, I suppose I was too.
I admit that these days, rationality, it's something I struggle with, both as a biological
female and as a Pisces moon.
But when I decided I wanted to make a video for men, Contra Pines, for men, I started
brushing up on my reasoning skills because I want to be so fucking rational for you.
So to prepare for this video, I read Newton's Principia Mathematica, Wittgenstein's Tractatus
Logico-Philosophicus, and of course the philosophical classic The Rational Male by Royal Calliante.
So my mind is well-lubricated and I'm ready for what I have no doubt will be a penetrating
intellectual interchange.
Look, I want to play by your rules, okay, so there will be no emotions in this video.
I will present my arguments in strict, logical form, relying only on facts, reason, evidence,
and deductive proof.
🔔
Actually, you know what?
Fuck that.
Let's listen to house music and do sax frogs.
🔔
I'm pandering to the male gaze.
Oh.
And the male straights.
🔔
God I love attention.
Hey gorge.
Okay I'm ready.
Let's crack open a cold one boys.
🔔
My hands are too pretty to open the can.
I need a man to do it for me.
🔔
Heeeeeeelp.
Fuck it.
🔔
Oh.
Okay that's super fucking pretty.
Hey gorge.
If there are any women still watching this video, I'm really sorry about all this.
Unless you're into that sort of thing, in which case how very dare, I'm a good Presbyterian.
And by Presbyterian I do mean pansexual, hey how are y'all.
Look the video's about men, so I'm trying to be attractive to men.
Am I doing this right?
Is this what men like?
Straps.
It is a risky look for a girl like me.
When you do a lingerie look, you know you're gonna wind up somewhere on the Frank-N-Furter-Violet-Tchotchke-Di-Devanti's spectrum.
Oh, but you don't know where exactly.
And that is a dangerous game, ladies.
I have to say though, I actually am feeling pretty fucking empowered right now.
But um, that could be because of the drugs.
Look, gentlemen, let's be rational.
And we're fooling around, okay?
Part one.
Oh wait, rational.
Axiom one, America's next top victim.
I think there is some truth to the idea that we live in a victimhood culture.
And I'm not just talking about campus SJWs with their microaggressions.
No bitch, this goes all the way to the top.
We have white people complaining about reverse racism.
We have the literal 1% complaining about anti-rich prejudice.
That must be super fucking hard for you.
We have the heterosexual agenda organizing straight pride parades.
You know, flaunting their sexuality in the faces of children who are trying to raise a family
and protesting in the street like a bunch of f***ers.
And so of course, because there was women's rights, there has to be men's rights too.
I've been hearing about men's rights for my whole adult life,
and I've always been very skeptical.
Because in my experience, online men's rights activism in practice always looks like this.
Women try to do a good thing to solve a real problem,
and then a man shows up to say,
well what about men?
Men also get harassed.
Why aren't you talking about men?
And is this man actually involved in activism to stop harassment against men?
Of course he's fucking not.
He doesn't give a shit.
He's a troll.
His contribution to the conversation begins and ends with what about men?
What about them, honey?
For this video, I decided to actually do some research for once,
and the first thing I did was read the foundational text of the modern men's rights movement,
which is The Myth of Male Power by Warren Farrell.
Actually I listened to the audiobook, because let's be honest, reading is hard.
But as I was listening, I admit I thought it made more sense than I was expecting it to.
Basically, Farrell says that second-wave feminists rightly fought against the traditional gender role
that confined women to domestic servitude.
But he argues that the feminist idea that men have all the power in society
is actually an illusion, because the traditional gender role for men is just as oppressive.
He introduces the idea of male disposability,
basically the idea that society values female lives more than male lives,
which are seen as expendable in the service of protecting and providing for women and children.
He points to statistics showing that men make up the majority of military casualties,
workplace fatalities, murder victims, suicides, and so on.
So we're supposed to conclude that even though at first it looks like men have more power than women,
in fact the queens have a certain kind of privilege in being protected and provided for
by the expendable male worker bees.
And I guess that kind of makes sense.
I feel like I can at least empathize with the point of view.
What I'm saying is, I took the red pill, and I rubbed it on my cluuuuuuuuuuut.
But some initial objections come to mind.
Like haven't men been almost all of the kings, presidents, and CEOs for millennia?
Didn't men make up all these rules in the first place?
I dunno boys, still seems kinda patriarchal to me.
But maybe he'll say that it's only at the top of society that men have more power than women.
Maybe the average man is also oppressed by this system that feminists call patriarchy.
If that's what you're saying, I think I basically agree with that.
See, what you have to understand about me is I am such a fucking Libra.
Whenever there's a conflict, my gut reaction is to be like,
well, maybe everybody's right, and maybe there's good points on both sides,
and we should all just listen to each other and rub each other's cluuuuuuuuuuuuuts.
But no, my Scorpio-rising persona will not allow that.
Oh, there will be a champion.
There will be blood.
So, judges, how do we decide which gender is America's next top victim?
I mean, it's not like you can just change genders and see how the other half lives.
Or can you?
Proposition 2.
Diary of an X-Man.
Dear diary, with every false smile I conceal that on the inside I'm drowning in darkness.
Mom!
Get out of my room!
You're ruining my life!
Look, I've never, ever talked about this on my channel before,
so this is like a super fucking vulnerable moment for me,
but I was born a boy.
Well, was I ever really a boy?
It's hard to say.
Dear diary, growing up I always knew that I was different from other kids,
especially other boys,
and it took me so long to pinpoint what it was,
but there was this moment.
I must have been, what, 7, 8 years old?
And I was playing in my parents' room all by myself,
and I saw this pair of my mom's shoes lying on the floor,
and I don't know what it was,
it was like this magnetism that drew me to them.
And I put my little feet in them,
and walked in front of the mirror,
and I didn't really have the words yet to describe how I felt,
but basically in that moment,
I sensed that God had made a mistake,
and I was destined to be,
to be a crossdresser.
That is super fucking coconuts.
Anyway, then in my 20s my life completely fell apart,
and I became a woman, hey how are you?
I became one of the dolls.
My plastic surgeon is an artist.
Look boys, the point I'm trying to make here is,
I used to live your lifestyle.
I know what people like you get up to,
and I think it's disgusting.
I gotta say though, since I transitioned,
my life has been super fucking great.
Like, way better.
Now of course a lot of that is not because women have it better than men,
but because, hey gorge, I am literally transgendered.
So before I transitioned, I was dying inside, you know?
I was in the wrong body.
And now, it's like I finally have the body I was meant to die inside of.
But it's not just that.
I do think that, in some ways, since I started presenting as a woman,
people actually do treat me better.
I mean, they take my opinions less seriously, sure,
but that's probably for the best.
Now before using my personal experience as any kind of evidence,
I guess I should say a couple caveats.
Caveat one is that most pre-transition trans women are not like other boys,
and most of us were not living the business-class male experience by any means.
You know, it's a lot of drunk melancholics, tormented sissies,
secretive transvestites, poets, you know, that sort of thing.
Caveat two is that my trans experience is not THE trans experience,
and I do have a lot of other privileges that made things go super fucking well for me, hey how are you.
Don't you just love it when someone checks their privilege in a way that's actually just bragging?
You know, it's super important for me to acknowledge that I've been so successful,
and I've come so far, in part because I'm white, and I'm skinny,
and I'm young, and I'm blonde, and I'm rich, and I pass,
and I'm educated, and I'm popular, and my plastic surgeon is an artist,
and my boyfriend is really rich and hot, and I come from a pure Aryan bloodline.
And part of what makes me so enlightened and so compassionate
is that I'm able to recognize these privileges that I have
that just might not be available to people who are less fortunate.
From the bottom of my motherfucking and my fatherfucking heart,
that must be super fucking hard for you, I can't even imagine.
What I was saying is, there are ways that people treat me better now
that I'm presenting as a woman.
You know, people smile at me more, I feel more taken care of,
men do things for me.
Now a lot of women don't like men doing things for them,
you know, holding doors, helping with luggage,
because they feel that it's infantilizing or condescending.
But not me.
I love it, both because I love attention,
and because I'm a recumbent queen
who's too much of a delicate flower to lift a finger.
I do this thing on airplanes where when it's time for me
to put my carry-on luggage in the overhead bin,
I pretend that my bag is too heavy for me to lift,
and then some man will usually get up and do it for me,
even though I'm taller than most men.
It makes me happy.
Another good thing about becoming a woman is
I integrated into female social groups,
and I found that they provide a kind of communal support
and overt affection that male social groups generally just don't.
I find the female social style suits me better than the male one,
which tends to be more atomized, more individualist,
where affection is always concealed
behind this semi-jokey front of competition.
Like, think about the way boys talk to each other
when they play video games.
A third improvement for me has to do with the way
men and women are treated in public space.
When you present female in public,
you're more likely to be treated as a spectacle
to be commented upon.
People, usually men, will just blurt out their opinions about you,
sometimes complimentary, sometimes insulting,
sometimes just fucking weird.
Whereas, when you present male in public,
you're more likely to be treated either as invisible or as dangerous.
Now feminists have traditionally interpreted these differences
as men asserting dominance over women in public space,
and they've criticized catcalling as being objectifying,
degrading, and misogynistic.
And it certainly can be all of those things.
But there's different kinds of catcalling,
and I have different feelings about them.
If I'm walking with another woman,
and a man says,
ladies, you look beautiful tonight.
I don't know, I like that.
I think that's nice.
It makes me feel seen, it makes me feel admired.
It boosts my confidence.
Whereas, if I'm walking alone,
and a drunk starts following me down the street,
singing,
have you seen a polythene pam?
She's so good looking, but she looks like a man.
That, I am less enthusiastic about.
I mean, not that that's ever happened.
I'm completely fucking unclockable, hey how are you.
No one knows what it's like
to be a sad tram.
I definitely get where feminists are coming from,
because street harassment sucks.
I'm a lot more afraid walking alone at night
than I used to be,
and there's a lot more places I just won't go by myself.
But on the other hand,
I do now enjoy being able to walk down the street at night
without other people acting afraid of me.
I think a lot of feminists have failed to imagine
the ways that being treated as invisible or dangerous
can also kind of suck.
In my video on incels,
I talked about male invisibility on dating apps,
and how getting no attention at all
can actually be emotionally worse
than getting a lot of shitty attention.
And when it comes to being treated as dangerous,
when I was living as a man,
sometimes if I was walking at night,
a woman on the same block as me
would change sides of the street.
And I totally get why.
Men do scary shit sometimes, and it's better to be safe.
But it still stung a little bit
to be treated as dangerous by default.
I think it can actually be harmful,
which becomes clearer if we add race into the equation.
There's ways that white women's fear
can actually be dangerous, in particular, to black men.
I had an experience with this recently
when I was filming my video The Apocalypse,
and I'd rented a room in a hotel casino.
Around midnight, I was carrying some camera equipment
up to my room, and I got into the elevator
with a group of people from the casino floor.
A couple floors up, everyone got out of the elevator
except for me and a single black man.
Well, I mean, he was alone.
I don't know if he was single.
That's not part of the story.
And as soon as the door closed,
he started literally whistling
row, row, row your boat,
the official melody of performative innocence.
And I realized, oh shit, he's afraid that I'm afraid.
And I found that just excruciating.
I was like, oh god,
how do other white women behave in elevators?
Do they like clutch their purses?
Ugh, that's so foggy embarrassing.
Nothing like that had ever happened to me
when I was living as a man.
It's not a thing between black men and white men.
It's a thing between black men and white women.
And so that dynamic was there
not just because I'm white and he's black,
but because I'm a woman and he's a man.
And I thought of that incident again
when I was listening to the myth of male power,
and Farrell says,
men's greatest weakness is their facade of strength,
and women's greatest strength is their facade of weakness.
I think there is some truth to the idea
that women's perceived vulnerability can make them powerful,
and men's perceived power can make them vulnerable.
Now I hope you're taking all this with a grain of salt
because these are just some little observations I've made
based on a handful of anecdotes.
And as rational males,
it's important that we consider the facts,
the stats, and the figures.
Did you know that 46% of men
are at least 2.8 times different than 73% of women?
Look it up.
I haven't.
I guess my super fucking Libra opinion
is that there's upsides and downsides
to male and female experience.
I don't actually think there's a single definite answer
to the vague and useless question,
which gender has it worse?
I consider myself a feminist
because I support reproductive rights
and I oppose workplace misogyny,
and I generally agree with a lot of the activism
that happens under the heading of feminism.
But I also think a lot of men
are just having a super fucking difficult time right now,
and that must be super fucking hard for them, eh?
How are you?
And I don't think feminists
have an obligation to care about male ex,
but I care about you boys.
God, I'm such a cool girl,
I think the entire mid-Atlantic region
is about to freeze over.
No, I'm just a super fucking empathetic Pisces moon,
and I really try to understand other people's pain
because I just find it really, really funny.
I'm also really, really sobering up here.
The drugs have worn off,
and I'm suddenly feeling very naked.
Like, it's just now occurring to me
that this is a highly inappropriate outfit
for this occasion.
So, I'm gonna go put on a robe,
and I'll meet you back for the next section.
Postulate three, the man question.
Hi boys, et cetera, et cetera.
Hey, how are you?
For the last three years on this channel,
I have been your Virgil,
leading you through gender hell.
Pick-up artists, gender dysphoria, incels,
radical feminists, non-binary genders,
men's rights activists.
It seems like everybody's having gender trouble,
so what do we make of that?
Well, Gorge,
a very, very rational male philosopher named Hegel
once said that the unfolding of history
is a basically rational process, Gorge.
That means that at any time in history,
society is based on certain principles,
like all men are created equal
as long as they're super fucking rich and white.
And there's always contradictions within those principles
which creates tension
and eventually leads to a rupture, like a revolution,
where society has to be reorganized
according to new principles.
At least, I think he was saying something like that.
It's pretty hard to make anything out
through the fog of his unreadable,
hyper-abstract man jabbering.
God, I can't stand that shit,
or any of the other music-hating vol-cells
of the male philosophical tradition.
My point is, I think our society has reached a place
where gender as we know it just isn't working anymore.
Now, no one seems to agree why it isn't working
or how to fix it,
but we do all agree that it's broken.
We have mainstream feminists saying
we need to continue advancing the rights of women.
We have conservatives saying
we need to restore the gender roles of the 1950s.
We have an increasing number of people
not identifying as men or women.
We have TERFs who think that the transgenders
are the single greatest threat to civilization,
hey, how are you?
And we have men's rights activists saying
we need a male equivalent to feminism
to liberate men from their oppressive gender role.
Now, I want to focus on that last one,
because in principle, I agree.
I've spent a lot of the last three years
covering the manosphere.
I know, such a feminine topic, love that for me.
And from all the time I've tortured myself
wading through these communities of incels,
pickup artists, men's rights slacktivists,
intellectual dark web fanboys, and alt-right racists,
I've noticed that they all have one thing in common,
which is that they all recruit
from the same massive pool of sad young men.
We all know the Archetype.
He has trouble relating to women,
he has no strong friendship group,
he's not excited about any long-term goals,
and he fills the void with video games and porn.
And just to clarify,
I'm not trying to take away your video games and porn,
I'm not telling you what to do with your penis,
you can rub one out to this video for all I care,
just don't pull a gamer gate on me, okay?
I live in fear.
Look, I like to believe
that until the red pillars inject their poison,
most of these boys are not bad people.
I think all of this originates
in a genuine crisis of male identity,
and I think it's happened in something
like the way men's rights activists describe.
The sacrificial role of men as warriors
is no longer widely glorified or necessary.
The traditional protector-provider role of men
is being replaced by a more equal
and undefined gender dynamic.
And college professors and activists
are telling men that most of our culture's
aspirational representations of manhood
are toxic and bad.
But without an attractive replacement vision
of aspirational manhood,
average young men can only envision their future as...
what?
The beta.
The cock.
The new male.
And in a post-left-tube internet,
we're so used to laughing at this vocabulary.
And to be fair, it is very funny.
But we forget, especially us grills,
that for a lot of men, these words actually do
tap into a deep existential angst.
And a lot of leftists go,
well how can men be so angsty?
Especially white men, they're so privileged.
But existential angst is often a disease of privilege.
If you're actually being oppressed,
you have a struggle,
you have something to fight for,
and therefore, a purpose.
But for a lot of men,
their lack of purpose puts them in search of a struggle.
And that, along with the loneliness
and the lack of a positive identity,
is what makes men vulnerable to recruitment
by the manosphere groups and by the alt-right.
And even worse, it seems to be a motivating factor
for the small but growing number of young men
who decide to pick up a gun
and open fire in a shopping center.
There were two mass shootings
during the weekend I was writing this video,
resulting in 31 deaths.
Both shooters were young white men,
and one of them posted about the shooting
on an alt-right image board.
Now I don't pretend to fully understand
the motives of mass shooters,
but I don't think it's a coincidence
that basically all of them are men.
One possible interpretation of the mass shooting epidemic
is that these killers are trying to resurrect
some horrible parody of ancient masculine glory,
and therefore, to be seen and recognized as men
by unleashing Homeric violence in a fucking Walmart.
And of course there's also the racism
of the alt-right killers,
and the wounded sexual entitlement
of the incel killers.
But that racism and that sexual entitlement are learned,
and men in the throes of a masculinity crisis
are more receptive to learning it.
So you can try to take down their forums
and ban their accounts and deplatform their events,
but as long as this male identity crisis goes on,
I don't see any end to these problems.
Theorem four, what do?
There is this media narrative that has emerged
around me and around this channel.
And by the way, the fact that there's any kind
of media narrative about this channel
is super fucking coconuts.
Because let's be real, Gorge,
I just wanted to pour milk on my face
and talk about the mouthfeel.
But there's this media narrative
that my role in the discourse is
de-radicalizing young alt-right men.
And it's true that if you read
the leftist YouTube fan subreddits,
I used to be alt-right posts
are so common they're considered cliche.
And some of them cite me as an influence
in changing their politics,
which I love for them,
and I'm super fucking happy about it,
but it's also a lot of responsibility.
They're my boys,
and I worry about my boys.
Because in reality,
it's not like they go from far-right extremists
to complacent centrists, no.
Most of them go far left.
A lot of them become communists or anarchists.
So I watch them go from far to my right
to significantly to my left.
It's not really de-radicalizing
so much as re-radicalizing.
And I think it's definitely an improvement,
but I still worry it's not gonna be enough.
I worry about my boys,
because I don't think that the left yet
has a final solution to the man question.
Oh no, that was worded poorly.
You know, there's kind of two options
the left has for disillusioned men.
The first is the Marxist promise
of economic revolution.
We say, well, actually yes, you are oppressed,
but you're oppressed because of your class,
not your gender.
So just join the revolution,
it's gonna be super fucking crazy,
we're gonna overthrow the bourgeoisie,
meow meow, smash, no voting,
and then things will be better for you.
Now, I think that has a couple limitations.
One is that I look at the far left,
and I see a bunch of people
who spend all their time accusing each other
of abusing moderator privileges
in closed Facebook groups.
And I'm concerned that
we might not succeed at ending capitalism,
meow meow.
Like, definitely vote for Bernie Sanders
or Elizabeth Warren or whoever,
but if you're investing all of your hopes
in a capital R revolution,
I worry that can become like waiting for Godot,
or waiting for the rapture.
So we do need political change,
but I feel like I'm failing
my boys
if I'm somehow giving them the idea
that revolution is their only hope.
Because here's the other thing,
if we succeed ending capitalism,
there would still be gender,
and my boys would still need some model
of what it is to lead a good life
as a man.
Now the other option the left has for disillusioned men
is the feminist tranquilizer.
We say, look, toxic masculinity
is the reason you don't have room to express your feelings,
and it's the reason you feel lonely and inadequate.
So while feminism tells women
you hate your body and you're constantly
doubting yourself because society
did this to you and needs to change,
we kind of just tell men
you're lonely and suicidal because you're toxic.
Stop it.
We tell them they're broken without really telling them
how to fix themselves.
I think what we need is a new, positive
ideal of manhood,
which I don't think is something that women can create
for men, even if they wanted to.
And honestly, the best way for that to happen
may actually be some kind of men's movement.
But on the left, the whole idea
of a men's movement is basically taboo
because the men's movement we all know
is basically just a backlash to feminism.
And at worst,
it's just straight-up misogyny.
And look boys, I understand that being
lectured about manspreading for most of 2015
was super fucking hard for you
and you're still mad about it,
but posting endless outrage porn
about false rape accusations
and paternity fraud isn't actually
going to make life any better for you.
Because yes, those things are horrible
when they happen, but they're not
systemic issues that affect most men.
I think what would actually improve life
for most men
is a positive ideal of
21st century manhood.
But that's not something I can give to you
because, in case you hadn't noticed,
I'm literally a fucking woman.
I can't mom you through this one, boys,
you're on your own. You have to help each other.
So find each other in the comments section,
meet up on Reddit,
make friends, clean your room,
leave the house. Fuck each other.
I don't know. It's worth a try.
And failing that,
you could always throw in the towel
and become a woman.
Worked for me.
I'm just trying to give, like,
milady energy.
Yeah, it is English.
It's very John McClane, very Quentin Crisp,
very aristocrat.
I'm super fucking naked right now.
That's crazy.
That's super fucking crazy.
According to traditional gender roles,
men are useful for their labor,
and women are useful for their wombs.
Well, I'm a woman without a womb,
so I guess I'm useless.
But I'm beautifully useless.
Ugh, I'm a work of art.
The problem with our society is we've turned
men into women. It's disgusting.
As an ally to men,
it's not my place to speak
for them or speak over them,
but I just want to use my platform
to uplift
some male voices who
might not have
as many subscribers as me.
Okay.
Meh.
I'm not a
pergamos. I don't need a rich husband.
If I may quote Cher,
I don't need a rich man.
I am a rich man.
It's not even really much of an insult being called
a delusional man. Many great
books have been written by delusional men.
So bad.
I'm bad.
I'm really bad.
Okay.