Thank you.
Are we talking about something that might literally
crack the Earth apart?
What?
No, no, calm down. This isn't really
another earthquake prophecy. It's only
little me. When I did my video
last month on the spurious 188
day earthquake cycle,
you know, the one that conveniently left out
dozens of earthquakes that didn't fit,
I asked any statisticians out there
if they could cherry pick other patterns
among the hundreds of randomly generated
numbers that make up the intervals
between earthquakes. And two
of you stepped up to the mark.
My thanks to Oblivion Calling, who polished
up my average earthquake interval and says
it's 17.5 days, not
19, with a standard deviation
of 18.7. And
Princip Hoffnung, who looked at all the
time intervals between major quakes and
found this 242
day cycle. Now if any of the
earthquake profits had got hold of it, I'm sure
they would have latched onto it, because
as my fake promotion rightly
says, it's been going on for a lot
longer than the 188 day cycle
and it has more earthquakes in it.
So what do all these magical
cycle believers say now?
We all die. I thank God for this life.
See you in heaven. No, it's OK.
It's not real. I'm trying
to show you that if you have hundreds of
randomly generated numbers, then by the
law of averages, you're obviously going to get
lots of four chain numbers that are the same
and a few five or six chain
numbers that are the same. I just
heard this for the first time and I think you're definitely
right. The weather has been very strange
lately. And you know how it talks about how we'll
get to the point where you won't even know what season
it is with the change in the weather? I could see it hitting
the Madrid fault line. I hope not,
but I always remember the work that was done on the dam
near the line. So has anyone ever
had dreams of the coming? I have multiple times
and it was so realistic I thought I was in heaven.
Look, I'm not trying to prophesise something
here. I'm trying to show you that this is rubbish.
Stop looking at me as if
I'm some kind of a messiah of the mega-quakes.
Tell them, Mum.
He's not the messiah. He's a very naughty boy.
That's right.
You don't have to follow me in this fictitious
242 day cycle.
You don't have to follow anyone
just because he finds a pattern that's nothing more
than a statistical exercise.
You've got to learn to think for yourselves.
You're all individuals.
Yes, we're all individuals.
No, I mean it. This isn't a Monty Python
sketch. You're all different.
Yes, we are all
different. I'm not.
Look, all of you, just find some
randomly generated numbers and do the
maths yourselves.
I've had a lot of these mathematically
challenged followers coming onto the
comments forum of my video insisting
that I must somehow be wrong
but they can't figure out why.
You look a little silly now.
The 188 day cycle predicted a
major quake, March 19th to 22nd
and I'm sure the earthquake in Mexico
had nothing to do with it.
No, because as I showed in my video
large earthquakes happen on average
every 19 days, or as oblivion
calling corrects me, about every 18
days. If you don't believe me, work
it out for yourselves.
So not only does this show there
is no 188 day
or 242 day cycle
unless you ignore most
earthquakes, I said that because
they happen so frequently there's a very good
chance there'd be an earthquake during that
three day spread. And there was.
What are the odds?
Well, obviously one in 18
divided by three, or about one in six.
Getting an earthquake on one of
those three days was like rolling a die
and betting on a six.
It's not rocket science, as
this professor of diceography
will show.
If you look good like this, you
don't have to bend down like this.
Find the corner, shake that
die really good, like this.
And then roll that dough.
What do I got?
I got one and six. Oh,
jump dog, I win. The only ones
who look silly are those who wet their pants
thinking they'd witnessed something mysterious
just because a six came up.
Because the odds
are so good, coming up with a sequence
of several earthquakes is remarkably
easy. Let's take any two
big earthquakes as our starting point.
The time in between is 136
days. So what
are the chances of getting another earthquake
136 days later?
One in six, of course. And the
chances of getting two more earthquakes
that time interval apart are one
in 36. The chances
of getting three more earthquakes, one in
216.
But of course you can go in either direction
and halve the odds, or split
the time interval up and decrease them even
more. Even if the odds
are pretty long, remember there are hundreds
of time intervals over the period we're looking
at. So the odds of finding one or two
strings of five equally separated
earthquakes are extremely good.
In fact, I'd bet on it.
I hate it when people are so closed minded.
Well, I'd say closing your mind
means only looking at the evidence that
fits your pet theory. You'd be
surprised at what you find if you open your mind
and look at all the evidence.
Lucas 911, that's
Wayne Young, did not make money on the DVD.
He posted them free. Videos
are free. Yeah, my mistake.
It's probably my inability to
read that led me to believe his website
said the videos were $9.99
plus $1.99 US
shipping. Well hang on, it did.
And here's a recurring theme
from Wayne himself.
If I ever do
want to take the time to debunk your video,
I assure you, I'll watch it.
I was debunking your premise
that there's a 188 day
earthquake cycle. If there's no cycle,
then whatever you want to put in the
video that might be the cause of it
is completely irrelevant.
You should let people make up their own minds. We're not
idiots. No, I'm not saying
you're not allowed to make up
your own minds. You can make up
your own mind that the chances of rolling a
six are one in a thousand.
But that doesn't change the mathematics.
The odds still cling stubbornly to
one in six, whatever your mind
has decided. There's nothing
wrong with checking what Wayne Young has
told you to see if he's correct
or checking what I've said to see if I'm
right. Nothing wrong with opening a
maths textbook or taking an evening
course in statistics before
you start latching onto what someone's told you
and treating it as the gospel truth.
You got to know how to camp. You win.