So for part two of our deep dive into gender and transformers
How's that for a phrase you never thought you'd say as an adult?
It's time to look at that most misunderstood of all film studies concepts
the male gaze
Male gaze is not just when a male character
Physically looks at a female character and the camera takes on the male characters point of view
Although that is certainly an aspect of the theory male gaze was a concept first developed by Laura Mulvey in her 1975 essay
visual pleasure and narrative cinema
It is important to note that the term originated as a film studies term and was expanded upon in the following decades in media studies
Communications and cultural theory in its original iteration the term male gaze relied heavily on the way
Cinematographers photographed women in movies and if you think Michael Bay is bad
The
Let's just say putting words to the idea of male gaze was a little more on the nose in
1975 than it is in today's mainstream media and it is still pretty on the nose today
Mulvey's idea of male gaze holds that women on film are objects for male fetishistic gazing with men as the de facto subject
And what about female gaze retorts the internet straw man according to Mulvey the language of film was made by male
filmmakers for male audiences female gaze isn't really a thing because even if say a
Female filmmakers tries to invert the idea of male gaze by fetishizing male bodies
It still uses the same language and techniques that male filmmakers used to create a degaze upon female bodies
Just substituting male bodies with female bodies
So according to the Mulvey in viewpoint Magic Mike XXL
Still falls under the purview of male gaze
Gaze has come to be defined not just by a house cinematographers shoot bodies within a frame
But also describes how one group season portrays another group
that's why it's not uncommon for for instance Joss Whedon's affinity for kick-ass fragile waifs or
Tarantino's use of girl fights or even Spielberg's use of beleaguered but powerless mother figures to fall under the purview of male gaze
But gaze does not only apply to members of one group portraying a different group
It can also describe how a group sees and portrays itself
Therefore the reason why Sam Witwicky and Cade Yeager are the way they are
Aggressive hostile abusive self-entitled insecure overcompensating paranoid lazy defeatist and obsessive a friend of yours. I'm not a romantic friend
Romantic friends do this your car
That is all a part of male gaze so in today's discussion
I am NOT going to talk about how Michael Bay's form of male gaze applies to his female characters. No, no, no
Today, I'm going to talk about how Michael Bay sees
the men's
Look at these two June bugs
There is a fascinating discussion of non-human masculinity to be had in these movies
It's supposed to hurt, it's an ass-kissing
Bumblebee oscillates between being a sapient thinking war machine and like a dog who keeps squirting his fluids on people. He doesn't like
Stop lubricating the man
There's a lot of sexual coding in the Transformers that you don't see in other Transformers media like Nokia bot has a dick cannon
Wheelie humps Michaela's leg and in the third movie when Michaela mysteriously disappears
He calls her a bitch before leering at Sam's new girl toy and of course dogs humping other dogs
But with regard to applying concepts like male gaze to male characters. I'm more interested in the two mains
protagonist of Transformers is one through three Sam Witwicky and
Protagonist of Transformers is four and five Cade Yeager your car
Like I think Michael Bay
Kind of hates them for what it's worth
I think he hates Wahlberg's character way less, but there is a staggering amount of baseless insecure aggression between the male characters
I'm about one second away from knocking you out taking the bomb and just leaving you here
You know, we got a rule about people messing with people from Texas
It's a freaking spaceship you go get insurance on a freaking spaceship
Good luck with that buddy pick any random scene in a Transformers movie
And if it's not like a soldier thing, it's probably two male characters being angry at each other over nothing, sir
Do you want to see the property? Sure. I'd be more than happy to give you a tour
I'll show you three other bars. I got buried up back then
I'll crack your head open like an egg in the fourth movie
The central character conflict is between Cade and his 17 year old daughter dating an older boy
What daddy doesn't like baby's new boyfriend one I punch you right in the mouth and you call the police on me
This is a pretty common character motivation for older male characters in Hollywood movies
Unselfconsciously hating daughter's love interest because he suspects that the boyfriend doesn't respect women because he's projecting him because he doesn't respect women and assumes
New boyfriend is like him and so the two are basically fighting over their object daughter lover the whole movie
This character arc usually ends with a dad dying so the breeding pair can go forth unfettered that doesn't happen in age of extinction
But the movie does add in some next-level creepy by having the boyfriend be four years the 17 year old
Senior and having him carry around a card with some obscure, Texas law
That means it's not statutory rape if I stoop your underage daughter Mark Wahlberg got a pre-existing juvenile foundation relationship
statute 2705-3
Yikes
But really it's all about Sam dear Sam Sam the ultimate worthless male protagonist, mr.
Masu-matsu
So worthless at the fourth movie doesn't even mention him and the fifth movie implies that he died off-screen somewhere
Probably slipped in the shower and choked on a bar of soap or something
That is how little respect Bay has for his own protagonist. That is not to say necessarily that Sam is worthy of respect
He is more or less defined by his own inadequacy
Let's go call your mom. I don't need any money for lunch. I have money from yesterday's lunch
Not demoralizing is they've saved the world twice
It's gonna be groveling for a job and inadequacy that he never really overcomes
They try to give him a character arc in the first movie something about
Sacrifice and victory and how he learns the value of sacrifice, but this doesn't make sense because Sam never
Sacrifices anything this is the closest any of the movies get to having a character arc for the main character by the by
So Sam's faults numerous though
They may be do not build to anything except a quiet removal and off-screen death
Sam is by no means unique in terms of his particular brand of character flaws
The last time I ate shrimp my throat closed up and I went into convulsions
Shrimp, but there's an important distinction be drawn between a character like Sam and a character like Star-Lord in the Guardians of the Galaxy
Movies who has a lot of the same character flaws as Sam does look. I'm gonna be totally honest with you. I forgot you're here
The key difference here is that Peter Quill's character flaws form the basis of a character arc for Star-Lord
his immaturity nearly gets the group killed in Guardians 2 if what's between my legs had a hand on it, I
Guarantee I could have landed this ship
His casual sexism is at least part of the reason Gamora doesn't want to settle down and his narcissism almost leads him to going along
With destroying the galaxy. Only you carried the connection
to the light
I don't want there to be confusion or misrepresentation of what I'm saying along the lines of oh
So men aren't allowed to have character flaws now either. No, that's not the point
But if you have a shrieking cowardly abusive overcompensating compulsive liar as your protagonist, maybe you want to I don't know
Do something with those character flaws?
Like have there be a consequence of some sort?
But there never is with Sam because the character flaws aren't framed as character flaws
There are jokey jokes to make him relatable to the audience
You said it first
In short Sam is the audience avatar. This is how Michael Bay sees you the viewer
Let's go call your mom and this is a part of male gaze
One of my friend by his money his power is good looks none of the above check Sam is shitty ineffectual and materialistic
But that's okay because the audience is shitty ineffectual and materialistic
Sam's involvement in the plot of the first two movies has no bearing on discoveries or decisions
He's made but objects he had in his possessions. These are my grandfather's glasses
Glasses
He inherited the glasses his dad purchases Bumblebee for him and then during the final boss battle
Bumblebee gives him the MacGuffin and tells him to run around with it in a circle for five minutes
Sam is a little more active in the third movie where he spends a lot of time trying to figure out why the
Decepticons are killing astronauts and Russian cosmonauts. But again, those character flaws are just kind of tacked on
That is the difference between a character like Star-Lord and a character like Sam Star-Lord's flaws and jokey joke lovable misogyny are meant to be
Relatable. Yes. Yes, I prefer to make people the old-fashioned way
But there is comment on these flaws in the film and there are consequences in the narrative
There is a reason why Sam always gets the girl despite not deserving her and Peter doesn't Sam just sucks
because this is how Michael Bay thinks the straight white male audience sees itself and will respond to
And apparently he's not wrong before we go I want to talk about one under discussed character John Turturro's Reggie
Seymour Simmons
I say slash because mr
Simmons had an unexplained name change between movies one and two Simmons from the get-go is
identified as delusional and pathetic compared to actual soldiers and actual robo soldiers getting peed on by them and
displaying an ignorance about both robots and
Warriors and the military in movie two he's back now manager of the deli of racist screeching
But he joins our ragtag group from the first movie and also this guy who is here for some reason
Don't be sucking the sack and helps organize the strike all while
narrating himself
One man alone betrayed by the country he loves now
It's last hope in the final hour of need like the hero of his own story
Then there is the third movie where he has now capitalized over his involvement with the Transformers
By my book spending the last half of the movie putting Francis McDormand in her place because they had sex at some point
You ever say a word to anyone about what happened that night in Quantico? I cut your heart out
Jesus Christ dude Simmons is in command posturing oblivious full of false confidence and denigrating towards most people
But especially women you in the training bra do not test me a little criminal girlfriend. Look at her now so much sure
What somebody got something for the house going on? Who are you?
Yet the more amoral he behaves the more fame and money he gets
John Turturro has gone on record several times to say that he based his performance of this character on
Michael Bay Simmons reflects the way base
He is a certain type of masculinity which then Turturro flips around to be a reflection on how he sees Michael Bay
This is I could do whatever I want and get away with it
bitch
Sam Cade and Simmons are all
Reflections of how the filmmakers see the audience and not the reason people go to the movies in the first place
This matters because it reinforces a very narrow view of masculinity like a male gazeception
This is called reflexive media
And there are a lot of studies that show statistically speaking that media is not great at necessarily shaping
Behaviors if you see robots blowing up the Lincoln Monument
You're not statistically more likely to go out and try to blow up the Lincoln Monument
But media is great at shaping worldview
Usually in ways that you the viewer are completely unaware of men continue to exist and emulate this narrow view of masculinity
Because media pushes it as normal and relatable the men in the Transformers movies are denied authenticity
They are the subject of ridicule and in constant desperate need to affirm their masculinity
There is a modicum of sincerity allowed in the first movie and sometimes in later movies and usually only in scenes with Optimus Prime
But for the most part sincerity and vulnerability in men is viewed with disdain
The only acceptable form of male authenticity is the soldier kind
So it is a common even cliche refrain now that Michael Bay doesn't respect women
But as far as representations of whole groups go
He doesn't have much respect for men either
You