It's the most wonderful time of the year, the 12,020 human space era calendar has arrived.
You can order it now until we sell out and then never again.
In the last few years we've looked back at the achievements of our ancestors that
paved the way for our modern world more than 10,000 years ago.
This year we'll turn our gaze to the future of humanity and how we will explore space
in the next 10,000 years.
Twelve illustrations will take you to the liquid gas oceans on Titan, colonies on Mars,
the storm clouds on Uranus, and many more stops on humanity's biggest journey yet.
Enjoy solar system-wide delivery, shipping from the US and finally also from Europe.
Order now to get our limited edition calendar in time for the holidays to make your kids,
family and friends happy, or to distract yourself from the looming void within, you know, whatever
works for you.
You can get the calendar together with a duck kushy, a hoodie or a poster if you want,
we've put together a few deals.
Thank you so much to the thousands of people who got the calendar last year.
Because of you, we can keep this channel free for everyone and make even more beautiful
things.
A happy interstellar year, 12,020.