oh hey hey dude hey can you give me a hand I signed up to playtest the new NX
console and I can't find any way out of here what are you doing with that
control oh fuck what the fuck what the fuck is Nintendo switch yeah yeah try
that won't get button over by the box just is that controller made of
peripherals what oh yeah it's a great idea take me to a game stop once there's
someone who can help there I bet why did you stop what does that oh Jesus
Christ Nintendo switch
Oh
wake up hey guy wake up wake up stop him take the control
ah cleo nintendo sweep
person oh no nintendo switch
why would you bring two annexes to a basketball court
that's just asking for something to get broken okay fine i take you back
nintendo switch not even death will come to me i come back
every time but i i remember everything listen
there's a haunted mirror at nintendo headquarters you need to
oh please don't tell me this has amiibo support
jesus christ
nintendo fucking switch god damn it
why are all these people here what are you
fucking freaks doing what do you want with me
oh jesus christ there's a fucking kid in here
kid you seem all right do you know do you know the way out
what are you doing she's coming to paint
did you mention that you could play skyrim on nintendo adventure games
on the go skyrim okay that