Blizzard's famous team-based multiplayer online first-person shooter video game has just updated,
and along with making Zarya's ult capable of actually killing half the roster,
and forgetting once again to add the very important feature from the trailers,
where Widowmaker's butt inflates for added aim stability,
they included a new character, Mr. Doomfist.
The character is well-known in the lore of Overwatch, the...
ICONIC
DOOMFIST,
having appeared in one of the cinematic advertisement trailers,
and ads for exhibits about him are in the game too.
The name and mantle of Doomfist have been handed down from numerous characters to others in the past.
Apparently Blizzard are so close to running out of names that now several characters just have to share.
Many players have been asking how long it will take for Blizzard to run out of ideas for good characters,
and just put him in the game, and the answer was 14-
Apparently Blizzard didn't do the usual thing they do when they run out of ideas,
and bring Illidan back again,
and since the character just came out,
I thought I should play him for the tiny amount of time I could possibly have played him
in the few days he's been in the game proper, and review him.
You might think it's intellectually dishonest to analyze a character prior to them getting a chance
to be fully integrated into the existing metagame of a competitive experience that's been out for over a year,
and to that I say, um...
So Doomfist has a-
Someone has-
Hold on a sec-
Doomfist has-
Oh...
Doomf-
This is cyberbullying.
Oh, I have to start loading in faster, or I won't be able to talk about the character on the internet for a few more days.
Well, I guess it's time to run some upgrades.
If you want to follow along, carefully extract the front panel of your personal computer.
Um...
Uh...
Watch for excess Plexiglas!
Remove old video card for future consumption-
Ugh...
The trick to overclocking the GPU is to apply a generous amount of thermal paste
to the broadband...
JavaScript.
Your screen is now fully integrated.
And...
JavaScript.
Ah, that's better. Much faster.
Anyway, Doom-
FUCK!
Doomfist has a very interesting moveset,
and I can't wait to see how it translates over to Blizzard's good game,
Heroes of the Storm.
Overwatch has come under fire for having some characters and abilities
that are highly evocative of Valve's highly popular team-based
multiplayer online first-person shooter,
Hat Loot Box 2,
but Blizzard have finally proven themselves to have their own unique ideas
by adding a guy who can charge forwards very quickly
and deal high amounts of melee damage
and recover health for doing it well.
Well, actually, it's a bit different because Doomfist doesn't really gain health.
He just gains temporary shields to differentiate himself from Reaper,
the close-range character who already gets health for hurting people.
He can also uppercut and hang slowly in the air to get shot to death,
but don't worry, if you're feeling really fancy,
you can wait until right before you die to do it,
and then you can fly away to escape being court-martialed.
Overwatch has been praised for its diverse cast of characters
that avoid playing into stereotypes,
which is false because it contains the most horrific caricature
of any people ever conceived and is deeply offensive
to my culture and heritage.
All these years, I've wondered if racism actually exists,
and I've finally found her.
Trying to crash another party, love?
You don't get to call things love.
Only we get to call things love.
Don't worry, loves. Cavalry's here.
Oh, yeah, stay classy, Blizzard.
Just make fun of our culture
and its inability to move beyond mounted horseback troops.
First, Apple refuses to include a pork pie emoji,
and now this.
Listen, Bethesda, I thought we'd patched things up a bit
since the War of Independence,
but this behavior really just spits on my whippet.
There was no need for this.
I'll see you in whatever the Warcraft equivalent
of, uh, Nuremberg is, but it seems the company
have listened to criticism of their reduction
of people to stereotypes by rounding the current roster out
with a villain who's a tribalistic,
half-naked African man covered in horns.
But he really believes that we as humans get stronger
the more conflict that we endure.
You see, he's called Doomfist,
but he's actually a very deep and interesting character
because he thinks he's right,
unlike all other antagonists in the history of stories.
To voice him, Valve hired Sarn Gauja,
a respected director and actor whose ancestry
reflects the canonical one they had in mind for the character.
But why didn't they let Terry Crews voice Doomfist?
For reasons that can't possibly be systemic,
I only know the name of one black actor
under the age of 50 they could put
Please sign the petition to replace the Doomfist voice actor
and also put back in Tracer's butt
and also remove Tracer entirely.
I was told that John Henry was overpowered,
but I think his addition to the meta is much more nuanced
than that in that he's also rubbish
and needs to be fixed.
Doomfist's punch does feel good to use, though,
and he can even knock his enemy off cliffs
like Lucio, the healer, only he can only do it
to one person at a time, so he's not even
as good a killer as the guy's fucking support class.
I'm really not certain Overwatch needed another attack hero.
We already had Genji Man, High Noon Man,
Justice Ro-ugh!
Ghost Boy, Scythe's Dad,
a racist caricature,
and Sombra, a hacker so powerful
that even your teammates disappear from the game
when you pick her. To be honest,
they could have made him have more health, deal a bit less damage,
and maybe gain more shields from his abilities
and make him a really interesting
new tank-type character
or come up with some other gimmick that makes him function
as a support, like maybe his ult
makes a bunch of Doomfists fly out of his fist
onto your teammates' fists,
and it vastly improves everyone's melee damage
for a few seconds, so you suddenly get everyone
on your team wrecking people with Doomfists
while the character applauds how strong
they've become under his tutelage or something.
Blizzard sold me this free character
with the promise that I'd be invincible
and Tracer would deal an insignificant amount of damage
and then be killed, which is a really good idea
if you ask, you need to patch the game,
Jeffrey. She's doing it again.
This is textbook false advertising.
Someone increase the jurisdiction of the FDA
and then call the FDGA.
So many skins in Overwatch
for the male characters expose one of their nippies.
Activision Lion's Head have one of the most
weirdly specific sociopolitical
agendas ever. I half expect
the next character's shift ability to expose
his nipple even more, and his ult
probably makes them reveal their drop rates
in compliance with Chinese law
and the enemy team dies of starvation
trying to get the new nipple skins in loot boxes.
Oh, speaking of loot boxes, here's two
I forgot to open before he got patched in.
Oh, man, maybe I already got one
of his skins.
Oh,
lovely, all the things that I already had
and they aren't even good things I already had.
Oh, boy, I'm so glad I bought this
instead of Battleborn.
Oh!
It's taking a moment to load in.
It could be the new...
...
..
I'm certain my problems with Mob Psycho 100 Punch Man will be solved
when he's been out for more than a few days, and I learn how to play him properly, and the meta gets a hold of him,
and Blizzard inevitably patch and balance him more. But you need to be current to drive engagement with your channel,
so I made the video now.