The desire to be free from the limits of the human experience is as old as our first stories.
We exist in an endless universe, only bound by the laws of physics, and yet our consciousness
is trapped in mortal machines made of meat. With the breathtaking explosion of innovation
and progress, for the first time the concept of leaving our flesh piles behind and uploading our
minds into a digital utopia seems possible, even like the logical next step on our revolutionary
ladder. Mind uploading and digital immortality are some of the core themes of the game Cyberpunk
2077. It plays in a grim dystopian future where humanity has progressed far beyond today's
technology and explores what this could mean for humanity. About a year ago, CD Projekt Red asked
us if we would like to make a video about some of these ideas and we were immediately on board.
So, let's explore this topic together. Is it possible to upload your mind into a computer?
Well, it's complicated.
Upload what exactly? Mind is one of those words that are really hard to define.
It's thought to be the collective abilities of your consciousness and intelligence, the thing
that lets you imagine, recognize, and dream. Mind uploading is the hypothetical concept of making
a copy of this inner world and transferring it into a computer to run a simulation of your
consciousness. But even defining the premise gets really hard, really fast. The possibility of mind
uploading is based on three assumptions. Assumption 1. Your mind is in your brain's
structure, arrangement, and biochemistry. The idea that everything about the mind can be found
in the brain is called physicalism and it keeps our discussion within the domain of natural law.
Assumption 2. At some point, we will understand the brain well enough and possess the technology
to simulate all of its aspects to make a digital mind copy.
Assumption 3. Computer software can host your mind, which means the mind is computable.
There is no physical property in the brain, including consciousness,
that cannot be simulated accurately even if it requires a lot of code.
All of these assumptions have been proposed and challenged by scientists and philosophers
and they remain the subject of passionate debate. With so many fundamental questions
still unanswered, it's hard to discuss the topic without annoying someone.
Whatever your position, every discussion of mind upload has to begin with the brain.
The brain in a nutshell. The brain is the most complex biological structure known
and deserves its own entire video, so let's just take a brief look at it.
Around 100 billion neurons are communicating via 1 million billion connections that are sending
signals up to 1000 times each second, which is 1 quadrillion events every second of your
waking life. And it's not just neurons, there are billions of supporting and immune cells
of various types performing different jobs. On a macro level, the brain can be divided
in two sections with different roles, from breathing and heart rate, to coordinating
movement and involuntary reflexes. The most developed parts, the neocortex,
or the outermost layer of the brain, hold memories, our ability to plan, think and imagine,
hope and dream. Where exactly the you part of the brain is situated is not entirely clear.
We know that areas like the precuneus cortex have the greatest influence on our consciousness,
but also that several areas can network together to share tasks none of them can do alone.
The brain's building blocks are not exactly simple either.
Neurons are not just wires, they alter and process information. Synapses, where signals are handed
over from one neuron to the next, contain receptors for hundreds of chemical signals,
opening them up to outside influence. We have a basic understanding of how these work,
and we can accurately predict their behavior at small scales, but there's a lot more to the brain
than just nerve signals. Hormones play a huge role, like serotonin, which affects our mood,
or histamine, which helps us learn. The brain is influenced by our other parts too,
from heart nerves to gut bacteria. What seemed like a very complicated system to begin with
gets even more complicated the more we learn about it. To get this wildly interconnected mess
of cells and meat and chemicals into a computer, we need a model that we can simulate in our
digital world. Some sort of scan. Unfortunately, our scanning technology, like fMRI machines,
is not nearly good enough to attempt such a thing. But there is a different method that seems very
promising. Cutting a brain into tiny slices and scanning them with a high resolution electron
microscope to create an accurate map of all the cells and connections. In 2019, scientists
successfully mapped a cubic millimeter of mouse brain, roughly the size of a big grain of sand.
It contained 100,000 neurons with a billion synapses and four kilometers of nerve fibers.
This grain of brain was cut into 25,000 slices. Five electron microscopes ran continuously for
five months, collecting more than 100 million images. It took three months to assemble the
images into a 3D model. The completed data set fills up 2 million gigabytes of cloud storage.
To scan a whole human brain, we would have to repeat this effort a million times,
which is much easier said than done. Even worse, to correctly simulate a brain,
we might even have to map out much smaller building blocks to include the billions of
underlying proteins or even individual molecules that cause all the behaviors we see at the cellular
level, which might produce more data than the capacity of all data storage on earth.
Brain water to consciousness wine. While all of these issues are annoying, the real question
is how we turn the static blueprint of the brain into an active thing. Even if we have a scan,
down to the level of synapses, we need laws and rules that animate the wiring diagram.
To endow this static structure with life, update it with the various laws of chemical binding
of electrodynamics to animate the simulation. So it becomes a dynamic active thing like a brain
that exists from one microsecond to the next that could evolve in time, think, see, and act.
The reality is that we just don't know if this is possible to achieve.
If our technology can give rise to real minds. It all hinges on the nature of the problem.
Are the brain and mind just complicated and a lot of work to figure out,
or are they complex in a way that we can't solve? In the worst case, consciousness is more than the
sum of the parts of the brain in a way that we don't realize yet. Complex in a way that we can't
solve by getting better scans. Just having a list of the ingredients might not be enough to get a
good consciousness cake. Right now we have a great starting point with tangible scientific results
and an end goal, but the road to true simulation is unclear and requires a lot of innovation and
research. Humans have historically been horrible at predicting the pace of progress. In the best
case, it's just a matter of doing the work and finding the right solutions. It might not be
necessary to simulate every last cell down to the last atom. Instead, it may be possible to
simplify elements into probabilistic models that could match the behavior of the brain using a more
manageable number of simpler systems. So we really don't know if we will ever understand our brain
and consciousness well enough to upload human minds, but the science is real and worth pursuing.
At the very least, we will just learn a lot about ourselves and develop a bunch of new technologies.
If we succeed, this might put mind uploading well within the capabilities of our rapidly
progressing computer technology. The consequences for humanity and our future in this universe
are vast, creepy, and amazing. The copy. Successful mind uploading is functional
immortality. Unless damaged or deleted, you will continue to exist as long as a copy is stored
somewhere. Of course, if the scan is corrupted in any of a myriad of ways, your mind might get
corrupted too. You might be in an eternity of pain or paranoia or having an endless psychotic
breakdown. The question if this digital mind is you opens another whole can of worms. For now, we'll
just assume that your digital mind at least feels like it's you. How would mind uploading change
your outlook on life? Will you feel safer knowing that death is not necessarily the end? Or would
you try to be super safe to avoid dying before your mind is uploaded? If scanning technology
does become advanced enough, your biological and digital versions could coexist. You could help each
other out by making your biological lifespan more enjoyable, and the future of the copy more secure.
Whatever happens, your mind copy will begin a completely new life once it opens their digital
eyes for the first time. Having a functional body is actually quite nice, and you're pretty used to
it. Food, love, pain and exhaustion, all of these things are parts of us that we must live with.
But in the end, they are the result of neurons firing in your brain.
So while you could decide to live in a simulated body, it might be optional for a digital mind.
Falling in love might lose meaning if you can have it at the press of a button.
Instead, you might end up searching for new extraordinary experiences. Walk on the surface
of the sun. Speed up time to skip past a few boring months. Experience a simulation of the past.
Your perspectives and priorities will change as you continue to exist in this liberated form.
The longer digital minds exist, eventually they will likely gain greater knowledge of themselves
and an ability to change their own contents. This can be as simple as deleting a memory that bugs
you. You might change aspects of your personality, like grudges, addictions or laziness. Without the
constraints of biology, your abilities might move up as technology progresses, while your priorities
or goals might become more and more foreign to your original brain if it's still alive.
Waking up to the true potential of digital immortality will be gradual. You can start projects
that would take more than a lifetime to complete. Scientists could accumulate an incredible amount
of knowledge, leading to discoveries that could revolutionize the world. Adventurers could upload
themselves onto small spaceships and embark on journeys to the stars, just putting themselves
on pause for thousands of years at a time. Although it's unlikely that every digital mind will work for
the benefit of humanity, since our current meat versions don't do that either. Some will seek
power and influence and will have a literal eternity of trying to create empires. Others will
begin hoarding as many resources for themselves as possible as they compete with other minds trying
to do the same. The longer they live, the less sympathy they may feel for simple meat beings.
Or imagine immortal cult leaders who propagate lies and invent religions, fine-tuning and
perfecting their dogma over hundreds of years. Or perhaps none of all that. Maybe our minds are not
made for immortality, and digital minds will just become rigid and unproductive and retire after a
very long life, having experienced everything they could ever want to. It's hard to predict
how much good or bad a self-improving mind could do with hundreds or thousands of years of free time.
While Mind Upload with all its wonders and horrors is beyond our current technological
capabilities, you can use some of your free time in the present and experience one interpretation
of this future right away by hitting the streets of Night City in Cyberpunk 2077. Cyberpunk 2077
is made by CD Projekt Red, the studio that brought us The Wisher series and is one of the most eagerly
awaited games of the last few years. You dive into a dark, dystopian future where incredible technology
is redefining who and what we are. You can become part of this stunningly large world with immersive
storytelling. Here's the thing, we haven't played the game yet, but when you see this video, we're
probably already doing so. If the past work of CD Projekt Red is any indication, then this will be
an amazing game, which is why we did this collaboration and sat on this video for far
too long. So if it's made you curious, check it out.