it's the most wonderful time of the year again the 12,019 human era calendar is
out go get our new limited edition now or regret it forever we heard your
comments on last year's edition so we've updated the design each illustration is
now featured on a full page with so much more space to take notes below exactly
two point three six six eight nine times as much as in the old layout also the
calendar has a spiral binding shiny silver letters on the cover and is
printed on high quality paper that's nice to touch the calendar looks awesome
on your wall but it's also the easiest way to tick off your whole present list
for Christmas if you order now it will arrive before the holidays and it's the
perfect gift for your friends kids grandma doggo mortal enemies or random
strangers you meet on the street on the inside you find 12 brand-new beautiful
illustrations of early human cultures and craftsmanship prior to the first
civilizations and the use of metal this topic is endlessly fascinating to us our
ancestors achievements from 10,000 years ago paved the way for our modern
civilization so we can only dream of what might be possible in the future
through human cooperation by the way if you're wondering about the date we
explained why 12,019 should be our current year in our a new calendar for
humanity video order your calendar now it will be available as a limited
edition until our stock is sold out and then never again the human calendar is a
super fun side project we got to do for the third time thanks to your support we
loved getting mails tweets and pictures with your calendars from over 80
countries last year so we're already looking forward to all your messages
you