As the year 12,021 slowly comes to an end, we present to you the 12,022 Human Era Calendar, Eons Edition.
As always, we're adding 10,000 years to the regular calendar to represent the human era and include all cultures around the world.
But this year, we're expanding the scope beyond humanity to showcase forgotten animals and plants from all across the Phanerozoic Eon,
like giant armored fish, scythe lizards or giant sloths on 12 elaborate pages.
Witness how multicellular life has persisted for over half a billion years, surviving asteroid impacts, volcanoes and frozen oceans.
And of course, pandemics.
In the end, life, er, finds a way.
And we want to celebrate that.
You can get the very shiny high-quality limited edition now until we sell out and then never again.
To support what we do on this channel, to fill the void in your soul or just to have something beautiful to look at.
As every year, we also have bundles and special calendar deals with some of your favorite products.
Thank you so much to all of the thousands of burbs who get the calendar every year.
You enable us to create videos and to publish them for free for everyone.
We wish you a happy year, 12,022.