Okay, yeah, it is a bit late for coffee in the UK, but upload days now with the addition
of director's commentary days are very long days.
So I'm quite tired by the end of it, but I feel like the right way to do this is to do
the director's commentary on the same day of upload.
If I don't do the director's commentary on the same day, then I know what's going to
happen, which is I'm going to start really preparing for it and then I'm going to turn
it into a whole other job and then it will never happen.
So this is why it's like director's commentary right away, whatever I happen to remember
or nothing.
So that's the way it's going to work.
This is a video that I really didn't expect I was going to do a director's commentary
for because I mean, obviously this is only the fourth one, so I'm still kind of figuring
this out, but for the Grey Goes Outside playlist things that I've been working on, these already
feel a little bit like they're behind the scenes videos anyway, so it's a bit odd to
do a director's commentary for them and I think they're just a lot less dense and intense
than the main CGP Grey animated stuff.
So I think in general, if I'm doing stuff like this in the future, there probably won't
be a director's commentary, but this Ticoi project, boy, did it turn out to be a whole
thing.
So I figure there's at least a little mini director's commentary in this one.
Would you classify this video as one of your light grey videos?
No.
I created on the channel this playlist in a category that I'm calling light grey.
That is for stuff that is really easy and is relatively unedited and unresearched.
So like the little video that I put up before this of just me driving the Tesla straight
into a bunch of tumbleweed that was like a cut scene, that's like a light grey video.
I think that sort of video can be kind of fun, but it's obviously not a main video or
like I did the explanation of the Supreme Court recently and for various reasons, like
that's a video that I could make without having to do a ton of research.
It doesn't need to be as tightly edited.
And so yeah, that's like a different category.
You know what this is, I'm putting this under my playlist of like grey goes outside, which
really I could not have timed worse as a project I was really planning on doubling down this
year on with the global pandemic.
So this is obviously a project that's a little bit left over for that.
But yeah, I had a whole bunch of things in mind for like grey goes outside as a concept
and the world had other ideas.
So that's the category this fits into and who knows how much stuff will appear on that
at any point in the future.
But that's the answer to your question of what do I consider this?
I consider this a grey goes outside video.
It's not a main video.
It's not a light grey video.
It's me being outside and exploring a place.
Yeah, the harbor master.
I could make a vlog taking out the trash and that is just about the most exciting outdoor
thing that I have done in several months.
So I hope everyone's doing all right.
So to give you a sense of this, I was talking to my assistant this morning and we were just
trying to trace back.
How long have we been working on this thing?
Because from our subjective experience, it feels like we have been working on Tico for
forever.
And the answer was the first correspondence between the two of us about this project goes
to May of last year.
That is more than a year ago when I first decided to bring someone in on this project
and then I don't know exactly how long before that I was working on this and sort of investigating
it as a possible thing.
But so yeah, May of last year is when this became like a real this looks like it's going
to happen project.
Still not as old as the Catan video.
Well, yes, I mean technically that's correct, but the Catan video is not actively being
worked on the Ticoi project was actively worked on for the past year and a bunch of different
ways.
But yeah, so it's just a very very long time ago and the way that this worked.
I was going to the Skull Valley Indian Reservation for other reasons at that time and it just
so happened that I came across this what I thought was just an incidental piece of
information that oh the on this reservation there happens to be this I didn't even know
what it was exactly like old weapons facility or something like I it was extremely hard
to figure out at the time but I could see that they like had this place as or like this
facility existed on the reservation is the best way to put it in the process of going
out to Skull Valley and going to the reservation.
I was able to get permission from the tribe to be able to go on to go on to Ticoi.
That's how this happens.
This is not a facility that you can just go visit like if anybody is out in the area like
don't drive down to Ticoi and just think you're going to see something you cannot go
on there.
They're not joking when they say that the area is patrolled.
It is also super dangerous like if people don't know that you're there it's not a it's
not a good place like it is an abandoned old facility and given that there's a lot of underground
construction and a lot of this stuff are huge metal doors and all the rest of it like
it's not a place to just go wandering on your own like that's a bad idea if people don't
know that you're there.
It's sort of funny as a creator because when I made the first video where I showed me just
exploring Ticoi I thought that would be kind of clear when I showed people the opening
scene is oh I'm unlocking the gates with this key and I figured like this is a clear
enough indication that I have permission to be here and this is not a place that you should
go there's a there's a lock and I am unlocking it and then at the end you know I'm closing
it back up but boy did I get a lot of comments from people about how did you go there like
people wanting to visit it themselves.
So yeah I guess I guess I was a little bit wrong about how clear that message is of unlocking
the gate but yeah so I just just want to say like it's not a public place that that a person
can go visit I was able to get permission from the tribal leaders and I had to sign
a lot of waivers in order to be able to go there so that's the that's the behind the
scenes of of how did this actually come to happen.
Really getting this secluded office space that you want I actually had I actually had
a little line that I cut from the exploration video where there was a bunker that was way
off to the side of the facility that I thought oh this actually would be a really charming
writing space if I could just get some air conditioning down there like I would really
love this as an office that didn't make it into the the original exploration video.
Oh one more thing before I before I could hear one more thing about the exploration
video before I forget the other really minor thing which I just just want to make clear
and I wish I had thought to put it in the original video but I did not take the badge
that I lift off of the rack in the opening of the exploration video like that that was
a little bit of oh let me show you the badge and the idea was that oh like oh I need this
to be here right this is the badge for being a tikoy you don't go to a unique historical
site and just take yourself a bunch of souvenirs that you're never going to look at but I was
pretty surprised by how many people are like oh I've got to take one of those badges it's
like no no no no no that's not what these places are you know you leave them for the
next people who are going to be there or you leave them to be reconstructed and restored
in the future but yeah so that's one thing it didn't occur to me at the time that I needed
to film putting the badge back on the rack but I just I just didn't think about it and
yeah that was an interesting piece of feedback from people would I ever go to Chernobyl it's
an interesting question probably not I don't know what the background radiation is for
that place now like how dangerous that is compared to other things but I think my gut
reaction is Chernobyl to me is not interesting enough that I would want to increase my risk
of getting cancer by visiting it even if it's a relatively small amount okay were there
classified things Revolution Dudes is asking were there classified things you couldn't
show on camera so as best I could tell here's some paperwork everything that was left there
was not classified documents now of course I didn't read through every piece of paper
that was there but there was lots of stuff that had obviously been removed there was
nothing on site that was classified but this project was weird because it kept running
up against the I'll say it this way like the edges of classified things but maybe we can
maybe we can get to that a little bit later okay all right let me actually start this
thing is my theory is that I want to do a relatively short one of these just to prove
to myself that I can this is the ticoi test range or at least it once was the site is
long abandoned now but it once served a vital purpose oh okay I don't know okay this is
this is one of these things where as a creator you're really pleased with something but I
don't know if anybody notices or cares I spent a million years on this okay so this is footage
of footage of me on the facility and then I do this little just little fade transitions
look guys look we're going we're going back in time back in time to the 1980s and this
is footage from ticoi when it was in operation now I don't know okay I need to be here's
the thing I need to be a little bit careful about the way I say things because for this
project it was necessary to have like legal consultation for some parts of it and prior
to this video existing as far as me and my assistant were able to determine there was
absolutely no public footage available of ticoi in operation at the time like no video
no photographs but this piece of footage was acquired and is the debut of anyone being
able to see what the facility looked like when it was an operation and just by total
dumb luck I happen to film myself in one spot where whoever the camera operator was
what I what I think what I suspect happens is the camera was just misaligned it happened
to be pointing at the bunker and then the camera operator guy you know real real aligned
the camera to where it's supposed to be and started to zoom in on on one of the tests
so I feel like this is just a lucky accident from 30 years ago and a lucky accident from
me a year and a half ago filming this thing that I was able to able to transition back
and forth so I'm telling you all about this because I spent forever on it and I was really
I was really determined I'm like I am going to fit this transition in the video somewhere
if it kills me so there we go served a vital purpose a military purpose and the work done
at ticoi is still out in the world today constructed during the cold war at the entrance to the
facility is a warning sign in Russian so everybody asks what does the sign in Russian say and
what I've what I've been delighted by is some people in the exploration video went through
all of the trouble of trying to translate the sign like typing it into Google or using
like translation software on a screenshot or something what the sign in Russian says
is what this sign in English says right next to it this they are the same sign and it's
like the list of prohibited items that are not allowed on the site you know so hey you're
coming on to a missile motor test site please don't bring matches cigarette lighters other
flame producing devices firearms ammunition drugs and intoxicants like those are the things
that you cannot bring on to a missile motor test site don't do that that's really bad
Russian but this is not the former Soviet Union this is the great state of Utah where
in skull intoxicants not allowed for Russians oh yeah I mean guys yes I know it says please
no cameras but it's not an operation anymore so it's okay I can bring the camera there
like I had permission it's all it's all totally fine so here's a map of Utah the geography
is that there are like four mountain ranges that cause three valleys and the easternmost
valley is where Salt Lake City is that's where like all the people live there's a valley
in the middle which is much less populated than the westernmost valley is is skull valley
which just has a tremendously awesome name and to the west here is the great Salt Lake
desert enormous and terrifying and yeah just an absolutely deadly deadly region skull valley
is extremely depopulated I think the reservation population is I mean I'd have to double check
the numbers but I want to say it can't be more than 40 or 50 people at most who are
living on the living on the reservation so it's it's a pretty it's pretty isolated area
but directly to the west the Salt Valley is used for a lot of weapons testing so any anyone
in Utah probably knows like this is the UTTR which is the Utah Utah test and training range
aircraft and bombs and other weapons are tested out there and I mean if the Salt Lake desert
is beautiful but it's also like if you got to pick a place in the continental United
States where you're going to test some weapons and nobody's going to notice or care it's probably
not a bad spot but it does it does leave skull valley like the first area where there is some
population right up against this and I think that's part of the reason why the ticoi test
facility was was put where it was because the missiles themselves are manufactured closer
to Salt Lake City but then skull valley is like within convenient striking distance of other
military other military facilities on the Great Salt Lake so just sort of was like a little spot
in the middle Lee ticoi resides much of what happened on site was classified and equipment
and documents were removed but what remains is enough to piece together the story of ticoi the
paperwork left behind bears the logo of Hercules incorporated Hercules got its start in the late
1800s with a patent improving on dynamite to the creator named Hercules powder and began
manufacturing the new explosive just outside of San Francisco in a company town that would outlive
the company Hercules California one of the difficult things in trying to put together
these videos is is trying to figure out what do you include what do you not include and a lot of
this Hercules stuff was really killing me so the video should be about ticoi right like I've put
up a video that it that shows the exploration of this place and now I should put up a video
that is the explanation of the place but I did get a little bit derailed by Hercules because in
order to try to figure out okay like what was this place the first thing that you need to figure out
is okay well who ran it and the answer is this this company called Hercules but just just like
with ticoi there was not a lot of information about Hercules that was public on the internet
but was able to trace it back to this patent that we pulled from the patent office website
that started off like this company now there's there's a line here where I'm sort of glossing
over some of the details right where what do I say it's with a patent improving on it's got
it start in the late 1800 right so yeah so I say like Hercules got its start in the late 1800s I
tried not to dig into the details too much but it seems like this guy Joseph Willard he patented
Hercules powder it's this improvement on dynamite but he was working for DuPont at the time and
something happened within the company where eventually the United States government as part
of like trust busting and monopoly busting decided like DuPont was too big of a monopoly
on chemical productions and so I don't say that the company was like founded in the late 1800s
just that it got its start but the the United States government apparently came in and said
like DuPont you're too much of a monopoly we're gonna split you we're gonna split you into several
other companies and like DuPont obviously went on and became its own thing but Hercules became
a separate company and this patents for this particular kind of explosives was like the
foundation of what the business was in terms of intellectual property like okay you Hercules you
own this new explosive that's what you get DuPont you don't get this explosive you have to go make
baby powder and other things and I'd never heard of Hercules but it turns out that like from
starting as this you know making making better dynamite for farmers seemed like the primary use
in the late 1800s they exploded to become just an absolutely ginormous company and I kept having to
cut stuff about Hercules from the video because it really isn't about them but it blew my mind how
huge they were like they had dozens and dozens of production sites all over the US manufacturing
gunpowder and then later manufacturing intercontinental nuclear ballistic missiles
it's just unreal they were involved in like every aspect of chemical production they did
petroleum they did turpentine like it's crazy how much they actually created and better better
dynamite for farmers to deal with the tumbleweeds yes I'm sure well we'll get we'll get to it in the
end but so anyway I spent forever like just trying to research this company be like what's the deal
and at one point I found what I thought like oh this is this is gonna be this is gonna be my
salvation this is now I'm gonna get all the answers that I want and my research is over so
let me let me find for you a little video to show you this is my desk here in my office so back when
the video had way more about Hercules than any normal person would care I thought I was going
to mention like the story of discovering this book but I ended up not doing that because nobody cares
but so this is as as far as I can tell this is like the canonical and maybe only book that exists
about the history of Hercules incorporated and it's huge it's and it's written by two guys who
it seems like this is what they do they like they just pick companies and go through and and write
these really detailed histories about it and so when I found this book I was just I was really
pumped and like yes I'm going to have all of the answers that I could ever possibly want and while
I read it and they did have a lot of interesting things about Hercules Ticoi is not even mentioned
in the book not once like it's not in the index it never ever appears anywhere in this book because
the company was so huge that Ticoi was just like an incidental little like nothing piece
of information compared to everything else that they were involved in I originally kind of thought
that would be a fun thing to mention like Oh Ticoi was so huge that the definitive book about the
company doesn't even mention Ticoi but it just like it just didn't work and then it also causes
like it's a little bit weird to cut away to my desk and and like later me showing you a book
it wasn't the point of that so I'm kind of showing you in the director's commentary but it was Gumbo
is asking how dry is the book like college textbook I guess I would I guess I would say
that you probably would want a reason to read the book would be the way I might want to phrase that
there are things that are like interesting if you've spent a year of your life trying to like
make a project about this weird abandoned facility but I would not put it on my list of like general
books to recommend for reading also I love there's like this picture here of this of this poor dude
on the bottom where they're like oh yeah here's a guy I don't remember where that plant is but
here's a guy his job is to transport nitroglycerin using this little like rickety looking baskets I
would not want to have to transport nitroglycerin using this thing and I say in the beginning of
the video that 60 people or about 60 people died in the manufacturing plant in California
I didn't say it clearly enough in the video because it really was just the people in that
plant in California there were plenty other of plenty other explosions nationwide related to
Hercules and all the various things that they did but yeah so anyway this book exists and yeah I
thought it was gonna be a gold mine that would solve all of my problems but nope did someone
post an Amazon link in the in the ghost chat hey if you know if you want to read it I'm not gonna
stop you oh yeah if you're totally right a plus on the book's name though labors of a modern
Hercules is an amazing title for that book like a plus oh I forgot to mention the other weird thing
about the book is it was written in like 1990 or 1989 and so at the very end there's mention of
how in the facility that I mentioned later West Baucus the author of the book saw all the Soviet
inspectors there as part of the facility and he's like oh what a what a new world we live in where
the Soviet Union is here at Hercules manufacturing facilities in the United States like how strange
is that and it was also super frustrating to me because since the book stopped in 89 or 90 all of
the questions I had about how this how this gigantic company went out of business like what
are the details none of those were present in the book because all of that happened like five years
later and there was a lot of digging around online to try to like answer that question more
precisely but again you have to realize at some point this isn't actually a video about the
company Hercules right I'm not adopting or I'm not adapting labors of a modern Hercules into a video
I'm supposed to be making a video about what this weird place called ticoi was so yeah this is this
is part of like the decisions that you have to make behind the scenes local products but their
smokeless gunpowder rapidly grew them to become a vital United States military supplier during the
world wars as the posters said Hercules men and women in the war keep them shooting I always love
these old war posters it's like these old propaganda posters they have such a distinct look
to them and it's like here's here's Uncle Sam he's trying to he's trying to raise money by selling
war bonds it's not clear in the video but the context of this is I think he's trying to guilt
the people who live in the factory town of Hercules like hey guys I know you're literally
manufacturing the bullets from my weapons but it's not enough you also have to buy Uncle Sam's war
bonds you come over to these so I found I found a few of these on the National Archives do I have
the other one so again I think these are like propaganda slash recruitment posters for Hercules
these were produced these are produced during the Second World War I find their messaging is like a
little mixed it's a little bit unclear like what they're what they're trying to what they're
trying to say here I'm glad of the chance to do something real while my husband's in the army and
say you know these machinists are swell that's like Sophie I like I get I feel like I get the
message but maybe there's there's like a better there's a better way to word this especially
because like these machinists are swell I'd like what do you what do you mean by that and it's you
know the I get to do something real it's just it's just odd it's odd messaging you know or like the
other guy over here he's putting in a full day every day at Hercules and he has to otherwise
he'd be letting down his kid who works in the parachute troops like you know that's a lot of
pressure yeah I don't know I just I find these kinds of things these sorts of posters really
interesting and there's one more can I pull it up yeah so here's the third one so this little logo
is is just pulled out from a third one that had a different color scheme which is which is this
guy he's talking to his he's talking to his buddies we may not be welding tanks but boy
we're keeping a Hercules plant running and that's something in this war it's just amazing it's a bit
like the old newsreels and propaganda videos where it's the same thing like there's something
earnest and deceptive about them at the same time Mary yeah posters were so wordy back then
yeah that's that's right people had more time to read posters back in in 1940 like what else
are you gonna do you don't have a smartphone to distract you you might as well read all the
propaganda posters being posted on the wall yeah no they look like they show up in a Fallout game
for sure cold war came next and brought with it a new weapon the intercontinental ballistic missile
tipped with a nuclear warhead now one country could destroy another remotely and the only
defense was a credible threat of retaliation this drew the United States and the Soviet Union into
an arms race I was working with the animator for a long time on this shot and the the sort of
inspiration and and the the design for this concept was a little bit of the the screens
in war games the movie all right so that like at the end there's all of these like these maps and
you're seeing all of the nuclear weapons spread on the maps you know and and that was kind of the
like the direction that I gave for this one is like what what it what if the you know the the
war game stuff like we're seeing it happen on an actual globe it's not happening on like on a
computer screen it states and the Soviet Union into an arms race building more and faster and
bigger nuclear weapons each year for the again this thing like the animator did the absolute
last minute just just today was animating in this graph which I just love I totally love the way it
looks like I love the cool smoky look and if it looks familiar this is the same effect that was
used on the time travel portal in the national popular interstate vote compact when gray goes
back in time there's like a blue smoky portal and that's the same effect that's being used on the
edge of the line up here United States this culminated with the Minuteman unlike earlier
missiles which had to be launched out in the open and were slow to fuel with liquid propellant the
Minuteman could be launched from an underground silo and thus be hidden in America's cornfields
the new solid fuel motors able to launch them instantly yeah so this is also I don't know how
clear this is to people like what what you're actually looking at here but it's really quite
shocking how open the United States is with some of the information about its nuclear weapons
program and you know one of the things that it's open about is is the location of some of these
nuclear silos but yeah if you like zoom in on Google Earth and you're looking around in a
northwestern Nebraska you can totally just find the nuclear silos if you know what you're looking
for this is a little hatch that opens up the Minuteman missile is underneath there's a little
bit of a entryway above ground for the military personnel to go into and and like the whole
facility is is under the ground here you know this is this is like unnamed country road number
four just going through a bunch of farmland but if you turn right at the correct moment it's like
oh and there is a Minuteman 3 nuclear missile underneath the ground right along the side there
it's crazy yes I know that you can tour some of these things another thing that has just is killed
it's killed me be that this there's like not being able to go outside thing is is heartbreaking
because yeah I know that there are places where you can tour some of these facilities that are
no longer active and this is a case where my original summer plans part of what I was going
to do was I wanted to wrap up this ticoi project by going back to Skull Valley and being able to
do a few more things like I wanted this project to be more of a thing than it ended up being but
the practicalities of it were just like look who knows when I'm going to be able to travel next
this project is already more than a year old I've got to wrap it up otherwise I am going to go crazy
but I would really have loved to be able to have made a trip to one of these silos that you can see
in person but that was not in the cards for this year so maybe it'll have to be a future episode
of Grey Goes Outside but we harvest corn here corn and nukes yeah that feels again very very
American like what a week what do we grow we grow nuclear weapons and we grow corn oh I have to I
have to show you like can I find it really quickly though but again some of these old videos about
like how the how the weapons work are totally crazy pants okay all right so this I just love
it this is this is the like the glory of America all right the minute man is ready primed in the
earth beneath its hardened blast-proof cap in the vast open lands of America from the
grasses of Wyoming to the North Dakota plains from the North Dakota standing guard amidst the
old ports silent sentinels of freedom on strategic alert in the defense of America
I just love it like it's amazing right they're like oh we have these nuclear weapons that can
fly out of the ground but like what are they doing they're protecting our beautiful grasslands and
and like oh there's silent sentinels in the ground we've got children with ponies to protect and we
need nuclear weapons it's amazing these things are totally they're totally unreal there's one
I don't know if I can find it really quick the reason I have these these videos that loaded up
in Final Cut I had a I had a brief cut of this project where I included I included some of this
footage but I decided like it just didn't fit tonally I wanted this to be just like okay I went
to this place and now I'm going to explain to you what it was and it was a little bit weird to cut
sometimes to this old like propaganda footage and then to cut back but I really did I really did
greatly enjoy producing some of this stuff so is this the it's this video where the narrator is
like really passive-aggressive about the Soviet Union and like America has to protect the world
and the Soviet Union doesn't I think it's this part all of these various projects while perhaps
not sufficiently emphasized in light of today's events did help the Air Force to understand the
problems of pilotless missiles and to begin to build its operational force Russia in the meantime
not hampered by having to police the world that's what it is right they're like we're working on our
missiles program Russia meanwhile like they get to just be the baddies because they don't have to
police the world it's amazing Russia in the meantime not hampered by having to police the
world concentrate on whatever weapon of war she desired since Russia did not have to worry about
aggressive attack from the free world she could jump ahead and develop weapons of the future at
her discretion this is we now know she did this is amazing right like because we're the goodies
like she didn't have to worry about us attacking them so they so like she got to make all the evil
weapons that she wanted which is such a weird like it's such a weird way to explain this
situation plus like given contemporary documents we now have of like what was going on at the time
we totally know that Russia was like their number one concern was like the rest of the world was
going to invade them at any moment but this propaganda film portrays it like oh the Soviet
Union knew that like the good guys would never attack them and so they just went on to build a
bunch of nuclear weapons because they're evil unlike our nuclear weapons which we're building
because we're policing the world it's just amazing you know what no I've got to I've got to stop well
just okay one more this gleaming metallic instrument is being developed in a race against time the Air
Force plans to win by taking calculated risks based on sound technical judgment only once
before in the Manhattan Project has this nation taken a comparable gamble of such billion dollar
immensity that time the stake was atomic energy to stop a war this time we aim for a ballistic
missile force to keep the peace yeah we're gonna keep that peace we're gonna keep it it's amazing
you know it's just like this gleaming weapon this is this is ours right there's bad things
happening in the world but this is these are these are ballistic weapons to keep the peace
like I just love the way it's presented you know I mean like you can totally have a conversation
that's reasonable and about like what safety do nuclear weapons provide and like the game
theoretical logic of mutually assured just like you can have this conversation and you can be on
either side of like does this makes does this make people safe does it not make people like
there's an adult conversation to be had there but this is just like hilarious propaganda for
children yes that's right lizard heart that's exactly right it's like the beautiful good
nuclear weapons versus the evil nuclear weapons also I don't know if you noticed but like whoever
made this film I totally love you know this is like 1950s Final Cut editor but you notice how
like the America stuff is all blue and beautiful and Russia is evil and red right it's like look
at our beautiful blue bombers like look at this evil Soviet Union it's hilarious okay all right
I'm getting distracted I'm sorry okay here we go launched out in the open and we're slow to fuel
with liquid propellant the Minuteman could be launched from an underground silo and thus be
hidden in America's cornfields the new solid fuel motors able to launch them instantly the
United States ordered 1,000 Minuteman missiles to be constructed which brings us back to Hercules
and ticoi for as a bullet in a round needs powder to hit a target so too does the nuclear warhead in
a Minuteman missile need its solid fuel motor I don't think this quite worked in the video I was
trying to draw this analogy like if I was going to spend an infinite amount of time rewriting it
I feel like I would have wanted to draw this analogy more closely that Hercules got their
start manufacturing this smokeless gunpowder that's like really what gave them their start
now in in the time that we're talking about like what was ticoi they're manufacturing the like
gunpowder equivalent of an ICBM but I don't think it quite came across right and again that this is
where you have to you have to put limits on how much you're going to rewrite things or rerecord
things or try to make stuff like perfectly fit together I also feel like this is a little bit
of a probably for most viewers of the channel like again doing the director's commentaries
right after I don't know how people are reacting but I wouldn't be surprised if this is a video
that a lot of people think is kind of boring so you know I've already spent probably way more
time on this than makes any kind of economic sense but I did get I did get a little bit obsessed with
it need its solid fuel motor Hercules manufactured the motors at a plant called Bacchus West in Magna
Utah and brought them to ticoi for testing the large concrete cubes still here are thrust blocks
their purpose to be an immovable object for a missile motor to push against during test firing
each motor needed to be individually calibrated hitting a target a quarter of the world away while
traveling at mach 20 is a precise affair excellent work by the animator to do the ICBM here and even
when I was just sent the like the really rough version of it like here's the outline of what we
want I think it really is kind of shocking to see how it motor works you know okay there's a
missile that goes up in into the sky and then it turns around and it comes back down but I really
do think there's something quite visceral about seeing what is basically a parabolic arc right
that people like you intrinsically know from things like throwing a baseball or whatever and
the way the animation is of the actual warheads coming down like I think it it's really quite a
striking piece of animation like it's it's it's incredibly well done you know it's not the whole
missile that comes down and and strikes I think that's a bit of a misconception that people have
that it's like the missile hits but it really is just this tiny payload at the very end which are
the warheads and the intercontinental ballistic missile can have many warheads and I think the
the early Minutemen had two later versions had three and I don't know I don't know what the
what the current state of technology is for warhead miniaturization but yeah I think it really is
quite striking just to see the like the simplicity of it thrust block technicians would connect
to measure heat and pressure and those sensors connected via underground cables to instrument
bunkers where engineers would record the results with state-of-the-art 1970s computer assistants
set up for each test could take a week or more so the motor and engineers and equipment had to be
protected from the elements but a missile can't be fired inside a building without melting the
structure around it and invalidating the test to solve so this is this is finally the part of the
video where I actually get to kind of explain like much more what ticoi is and again part of
the reason why I had such a hard time finishing up this project is like my original vision was I
never intended for there to be two videos I wanted for there to be one video that was both the
exploration and the explanation at the same time that was the original idea but when I was making
the first exploration video just the fact of the matter was there is absolutely nothing available
that could show what did this facility look like you know it was a classified facility and many of
the things related to it are still classified today and so I ended up having to just make the
first video a pure explanation one and kind of putting out a little call for like hey if you
know anything get in touch in the end I actually feel like it worked better as two parts I like
having the explanation and the exploration separate but I had originally thought when I
put up the exploration video I was like oh I'll have the explanation done in in two weeks I'm
gonna I'm gonna wrap this up real quick but meanwhile like two months of very solid work
later it's it's finally actually done but it is very surreal personally for me to see like oh
here's this footage of me in this location and then to see test footage from the time of like oh
I know exactly which thrust block that is you know there's three thrust blocks on site and this is
the big one that was at the you know the far end of the facility so it's it's a it's a strange
experience personally let's go let's move on to the exciting parts solve this the buildings at
ticoi were constructed on rails so they could be pulled back before firing and also give the
nearby camera houses a clear view of the test this will be the fine of d5 second stage at 5b
250 minus ten nine eight seven six five four three two one zero we have ignition Hercules did
improve thanks chat I'm glad the chat seems to agree that they like the the two parts that it
worked yeah I do think in the end it works better than my original idea I just you know I just never
expected it to take this long or to be this much work as always is the case I think oh I'm at the
Skull Valley Reservation working on what is the the main project and this and this will be just a
fun little diversion this this will be just like a oh look what a what a little a small fractal
shard that I can pick up and just easily turn into a fun video about what this place is it's
fast-forward a year and several months later and it's finally done okay so here here is where we
get the actual labeling of the facility so yeah this this is like where it comes together you
can see what all the different parts are you have that the test site which is in the building on
rails the thrust block is inside that building if the instrumentation bunker there are three camera
houses there's another one which is being hidden by the building itself and then the lightning rods
that are around it to divert the lightning strikes and I feel like I'm incredibly lucky that there
was an oncoming storm when I happened to be filming this you're glad the storm was correctly
labeled do you like I spent a long time trying to figure out if I could put an arrow to point
to the storm but it just didn't work so I ended up going with like a little label just like I can
label the whole background okay killed a t-coin oh right so yeah here we get to serious part
explosions nonetheless one man was killed a t-coin in 1984 crushed beneath a motor that came loose
during securement to the test block an accident for which the United States Occupational Safety
and Health Administration find Hercules 640 doll I had to kind of have my assistant just sanity
check me on this one of like does this report really say six hundred and forty dollars like
is that actually is that actually correct you know and and you can you can look up this accident
reports on on OSHA there's a description at the bottom which is you know it's a it's a little
difficult to understand I feel like if a man died on a facility like maybe you could include
a diagram not just a bunch of all caps sentences with tech jargon but yeah he was crushed to death
underneath the missile motor when it came loose and yeah I cannot believe that the penalty was
six hundred and forty dollars you know even if you do inflation from like 1984 dollars to now
that's not enough dollars but the thing is like right it's six hundred and forty dollars but
that's infinity more dollars than all of the people who died in the explosions in the original plant
in California or all the stuff before OSHA existed so I guess like this is an improved upward trend
but it was still really is really quite shocking to come across this as as part of the research
dollars the end of the 1980s was the beginning of the end for Hercules the United States had
been slowing production of nuclear warheads and needed fewer missiles to carry them ticoy was used
less as a testing site and more as a storage location as military contracts dried up leading
to hundreds of layoffs in the early 1990s what I'm saying right here about ticoy became a storage
facility I think this is also part of the reason going back to the very beginning why by the time
I get there it's you know where it's been abandoned for a long time there's not much
confidentiality there's not much confidential equipment left on site or like those things had
already started to be removed it seems like you know by the mid 1990s or so that that the ticoy
facility was already on the way down though the United States no longer needed the facility for
strategic production it was still strategically useful in a different way politics in 1991 the
United States and the Soviet Union signed start the strategic arms reduction treaty where both
agreed to reduce the size of their nuclear stockpiles because of course neither country
was just going to take the word of the other numerous trust but verify policies were put into
place for example both sides disabling their long-range bombers out in the open for the others
satellites to see this little detail it doesn't really belong in this story of of ticoy but I
found this too fascinating not to include and I can't I can't imagine ever coming across this in
a video again as a place to mention it but there's something really that I find quite amazing about
these photographs of bombers and it was it was in the treaty that they had to be like all the tail
fins had to be cut off and they were literally left out just out in the open so that the spy
satellites from the other country would be able to see them and to confirm that they had been
dismantled it's an interesting question about trying to disarm and I mean we'll get to the
inspectors in just a second but it is a it's a weird thing when you think about it like how do
you try to let someone else know that you actually have disarmed and that you haven't like hidden a
bunch of bombers somewhere else that they don't know about it's a it's a difficult question and
this is this is one of oops this is one of the mechanisms that they tried to come up with and
presumably because like each of these are just so expensive to make that even if you were like
hiding bombers you're still incurring such a tremendous cost on yourself by destroying a
bunch of these things. Gombos to answer the question how long were they left there I don't
remember I do I know I came across it in the treaty at some point that they had to be left
out for a certain period of time but I don't I don't remember offhand I don't remember offhand
what that was there and nothing a bit of shiny tape couldn't fix I would not want to fly in a
plane where where they had welded the the tail fin back on no thank you. The open for the others
satellites to see and each country picked weapon production sites the other could inspect the
United States provided a list of dozens of sites for the Soviets one of which was the
ticoi test ring this is also where to go back to the book from before where is it so on this list
you can see that a couple of the other test sites Hercules plant number one Magna Utah and I forget
somewhere else somewhere else on here is another Hercules plant but I think the Hercules plant in
Magna Utah is the the one where they were building the motors and this is the one that the authors of
labor of a modern Hercules were observing and where they saw the Soviet inspectors as part of
that process is why the sign in Russian is at the entrance temporary housing for the inspection
team was built in the Soviet Union to ensure the Americans had not installed any bugs in the walls
or tampered with the equipment and transported to Utah forming a small Soviet outpost in Magna the
flags of which had to be changed after the Soviet Union dissolved and inspection duties fell to the
Russian Federation these bunkers okay you know what let me get to the end of the video but don't
let me forget about the bunkers because I have a bunch of things to say at the bunkers but let's
just let's let's finish this off Russian Federation ticoi limped on during the inspection period but
in 1995 with too many cancelled contracts the now failing Hercules incorporated put itself up for
sale acquired by Alliant tech systems and American aerospace defense and sporting goods company okay
yeah so that's not that's not like a joke as far as I can tell Alliant tech systems really does
make military gear and sporting equipment which I guess kind of makes sense like I didn't look into
it too far but maybe that stuff like paintball guns and body pads like I have I have no idea and
again you can't research absolutely everything but someone had asked the question earlier about
Hercules going bankrupt or going out of business I should say they didn't go bankrupt they sold
themselves off and yeah I found it kind of frustrating because I wanted to know more of
the details about like how does this happen how does a company that is a major supplier to the
US military go out of business and you know there weren't great answers like we were able to find a
bunch of articles at the time but they would all just like say these vague things about cancelled
contracts so I don't have a good answer but I do find it interesting like how enormous companies
can just disappear and so I kind of guess or presume that with Hercules it's the same way
that it goes with a lot of other big companies that they they end up acquiring a lot of fixed
costs over time and then if the market just slightly changes like they're left with a huge
number of fixed costs and it's hard to be profitable that's what puts them in trouble
and they end up going bankrupt or as Hercules did selling themselves off I didn't mention it
in the video but Hercules split into two and they sold all of the missile stuff to Alliant
tech systems the actual Hercules company existed for I can't remember I think until like 2004 and
then the rest of the company got bought by someone else and I don't remember off the top of my head
who that was but but this is again where you have to make a decision in a video and it's like does
it matter that not all of Hercules was sold off in this moment probably not we can just sort of
simplify that and say like Hercules was sold off even though part of it continued to exist but yeah
I I really wish that labors of a modern Hercules had been written six years later it could have
covered the details of how did this actually disappear but you know what even if it had been
written later without a doubt I would have read it found it interesting and probably written a
similar sentence that just kind of glosses over quickly like what what is that that happened I
included this this was like one of the few things I could find for Alliant tech systems at the time
but I love this image that they had on their website of like Alliant tech systems we make
rockets and guns and it's just you know America has a very America culture that I can't help but
love right like it's it's like ridiculous and awesome at the same time right it's it's like
it's why it's often parodied in like the Fallout games and that kind of stuff is is there's there
is a sort of ridiculous and awesome like don't tread on me American s and it definitely comes
definitely comes through sometimes American aerospace defense and sporting goods company
in 1999 the lease on this land expired Alliant tech systems did not renew and control of the
Ticoi test range reverted to the Skull Valley Indian Reservation within the borders of which
Ticoi sits I know what I'm doing here and I I intentionally did want to wait the whole video
before mentioning that this is actually on the Skull Valley Indian Reservation because it because
I do think there's there's not a small number of viewers who were paying attention and who
even if they're not watching the directors commentaries they're like they're not watching
the behind-the-scenes stuff I imagine for a lot of viewers this is like the lightbulb moment that
explains oh this is what all like this nonsense has been with these two videos that gray made like
why did he make this video where he just walks around an abandoned place why is he telling me
about a bunch of Cold War nonsense that I don't care about oh he was out there for the Indian
reservations and like all of this is just a fractal off of that again for me as a viewer
you know the kinds of things that I watch I like those moments like I really appreciate when a
creator sort of lets you in on like hey you're a viewer who pays attention this is a detail that I
know you will love and will make it feel like the puzzle pieces have come together so it is part of
the reason why like on the earlier maps or in the beginning of the video I don't say it first hey
this is on the Skull Valley Indian Reservation I wait until the last possible second to mention
it and links yes you're totally right one of my favorite things about driving out west is these
Buffalo crossing signs like they are amazing and I mean you know I can't say I can't say too much
but the the Skull Valley go shoot Indian tribe they do have a pack of Buffalo we'll leave it at
that it operates no more its work lives on of the 1,000 minute man missiles constructed during the
Cold War 400 are still active waiting with their solid fuel motors calibrated here at Ticoi to
launch at a moment's notice so I don't know how surprising that end is for people I think I don't
know for me before going out to Ticoi and before reading about any of this stuff there's a there's
a way in which I tend to think of the Cold War as oh the the Cold War is over like it's a thing
that happened a long time ago and is is totally irrelevant and while that is true with almost all
of history and almost all of wars there is a way in which I think the Cold War is is different
because a lot of the stuff that was made during the Cold War is still sitting around waiting to
destroy the world and that's that's part of what's going on with this Ticoi project is like I mean
yeah this is all like ancient history you know this this facility was built and operated before
I was born it's definitely built and operated before almost everyone watching this video was
born and and shut down before a lot of those viewers were born but unlike most of the boring
history stuff it's like yeah but the missile motors that pass through here are still sitting
in bunkers out in cornfields all over America just like waiting to go off and yeah it's it's
just weird and uncomfortable to think about yeah it's just uncomfortable to think about
that is the ending of the Ticoi video and a project that I felt like was was never going
to end in my life yeah some some projects they take a long time some projects they really feel
like they take a long time and for sure the the Ticoi project it felt like the long project that
was this one I feel like it just it took a little bit took a little bit too long for me to actually
bring it to the wraps Oh Oh Florence thank you so much bunkers I almost forgot okay I and and I
can't believe I almost forgot because this is the thing that I was the most obsessed about okay
bunkers bunkers bunkers how do I how do I even know how to begin with this okay so at some point
in researching this project I came across this incidental piece of information that like oh hey
all of these inspection sites right if you look at the inspection list you'll see there's a ton
of stuff in Utah it's like oh the UTTR is out there the the Dugway Proving Ground is out there
there's like a lot of military stuff out there and the United States as part of SALT and START
treaties invited the Soviet Union to come out and inspect them and it's like okay what are you
gonna do with these Soviet inspectors you got to put them somewhere and the Soviet Union built
housing that it's sent to the United States for their inspectors to live in because they were
paranoid about the US spying on their inspectors they were paranoid about the equipment being
messed with and apparently they were also paranoid enough that they had sanitize its electrical
separation between the power supply and the bunker where you're like smoothing out the electrical
signal like the Soviets did not do not trust the United States very much so I do not know why but
I became really obsessed with these bunkers because wherever I initially found out this
piece of information it was like this casual off-handed thing that said like oh by the way
these bunkers still exist I was like oh really that's interesting the bunkers still exist
somewhere and this is also where the global pandemic was incredibly frustrating because
if that had not been happening 100% I would have flown back to Utah to find these bunkers
so this project ended up having to be done entirely online and I cannot cannot give enough
credit to my assistant who just did did a herculean amount of work to track down where these
bunkers were and to to get the photographs that you're seeing now like phone calls over the course
of a year to many military installations and Utah research installations and like yeah just
a tremendous amount of work the number of human hours on this is unbelievable I don't know if I'm
gonna be able to find this just off the top of my head yes thank you guys for congratulating my
assistant here you know one of the things with patreon like obviously you're supporting me
writing and researching the videos and obviously you're supporting the animator and like the music
and everything else my assistant does a tremendous amount of additional work like helping these
things to happen and like the whole ticoi project getting in touch with the skull Valley reservation
and like getting permission to be on ticoi like that never would have happened without
her being able to take lead on that project and so like yes there's many things many things that
that happen because of her so okay so where are we here okay so this is Utah so you've got Salt
Lake City is over here skull Valley is over here we've got the giant desert so originally the
inspectors were all in magna Utah which is sort of right by West Valley City it's over here for
reasons that I cannot remember off the top of my head the bunkers after the Soviet Union collapsed
the Russian Federation was inspecting for a while and then the start treaty came to an end and the
bunkers were vacated and they ended up all the way on the other side of the Salt Lake Desert in
Wendover so Wendover is this little town that's right on the Utah Nevada border they were slash
are a Air Force Base kind of town the historic Wendover Airfield Museum is the place where it
was reported that these trailers ended up but I was determined to try to find out like for real
where are these things and if you now am I going to be able to do it just from memory okay here we
go boom okay so we went on a Google Street View and right outside the Historical Society in this
town you can see that there are a bunch of bunkers we eventually were able to get it confirmed that
yes this is where the bunkers that the Soviet inspectors used ended up and so there's I think
there's three or four of them that are in this this place and again through tremendous tremendous
effort we were able to get some photographs of the things so hold on let me pull this up okay so I
mentioned before like there was just nothing that existed that existed publicly about what did
t-coi look when it was being operated and it was a very similar situation for these Soviet trailers
like come on guys there's got to be pictures of this at the time and again what my assistant was
able to do with just an ungodly number of hours spent on the project was eventually tracked down
some boxes that were at the Utah State Archives and these boxes did not have date labels on them
they were like boxes of photographs from Magna Utah around this time like none of the photographs
are labeled they're not ordered there's no information on them but she was able to convince
one of the researchers there to scan some of the photographs for us that looked promising that they
might be bunker photos from the time and then we were able to by looking at the outsides confirm
like yes some of these are totally the Soviet bunkers these are the photographs from the inside
this is the one that I've used in the video but some of these photos are a little mysterious so
like this looks like it's the inside of one of the bunkers it was with the other bunker photos
it who knows like what's the deal where is this photograph taken is this is this when it was
constructed in in the Soviet Union is this in America like who knows there's just a bunch of
photos of like inspectors you can totally see like this is definitely out in Utah here's inspectors
investigating like a housing for one of the missiles guys hanging out like having a little
picnic it took forever to try to find these photos and this was like you know I don't know if you've
ever worked on a really long research project but we were so pumped when we finally were able to get
some of these photos and it's like excited all out of perspective with like what these images
actually are but to have been tracking them down for so long to actually get your hands on
something that was like in a box in an archive somewhere undated it was it was just it was just
incredible if I can get the other one so this is the other thing that I then really like so in
addition to tracking down like what were the archival images we were also able to get the
Wendover Historical Society to go inside these bunkers that had been like untouched on their
grounds in decades and just take some pictures from the inside of like what do these things
actually look like and so here is the state of the bunkers today and so you can see like this is
this is what's left inside there's the sign in Russian here is again like some of the old
equipment and the desks that they they sat at like again just equipment that's left inside
they're in really rough shape as you can see but like this is this is what's left of these bunkers
and here's what it looks like from the outside this is what from like a month ago I guess this
photograph and this this was really amazing because again if the pandemic had not been occurring I
would have flown to Wendover to try to like talk my way into these things but because that that
wasn't possible you know my my assistant was able to do the next best thing and like get the
Historical Society to take some photographs of what they look like I really really wanted to
work these into the video after so much effort trying to find them but here's the thing like
what is the video about the video is not about these trailers they're not really part of this
they're like an incidental part of the story it only loosely connects because they were in Magna
and Magna is also where the missiles were manufactured by Hercules and and so by the
time that I mentioned the bunkers we're already really at the end of the video and so to have a
little diversion about like oh these bunkers still exist today and here's some photos of
them like I just could not make it work in the actual video but I just really wanted to show
everyone who crowdfunds like look at these pictures we found isn't it amazing it was
incredibly exciting to find them and and so much so that I want to thank everyone who crowdfunds
the channel because what we're doing is we are donating to the Wendover Historical Society
to get one of these bunkers restored we are donating to them so that they can actually
turn one of these things into the best restoration of what it was at the time
that's possible perhaps someday when the global pandemic is over if you happen to find yourself
traveling through Wendover and you want to make a little diversion there will be a restored soviet
cold war inspection bunker related to the crazy ticoi project out there to see so thank you all
of the crowdfunders for making these sorts of videos possible and thank you for letting us
help try to restore something in the real world that's actually related to one of these projects
it's it's this one has been a real real journey guys so thank you so much that is the end of the
short director's commentary for the evening and stay safe and I'll see you in the next one
you