I'm usually rather scathing about climate bloggers, but someone sent me some links to
a number of blogs that convinced me they'd got at least one thing right. There was much
ballyhoo in the media a few years ago when two huge chunks of the Petermann Glacier in
Greenland broke away, and it led to concerns from scientists about an increase in the rate
of melting of Greenland's ice cap. And yet, as the bloggers rightly point out, the glacier
hasn't retreated, it's been advancing. Why can't scientists who study the glacier
see that too? We should all be very concerned about the
fact that our so-called free press and scientists in academia are aligned to us in such a bold
and obvious fashion. Well, that's a bit strong.
The corruption in climate academia is obviously very deep.
Hang on, before I start climbing on board with a conspiracy theory, I need to do a bit
more than just spend five minutes looking at blogs and photos.
The first thing that puzzled me was, since no one disputes the fact that two huge chunks
of ice came away from the Petermann Glacier, why didn't that make a dent in its position?
Why did it move forwards rather than backwards? So I looked more carefully at the timeline
and found more information and then I checked my watch. It had taken only another five minutes
to discover that all these very convincing blogs and videos are talking complete nonsense.
They all show photos of the ice advancing after 2012, which is true. But how come they
never show photos of what happened before 2012? And this is what it looks like. These
red lines mark the outlines of blocks of ice that broke away in 2010 and 2012. So let's
take a closer look at what the blogs aren't showing you.
The Petermann Glacier is in the far north of Greenland and one of the reasons it's
being studied is that it's been pretty stable for over 130 years, since it was first measured
in 1876 until the massive break-up of 2010. As the ice front advances at the rate of about
a kilometre a year, small icebergs are breaking off into the sea or carving, keeping the ice
front pretty much in equilibrium. This is what the ice front looked like in 1999 and
2004 and again in 2010. But around 2008 researchers noticed cracks
beginning to appear and in 2010 something unusual happened. A huge area of ice four
times the size of Manhattan broke away. It was a record. And sure enough the rupture
did cause the ice front to retreat. Then more cracks appeared further upstream
and in 2012 the same thing happened again. This time a double Manhattan sized chunk of
ice separated and again the ice front moved back. Researchers calculated that the break-ups
shortened the glacier in the fjord from 81 kilometres in length to 46 kilometres.
The advance between 2012 and 2019 hasn't even made up for the ice lost in the 2012
break-up, let alone the 2010 break-up. Now more cracks are appearing 12 kilometres even
further upstream, just like the cracks that heralded the 2010 and 2012 break-ups. Researchers
are expecting that another ice island may break away in the next few years. That would
take the ice front back even further. The next thing I checked was why the scientists
were claiming that the ice was not advancing after 2012 when it clearly was.
Good question. Is it really because they're paid to lie about the climate? No, again,
it turns out the bloggers got that wrong too. Firstly, when bloggers make a claim about
what someone said without providing a name or a quote, be sceptical. Experience has shown
me that it usually means they've made it up. I can't find a single instance of a
scientist making that claim and neither can the bloggers. On the contrary, scientists
have openly reported on the advance in the ice since 2012. NASA has posted images of
it online. The advance is mentioned and illustrated in scientific studies. You can even look it
up on Wikipedia. So if the bloggers think they've exposed a scurrilous secret that
scientists are trying to hide, I'm sorry to say that everyone else was way ahead of
you. And they certainly never claimed that the ice was retreating.
Then I noticed something in Tony Heller's video that showed where this idea might have
come from and it's a great insight into how these conspiracy theories get started. I'll
come back to that in a minute. First, it's important to look at why the
Petermann Glacier is behaving like this. After all, you don't see seven years of advance
like this in most of the world's glaciers. They're nearly all retreating.
So here's a bit of background. Outside of tectonic movement, glaciers advance and retreat
according to two main factors. One is the amount of snowfall they receive at the top
in what's called the accumulation zone. The other is the amount of ice that melts
at the bottom, called the ablation zone. The terminus of the glacier is called its foot.
When accumulation and ablation are in balance, the foot of the glacier neither advances or
retreats. In recent decades, the amount of snow accumulating
on glaciers has been outpaced by rapid melting. And the ablation zone has been moving higher
up again because of warmer air temperature. As a result, the feet of most glaciers have
been in constant retreat and certainly haven't been advancing since 2012.
So why is the Petermann Glacier behaving differently? Answer, because none of the photos in any
of the blogs actually show the foot of the Petermann Glacier.
I know, I was as shocked as you are. Turns out I didn't know as much about glaciers as
I thought. Greenland's glaciers aren't like the mountain
glaciers we're familiar with and the ones I've studied. They're continental glaciers,
an extension of the massive Greenland ice sheet. Basically they're an outflow of the
sheet itself. Unlike mountain glaciers, they're tapping into a huge reservoir of ice. And
unlike mountain glaciers that end on land, the Petermann Glacier extends far into the
sea. It continues in contact with bedrock for a short distance, but then it floats and
for most of its length it's an ice shelf known as the Petermann Tongue. So what we're seeing
in all these photos is the edge of the ice shelf, not the foot of the glacier.
This is important because the ice shelf isn't moving under its own weight due to gravity,
like a mountain glacier. What's causing it to move is the force of the descending land
ice behind it. And because the ice shelf is stuck between two rock faces on each side
of a fjord, it resists this movement. Effectively it acts like a break, holding back the outflow
of the ice sheet behind it. Anyone who's lived in a cold climate will
be familiar with the blockage that ice can cause inside a frozen pipe. It impedes the
flow of water. You have to warm the pipe to get the ice to break up and break away. As
chunks of ice come out, the blockage is cleared and the water flows faster.
So this isn't a difficult concept to grasp, and scientists say that's the danger of what's
happening on the Petermann ice shelf. If large chunks of this blockage continue to break
away, the ice will flow more freely and quickly out of the ice sheet, and that will accelerate
sea level rise. That's why scientists have been studying
the velocity of the Petermann glacier since the early 1990s, and that's a measure of how
much ice is flowing. And there was indeed an increase in velocity of the glacier after
the 2012 blockage was removed. We see the ice flowing more freely. In normal times it
takes one step forwards and one step backwards as icebergs carve into the sea. So the small
advance we've seen over the last seven years is not unusual. What's different now is that
it's taking one step forward and seven steps backwards.
There have been large break-offs before, around 1960 and 1991, but what scientists are concerned
about is the fact that the breaks are becoming larger and more frequent. Instead of being
decades apart, the last two were just two years apart, and another rift may already
be forming. And the 2010 break-up was much larger than anything that's been seen before.
The omission of all this crucial detail in the blogs can't be because of ignorance, because
even though the bloggers don't read scientific journals, even the newspapers they cite explain
it. This is from the independent story that Anthony Watts cited on his blog, but didn't
show. And Tony Heller shows the top of the Washington Post story, but cuts it off before
the crucial paragraph that also explains it all, and he replaces it with this tip. You'd
have to be a complete moron to believe anything the Washington Post writes about climate.
I'm no fan of the way the media reports science, as anyone familiar with my channel would know,
but this reference to the Washington Post brings me back to the false claim I showed
earlier. Where did Heller get the idea that scientists claimed the ice was retreating
after 2012?
Why are they claiming that the Petermann glacier has shrunk since the cabin event in 2012?
As I said, that's simply not true. Scientists say clearly that the ice advanced after 2012,
but I think I've figured out how Heller managed to make completely the opposite conclusion.
This is from his video.
So based on the Washington Post article, it would be safe to assume that the ice edge
has retreated since 2012.
But is it safe to assume the Washington Post says that? Well, that's very easy to check.
Let's read the Washington Post story and find out.
It turns out the Washington Post did not claim the ice had been retreating after 2012. In
fact, it had a graphic that clearly showed the advance since 2012, and it even gives
the speed of the advance about one kilometre a year. So the assumption that it said otherwise
is nonsense and could very easily have been checked. Therefore the assumption that a scientist
told the Washington Post this, which then becomes a pluralised fact fed to subscribers,
is completely made up.
Fortunately the people who follow these blogs are all sceptics. So when I read the comments
sections, I discovered that most of them had checked the newspaper stories for themselves
and discovered that the assumptions were wrong and uncovered the complete picture that the
bloggers didn't show. I'm kidding. Of course they didn't do that. They're not the least
bit sceptical. They didn't bother checking any of this. Of course they blindly believe
whatever the bloggers tell them. We're living in an internet world plagued by conspiracy
theories.
Why is it up to me to go do five minutes of research on the NASA website to find out what
a big lie this whole story was?
Well maybe you shouldn't just spend five minutes looking at some photos and decide that you
know more about this than the oceanographers and glaciologists who spend half the year
on the ice shelf studying it. Maybe you should spend more than five minutes on this and read
some of the material you're citing and find out what scientists actually said, rather
than jumping to the conclusion that they must be lying because you assume the only source
you cite says something it doesn't.
That goes for all the bloggers who misrepresented these facts. No one is forcing you to sit
comfortably at home, look at a few photos, misrepresent the science and ask for donations.
After all, it was only after I'd spent five minutes looking at the photos and agreed that
the ice was advancing that I discovered what happened before 2012 and that scientists didn't
lie and claim the ice was retreating after 2012. And after more hours studying the research
material I learned how the velocity of the glacier increased after the 2012 carving and
why that happened and why it's important. And I learned that 80% of the melting is coming
from warmer water underneath the glacier and that recent measurements show the temperature
of that water is increasing. I'm not going to pretend that a few days studying this makes
me any kind of authority, but I do know a lot more than I did when I started out, reading
the blogs and looking at a few photos. There's still a huge amount of information I can't
squeeze into a 16 minute video, and there's still a lot the researchers don't know. That's
why they're not saying that the ice breaks are a sure sign of global warming, contrary
to what the bloggers claim, but they are saying that they're concerned and they explain why.
Maybe we should listen to those concerns and understand the science behind them instead
of believing blogs that deliberately hide the evidence and make up fabricated claims.
So please fact check anything in this video that you're sceptical about. Unlike the bloggers,
I cite all my sources in the video description, so it's easy for you to check. To the conspiracy
theorists out there, if you have to misquote me to find a mistake, or if you can't do any
better than criticise my voice, my attitude or my personality, thanks. I'll take that
as a sign that you've fact checked my video and can't find a single error. But if you
do find a mistake, then of course I'll be happy to issue a correction, as I always do.
I wonder if we'll see the bloggers do the same thing.
Unlike these blogs, my channel isn't monetised and I don't ask for donations, so I've suggested
that if you want to give money to support this channel, please give it to a worthy charity
which is detailed at the top of the video description.
And just to set the record straight for a few people who made assumptions about this
charity and didn't bother to check their facts before posting, ironic given the theme of
this video, this is not a reforestation project and it hasn't been imposed on local people.
It was instigated at their request. The charity has successfully stopped most of the illegal
logging in a national park in Borneo by offering free community medical healthcare in return
for a commitment not to cut down trees, since the main reason people were logging in the
national park was to get money when family members were sick. Payment to the hospital
is made in the form of saplings, which are planted in open spaces of the forest that
had previously been logged. Camera traps show that wildlife is now returning to these areas.
And money from carbon credits for this reforestation pays the salaries of doctors and nurses.
The people get proper healthcare and the forest is being conserved and even restored.
So reforestation is only one element of this model, which thanks to your donations is now
being trialled in Madagascar and Brazil. I'm not connected to the charity, I just did a
story on the project several years ago and was hugely impressed. So when people started
asking if they could donate to my channel, I told them to donate here instead. And thanks
to all of those who did.