Hello internet. I'm here to talk about an experiment on the channel.
There's a problem on YouTube. See, down in the comments
there are so many scam bots and sex bots and sex bots and scam bots.
I don't know what the deal is. It's been a problem for years
that multiple creators have complained about, and it's only getting worse.
Soon I expect much worse, and I really don't want these videos
to be a place where scammers can scam.
So I'm experimenting with a solution in the form of a new privilege for Bonnie B's.
As the verified humans that you are actually making these videos happen,
you alone will be able to post in the comments below.
The official video discussion, which happens over at the Reddit, is unchanged.
They don't have this problem as much.
So if you are a student and thus banned from Patreon, I'll see you over there.
It's where I spend most of my comment time anyway.
Back to YouTube. There is unfortunately no automated way
to do what I'm trying to accomplish, so every one of you that signs up
will have to be individually approved by myself or my team,
which is an admin nightmare, so please be patient while we work this out.
It's not ideal, but right now it's the best solution
while also raising the visibility in the comments of everyone
who helps make these videos happen.
And it's an incentive I'm also happy to add with YouTube's ceaseless promotion
of shorts over regular videos, which is having a real impact
on normal long form creators like myself.
So if you've been watching the channel for years
and if you've been considering signing up
but have never really quite gotten around to it,
and if and only if you are in a financially stable place,
perhaps this benefit is the thing that will finally push you over the edge.
And click here to sign up.
If it does, thank you from me and from my team
for allowing us to spend an unreasonable amount of time
working on animated explainers for the internet.
It's an honor.