At its height, the Roman Empire was home to about 30% of the world's population, and,
in many ways, it was the pinnacle of human advancement. Its citizens enjoyed the benefits
of central heating, concrete, double glazing, banking, international trade, and upward social
mobility. Rome became the first city in history with 1 million inhabitants, and was a center
of technological, legal, and economic progress. An empire impossible to topple, stable and
rich and powerful. Until it wasn't anymore. First slowly, then suddenly, the most powerful
civilization on earth collapsed. By civilization, we mean a complex society where labor is specialized
and social classes emerge and which is ruled by institutions. Civilizations share a dominant
mutual language and culture, and domesticate plants and animals to feed and sustain large
cities, where they often construct impressive monuments. Civilization lets us become efficient
on large scales, collect vast amounts of knowledge, and put human ingenuity and the natural resources
of the world to work. Without civilization, most people would never have been born. Which
makes it a bit concerning that collapse is the rule, not the exception. Virtually all
civilizations end, on average, after 340 years. Collapse is rarely nice for individuals. Their
shared cultural identity is shattered as institutions lose the power to organize people. Knowledge
is lost, living standards fall, violence increases, and often the population declines. The civilization
either completely disappears, is absorbed by stronger neighbors, or something new emerges,
sometimes with more primitive technology than before. If this is how it's been over the ages,
what about us today? Just as Europeans forgot how to build indoor plumbing and make cement,
will we lose our industrial technology, and with that our greatest achievements,
from $1 pizza to smartphones or laser eye surgery? Will all this go away too? Today,
our cities stretch for thousands of square kilometers. We travel the skies. Our communication
is instant. Industrial agriculture with engineered high-yield plants, efficient machinery, and high
potency fertilizer feeds billions of people. Modern medicine gives us the longest lifespan
we've ever had, while industrial technology gives us an unprecedented level of comfort and abundance,
even though we haven't yet learned to attain them without destroying our ecosphere. There
are arguably still different civilizations around today that compete and coexist with each other,
but together they also form a singular global civilization. But this modern
globalized civilization is even more vulnerable in some ways than past empires because we are
much more deeply interconnected. A collapse of the industrialized world literally means that
the majority of people alive today would perish since without industrial agriculture we would no
longer be able to feed them. And there's an even greater risk. What if a collapse was so deeply
destructive that we were unable to reindustrialize again? What if it ruined our chances of enjoying
a flourishing future as a multiplanetary species? A global civilizational collapse could be an
existential catastrophe, something that ruins not just the lives of everyone alive today,
but all the future generations that could have come into being. All the knowledge we might have
discovered, the art we might have created, the joys we might have experienced, would be lost.
So how likely is all of this? Let's start with some good news. While civilization collapses have
happened regularly, none have ever derailed the course of global civilization. Rome collapsed,
but the Aksumite Empire, or the Teotihuans, and of course the Byzantine Empire, carried on. What
about sudden population crashes? So far, we've not seen a catastrophe that has killed much more
than 10% of the global population. No pandemic, no natural disaster, no war. The last clear example
of a rapid global population decrease was the Black Death, a pandemic of the bubonic plague in
the 14th century that spread across the Middle East and Europe and killed a third of all Europeans
and about one-tenth of the global population. If any event was going to cause the collapse of
civilization, that should have been it. But even the Black Death demonstrates humanity's resilience
more than its fragility. While the old societies were massively disrupted in the short term,
the intense loss of human lives and suffering did little to negatively impact European economic
and technological development in the long run. Population size recovered within two centuries,
and just two centuries later, the Industrial Revolution began. History is full of incredible
recoveries from horrible tragedies. Take the atomic bombing of Hiroshima during World War Two.
140,000 people were killed and 90% of the city was at least partially incinerated or reduced
to rubble. But against all odds, they made a remarkable recovery. Hiroshima's population
recovered within a decade, and today, it's a thriving city of 1.2 million people. None of
this made these horrible events any less horrible for those who lived through them. But for us as a
species, these signs of resilience are good news. Why recovery is likely even in the worst case.
One thing that's different from historic collapses is that humanity now has unprecedented destructive
power. Today's nuclear arsenals are so powerful that all-out global war could cause a nuclear
winter and billions of deaths. Our knowledge of our own biology and how to manipulate it
is getting so advanced that it's becoming possible to engineer viruses as contagious
as the coronavirus and as deadly as Ebola. Increasingly, the risk of global pandemics
is much higher than in the past. So we may cause a collapse ourselves, and it might be much worse
than the things nature has thrown at us so far. But if say 99% of the population died,
would global civilization collapse forever? Could we recover from such a tragedy? We have
some reasons to be optimistic. Let's start with food. There are 1 billion agricultural workers
today, so even if the global population fell to just 80 million, it's virtually guaranteed
that many survivors would know how to produce food. And we don't need to start at square one,
because we could still use modern high-yield crops. Maize is 10 times bigger than its wild
ancestor. Ancient tomatoes were the size of today's peas. After agriculture, the next step
towards recovery would be rebuilding industrial capacity like power grids and automated
manufacturing. A huge problem is that our economies of scale make it impossible to just pick up where
we left off. Many of our high-tech industries are only functional because of huge demand and
intensely interconnected supply chains across different continents. Even if our infrastructure
were left unharmed, we would make huge steps backwards technologically. But then again,
we are thinking in larger time frames. Industrialization originally happened 12,000
years after the agricultural revolution. So if we need to start over after a massive collapse,
it shouldn't be that hard to reindustrialize, at least on evolutionary time scales. There's
a hitch though. The industrial revolution was fueled literally by burning easily accessible
coal, and we are still very much reliant on it. If we use it all up today, aside from making rapid
climate change much worse, we could hinder our ability to recover from a huge crisis. So we
should stop using easy-to-access coal, so it can serve as a civilization insurance in case
something bad happens. Another thing that makes recovery likely is that we probably have most of
the information we need to rebuild civilization. We would certainly lose a lot of crucial
institutional knowledge, especially on hard drives that nobody could read or operate anymore. But a
lot of the technological, scientific, and cultural knowledge stored in the world's 2.6 million
libraries would survive the catastrophe. The post-collapse survivors would know what used
to be possible, and they could reverse engineer some of the tools and machines they'd find.
In conclusion, despite the bleak prospect of catastrophic threats, natural or created by
ourselves, there is reason for optimism. Humankind is remarkably resilient, and even in the case of
a global civilizational collapse, it seems likely that we would be able to recover. Even if many
people were to perish or suffer immense hardship. Even if we lost cultural and technological
achievements in the process. But given the stakes, the risks are still unnervingly high.
Nuclear war and dangerous pandemics threaten the amazing global civilization we have built.
Humanity is like a teenager, speeding around blind corners, drunk without a seatbelt. The
good news is that it's still early enough to prepare for and to mitigate these risks. We just
need to actually do it. We made this video together with Will MacAskill, a professor of
philosophy at Oxford and one of the founders of the effective altruism movement, which is about
doing the most good you can with your time and money. Will just published a new book called
What We Owe the Future, which is about how you can positively impact the long-term future of our
world. If you like Kurzgesagt videos, the chances are high you'll like it. The book has some pretty
counterintuitive arguments, like that risks from new technologies such as AI and synthetic biology
are at least as grave as those from climate change. Or that the world doesn't contain too
many people, but too few. And especially that everyday actions like recycling or refusing to
fly just aren't that big a deal compared to where you donate or what career you pursue. Most
importantly, it argues that by acting wisely, you can help make tomorrow better than today. And how
we together can build a flourishing world for the thousands or millions of generations that will
come after us. Many things we at Kurzgesagt talk about regularly are discussed here in much greater
detail. Check out What We Owe the Future wherever you get your books or audio books. Did we manage
to unlock a new fear for you? Let's counter existential dread with appreciation for
humanity. Look how far we've come as a species, what we've built and where we've gathered. Let
this new world map poster be a reminder of what we can achieve.