You can also go for the treasure chest and stuff.
Treasure chest is worth more than the bag, which is worth more than the single.
Nope, nope, nope, nope.
Back off!
What the fuck is that?
Why would it do that?
What, did it only get one go?
I think I was wiggling pretty good.
But it doesn't, it didn't say anything about me only getting to go once.
Are those results?
This is bullshit.
Fuck this game.
You only have 48 turns to go.
Oh god.
Okay.
Oh, so Mario, wait, oh so now you might, oh but you don't have enough coins, and he lands
on Bowser?
Yeah!
Wait, I'm going to turn you into a fan of this game.
I thought that was the last space.
No, you've got to go past it, so you're going to get screwed and then you might have to,
either way it's bad after that because you don't have enough coins.
No, I want to get there without enough coins.
Because fuck that.
Oh, you're just going to watch the world burn.
I mean, if I can't get it, that's what I want to have happen, because that'll rotate it
to Bowser, right?
You have literally nothing.
Good, I don't fucking need it, man.
Rock bottom.
Okay, I'm using pretty good at this, let me see.
Who do I want to steal from?
Um, are you in second, Drew?
I think so.
Okay.
I want to be here, so I'm at your Yoshi.
And I want to receive money, oh this is tough, okay.
What?
Okay, star.
Okay.
I'll take it from whoever.
Not Mario.
Damn it, he has no money, yeah!
Oh, my coins go to you, here have my 20 coins.
You broke son of a bitch.
Here comes Mario, totally fucking destitute.
He woke him up from a park bench, stole the newspaper he was using to sleep, and then
said this is worth 20 coins.
Damn it.
My own fucking brother.
Trying to rob my homeless brother.
Queen game, all right.
All right, here we go.
Oh, now you're only two coins short.
So you just got a bunch of money just to lose it immediately?
Probably.
Oh, you're going to get a star anyway, Jeff, look.
He's going to give me one, he's nice.
Oh wait, you don't have enough.
All right, see ya.
That rotates back to Toad, who has nothing to say.
He just dropped you off a cloud.
Sorry, dude.
Yeah, you should have thought about this shit a little more, I guess, I don't know.
Hey, Jeff, get back to the start.
You could have like not even shown up and then like walked in right now.
That's true.
Yeah.
And your hand would feel better.
Yeah, that would be it.
Oh, cool.
Great.
I'm having a great time.
This is a real fun part of you guys.
Star!
Mario.
Oh, I thought it was auto-run.
No, I'm still in it.
God damn it.
Fuck.
Damn it, Mario.
What the fuck happened?
I pushed A, it didn't jump.
You got a coin.
Motherfucker.
I guess I need to roll big and get up there right now.
Yeah.
Wait.
Whoa.
Where did that come from?
I think you got a random warp block, which is probably going to turn into spaces.
Hey, Mario Party, am I right?
I forgot in this one that just happens randomly.
Fuck all video games forever.
And it just picked me randomly to swap with?
Yeah.
So, jump across the top, remember where you land, the tower's tilted in a different direction,
move the jump, once the tower teeters over, jump with all you got, then you make it to
the next tower, and to what end?
Just get to the end and get a bunch of coins on the way.
The instructions could say there's an end.
Look at this artsy shit.
Look at that Donkey Kong Country stuff.
Basically like Limbo.
Oh.
Wow.
See, it starts you out.
See, the first one before he jumps out there, I was holding up the whole time, which made
me think that you couldn't run off the edge because it was holding me up.
Like, I appreciate that.
It's just unfortunate that it had to be in this context.
How the fuck do you grab the eyeballs?
You don't.
Oh, you're right.
The cheeks will do it.
Mine has always looked exactly like the fucking picture, and I get like a 72.
Fuck you, you motherfucker!
That's right.
Who are you?
99.
My goodness.
I'm a regular face-stretching artiste over here.
You're doing alright, Mario.
You gotta start.
You gotta start, Mario.
It's okay.
It's not okay.
It would have been kind of funny.
I feel pretty good about what I got going on here.
Oh, I fucked up.
Which one were you?
Fuck this!
Mario, you just lost 30 coins.
Like sunlight hitting a lily.
I just want to know.
That's what you want.
Oh!
Hey!
What do you know?
Oh!
Even when things go my way, they don't go my way.
Wait.
Oh!
I just got that.
Oh, no.
Welcome to my world.
Fuck all coins.
Who needs them?
Hey, if it's who needs them, don't do anything.
That's a good point.
Yeah, I just won't do anything.
Yeah, huh.
Talk the talk.
Yeah.
No, I'm getting these so I can lose them again later.
Okay.
Money.
Fuck.
God damn it.
Shit.
Fuck.
Who's up there?
Is that?
Fuck.
Oh.
That's why you were saying fuck a lot.
Can you burn me a CD?
I threw them at the party.
I'm gonna entertain myself somehow.
I had 38 points.
We had like video game play or something.
I had 38 coins.
I've got zero stars.
I mean, they just didn't maintain security on achievements.
It was too easy to hack them so they could never do anything good with them.
Yeah.
Mine's the best.
Are you looking at mine?
Yeah.
Fuck you.
Mine was seven better than yours.
Why?
How was that?
Did you see it?
Hey, you know what?
We all won though so there.
Wait, who got the highest score?
Me.
But we're all having a good time.
Oh yeah.
No.
It's the most fun I've had in ages.
We all profited.
So none of us profited then.
Here's ten coins to everyone.
You could win them in the next thing.
Very true.
It's me.
I'm pretty sure it's me.
Yeah, now that the star has been collected, what will happen on this board?
Oh, it's stupid.
Stop moving.
Is that not it?
Is that it?
That's it, isn't it?
What?
God damn it.
Oh, I was looking at yours and then.
Oh, Yoshi.
Damn it.
Well, you have one that's wrong.
No, no, you do it twice.
If it's like, there's three.
No, I was building the picture.
I think that may have been a colorblind map.
Oh, really?
Yeah, maybe like one of the corner pieces that didn't have any characters on it.
Yeah, your top right one was blue.
Oh, okay.
Huh.
That's really interesting.
Fuck this game.
It's racist.
It might have a colorblind mode.
Fucking kidding me.
How do you climb?
Hey, tap A.
Okay.
Boy, they don't give you any quarter.
No, that's how Drew died immediately last time.
Oh.
Oh, shit.
No.
Fuck this game.
I got it.
Don't tell me I got robbed there.
Yeah.
Wait, what?
What do I have wrong?
Which one did I?
Top right again.
Top right, really?
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, it's red.
It had a little hooky corner on it that looked...
Yeah, the color.
Man.
Man, that's crazy.
I want an instant replay of that because I thought I hit it.
I think that this game needs the ability to turn off certain minigames and I'm offended?
This is pretty cool.
Well, good.
You have three more coins than me.
Yeah, that makes me feel better.
That's a good point.
Oh, wait.
I'll get another shot at it.
It'll be fine.
We'll roll this again.
I have more time to get the coins.
You can get more coins?
That was a good thing.
That was a blessing.
Yeah, that's what we call it.
A blessing.
For everything in Mario Karting.
Blessings or blessings in disguise.
I'm getting stuffed now.
Oh, and then a blooper comes and takes you off the stage.
Mario win this.
Don't let Mario get more.
Is that a draw?
No.
Hey, Dan, you care to make a friendly wager?
What's that, Brad?
I don't know.
I'm just gauging your interest before I lay any terms down.
On the outcome, the winner of this?
Sure.
Is the wager...
What turn number is this?
Let's see.
16.
God!
Here we go.
Yoshi, take it.
Yeah, he got in the way.
Yeah, blocking him.
I think we won.
Don't you worry.
I think there's too much overlap between Birdo and Yoshi.
Not a whole lot.
Birdo is cool and Yoshi sucks.
Birdo is a dinosaur that looks kind of like Yoshi, right?
I mean...
The mouth thing is totally different.
Look at the mouth and nose.
They're clearly different.
I guess that's true.
I think all Yoshi's are females.
It's only eggs.
I thought it was the other.
Well, so does Birdo.
I don't know.
Birdo is in the ladies bathroom in the new Mario Golf Toadstool Tour.
Or the Game Boy one.
Is that cannon?
Yeah, I think so.
We're all doing real good, guys.
Oh, come on.
I pressed the button.
Nothing happened.
That's what happened.
Oh, boy.
Oh, my God!
This is getting rough.
Oh, my God.
I need this to end quick.
This is just 50 jumps.
Oh, my God.
How are we doing this?
But...
Oh!
This really needs to end.
But...
Okay.
This is unprecedented.
I hit it!
Nothing!
You hit nothing!
Oh, man.
Wow, this leaderboard is flip-flopped.
Anything can happen in this piece of garbage masquerading as a video game.
Too true.
Don't fucking be a star.
Oh, my God!
See?
Yes.
Do you see?
Oh, my God.
Do you see what I've been saying this whole time?
This game sucks.
No. What? No. What?
Did he just unrest the dead?
Get the fuck away from my coins.
These are my coins.
This is all I have.
He didn't star.
We shouldn't be grave robbing.
21 coins.
Throw it opposite a grave robbing.
Total BS.
Came out of the grave and robbed you.
That's hot crap.
Still not exactly clear what this does, but whatever.
Game & Watch is worse than 64.
Wait, what?
You're moving the fucking star.
I thought that was the one that...
It was right when Jeff was almost...
Wait, I thought you went the other way around the star.
He was working his way back.
Fuck.
Jesus Christ.
He was really good at basketball, it turns out.
Come on!
Let me just...
Don't...
Yes!
Press the button.
Advance the game.
This game's fucking great.
Oh, another game here.
Oh, no, it's the honesty thing.
I didn't want the other two, so it doesn't matter.
That's harsh.
What a dick.
That's pretty good.
Watoed?
Toad doesn't give a shit about honesty.
Integrity.
Seems to be the case.
Toad's a fucking snake.
No.
Aw, so close.
Oh, and then you gotta play a game by yourself.
Oh.
Coins sucked out of you by the bank.
Who knows?
Jeff, this is it.
Why?
Who cares?
I get a big enough roll and I use my...
Use the item.
20.
What is your item?
Roll 20.
You can use your mushroom.
In fact, you definitely should.
Make use of that.
The new key's got to hang out with you for a while.
Oh, but I got 10 coins out of it, so that's cool.
Oh.
What's happening?
He's got a little wahoo.
He's like, finally.
Satan has come to take me away.
What kind of dash LEDs can you do today?
I'm a genius.
I'll just rub.
That is genius.
Man, who?
I never thought of just a straight jack move.
No, because we have forward controls too, so we probably both have two wars.
We probably just need to cooperate to steer.
You do A, I'll do B.
We'll figure it out as we go.
So A and B at the same time just go forward.
It's fucking silo-y.
Who's on, Jeff?
I am, but I'm hitting A and B.
We're on the right.
And nothing's happening?
And nothing's happening.
B has to go left.
B has to go right.
So yeah, let's do both.
Nothing's happening.
Well, we're fucked.
A and B at the same time.
No, nothing's happening.
I can't do anything.
These buttons are not working.
Man, what a great game.
Can someone unplug my controller?
You gotta kick that.
Uh-oh.
Gotta explain it.
Game of skill.
Fucking game of cheating, more like.
Uh, I don't wanna spoil it.
Is that where you wanted to go?
Oh, did someone already get that other star?
Oh, you're right.
I wanted.
Yeah, well.
Well, whatever.
There was nothing I could do.
I rolled the dice and then I went there.
Oh, god damn it.
I had no choice in the matter.
Making a fatal mistake.
There was no skill that could be used to.
Oh, okay.
Fucking.
Fuck.
You alright?
I thought that was a pretty good roll.
I was a little confused there.
This infinite death trap.
You're rubbing.
I'm up there again.
That's about right.
If you're just joining us, this is Mario Party 4 for the Nintendo GameCube.
Oh, shit.
Anybody.
My fate in the hands of the universe.
It's all fair.
It's war with the battlefield.
Still got some coins.
Ooh.
Again?
Oh, no.
Holy shit.
Is it gone?
Dude.
What triggers that?
It's the question marks.
Any of them?
No, just the question mark green space.
The one, so you landed on the spot right before the start?
Yeah.
Uh-huh.
Man, that's incredible.
Fuck all video games forever.
Fucking what a piece of shit.
God.
Build a time machine, go back in time, find the first pong machine, smash it with a fucking
sledgehammer.
I know it's a little late to start, but I feel like we should end all of these by destroying
the game at the end.
So nobody could ever be cursed with it again.
Take up a spot in your fucking inventory.
It's huge.
It's a huge tent.
Is this star still over here?
I don't even remember.
Yeah.
Whoa.
Okay.
Oh, wait.
My god, man.
Well, fuck everything.
Oh, no.
Oh.
Hey.
Hey,linger anytime anything opens?
Oh yeah.
Come on.
Come on guys.
BOOM.
Come on.
Always the best house.
Yeah.
I'm looking forward to it.
Okay.
Uh.
Adds one dice block.
That might actually be.
That'd be cool.
Wait.
Are you close to the thing?
Save that.
Yeah.
You should save that.
Oh wait.
Yeah.
Do it.
You feeling lucky?
I'm gonna use.
I'm gonna.
I'm gonna do that.
Yes.
Let's do that.
Okay.
Double ones.
Here we go.
Jeff.
I'm rooting for you.
I know.
Yeah.
I just want somebody to get it.
Okay.
Oh.
You're gonna lose.
No.
He's not.
Aw.
Yeah.
Best Mario boss.
Best Mario party.
Where?
You just go here anyway.
You end up here anyway.
I go to the exact same fucking space.
No matter what I fucking pick.
If you go right.
You don't have to see the animation.
This will be faster.
Cause we don't have to watch the dumb animation of this stupid fucking cannon.
This piece of shit.
Fuck everything.
That seems way too powerful.
This game of skill.
Shit.
So this is like chance time.
Okay.
Oh.
Yeah.
Totally chance time.
Okay.
Fuck.
Oh my god.
Wait.
Is that even bad for you?
Oh wait.
Oh shit.
This could be like ten fucking coins.
Fuck.
Oh.
I'm sorry Jeff.
It's fine.
I didn't want it to be like this.
No it's fine.
No.
I don't even have them at rolling.
Where's the star?
Good.
Three coins.
Enjoy.
Enjoy those three fucking coins if you land on the back of the end.
You could have had like a real nice lunch and then like come in an hour later and just
like join our game and be right in the same spot.
Alright.
What will happen?
Who else it will happen to?
It always calls you.
Okay.
Oh.
Aw shit.
Stars.
Aw.
Scale.
Burn it all down.
Man.
Strong turn.
I'm playing turn one over here.
Let's go.
Why?
So there is a chance that you get all of my stars.
Yeah.
Okay.
Just wanted to make sure that was on the line here.
That's really bullshit.
Yeah.
That's bullshit.
It's the game man.
Aw.
The rich get riches.
Oooh.
Just rotate the lever.
Just fucking do a thing.
That was hard.
I swear this fucking game.
Wait.
What do we do?
Did I say pull a rope?
I didn't complete random.
What do we do?
Pull a random rope and something fucking dumb happens.
Okay.
What?
Just pick a rope.
You got to pull a rope Brad.
You have to pull a rope.
How do I pull a rope?
Let's go up and hit A.
I'm hitting A.
You got a rope.
You picked one.
You hit A already.
Oh okay.
You hit that rope.
Ha ha ha ha.
Woo.
Yeah.
Okay.
Cool.
How many more Mario parties are there?