So, April 27, 2017 was the greatest day in the history of twitter.com.net.gov.
I realize that to you children, Twitter is an app, but to us MILFs, it remains a website.
We have to dial in.
Hello operator, connect me to hell.
This was the day that Fyre Festival, a luxury music event hosted by Ja Rule and some charlatan,
was scheduled to begin on a private island in the Bahamas.
There was a lot of hype, Kendall Jenner and Bella Hadid endorsed the festival on Instagram,
there was a promo video full of supermodels, tickets were selling for thousands of dollars.
One twitter thread summarized the marketing as exclusivity, conspicuous consumption,
and many, many promises of excellent selfies for your already insufferable Instagram.
So when the day arrived, and the advertised best in food, art, music, and adventure turned
out to be two slices of pallid American cheese languishing over sliced bread in an atmosphere
that can only be described as muddy third world shantytown, I mean if you weren't
on Twitter that day, I don't think you can even imagine the revelry.
Just learned about Fyre Festival, aka Ja Rule's concentration camp for Instagram models and
rich white kids.
Yuppie hunger games hosted by Ja Rule.
Finish your food, there's starving millennial influencers in Fyre Festival.
Instagram entitled rich kids, meet Lord of the Flies.
Let them eat salad.
It was a shuddering climax of pent-up class rage.
You know, maybe millennials couldn't get Bernie Sanders elected, but at least those
sandwiches were garbage.
Jamila Jamil is an English actress who's just extremely pretty.
Imagine looking like this.
Imagine being perfect.
Why are you doing this to me, Jamila?
Why are you doing this to women?
One day on Instagram, an ordinary peasant told the queen Jamila,
Your skin is so perfect, uwu.
And Jamila replied,
My skin is currently clear because A. Privileged people have more access to good
quality nutrition and also our lives are significantly less stressful than those with less privilege.
I also get to sleep more because of this.
All of these things keep my hormones in balance and I'm able to address food intolerances
easily.
B. I believe that trans rights are human rights.
C. I exfoliate twice a week.
Oh boy.
Jamila, they're gonna cut your head off, gorge.
I'll protect you, queen.
Could she be any more annoying?
Someone wandered on Twitter to 77,000 likes.
This trend of fake self-awareness legit makes me want to rip my hair out.
Now look, to be fair, everything Jamila said is true.
Being privileged does make it easier to spend time and money on cosmetics.
But Jamila's acknowledging this, this recitation of all the complex socioeconomic factors that
account for why she's prettier than you, doesn't take any of the sting out of inequality,
does it?
And that's kind of at odds with what activists used to say, which is that you should check
your privilege.
A suggestion which the privileged seem to have taken to heart, since the rich and famous
now go around delivering these orations on how fortunate they are compared to the rabble.
And this of course turns out to be far more annoying than when they acted oblivious to it.
I don't have any beauty secrets, I guess I just drink lots of water.
Take me, mother.
A similar scandal occurred when Kim Kardashian tweeted about her birthday party at the height
of the coronavirus pandemic.
40 and feeling so humbled and blessed.
There is not a single day that I take for granted, especially during these times when
we are all reminded of the things that truly matter.
After two weeks of multiple health screens and asking everyone to quarantine, I surprised
my closest inner circle with a trip to a private island where we could pretend things were
normal for just a brief moment in time.
I realize that for most people, this is something that is so far out of reach right now, so
in moments like these, I'm humbly reminded of how privileged my life is.
Hashtag thisis40, tag me bitch.
So like Jamila, Kim is attempting some kind of privilege-checking maneuver, and once again,
it has not gone well.
You are the Marie Antoinette of the 21st century, bragging about being humble and letting us
eat cake.
Millions of Americans sick and suffering, standing for hours in food lines and being
evicted as you flaunt your wealth and privilege?
Your tweet made ten times worse by hashtag tone-deaf humbled and blessed line, hashtag
gross.
Happy birthday, mmm.
I hope somebody got you an alphabet book as a gift so you can read the motherfucking-
So the response on Twitter resembles moral outrage, but what people were upset about
was not that she had the party, I mean, wouldn't you escape to a private island if you got
that milf money?
The problem was more that she tweeted about it, and that the tweet was maybe, just maybe,
a little bit yikesy.
But if having the party wasn't wrong, then why was tweeting about it wrong?
This isn't a good look, we say.
Bad optics.
Not relatable.
Relatable.
Relatability is not a moral category.
This is public relations, it's not ethics, and it definitely isn't socialism.
Like I'm pretty sure Karl Marx never said,
The problem with the bourgeoisie is they are not relatable.
They can't read the room and it isn't a good look.
This should have stayed in the drafts.
Hashtag tone-deaf.
Isn't the issue that, when Kim tweeted this, most people were trapped in quarantine?
We didn't get to have birthday parties, some people couldn't even travel to visit
their dying relatives.
So watching Kim get to travel and celebrate her birthday like normal was painful.
Pain at the good fortune of others is how Aristotle defined envy.
And I think it's interesting that whenever social media erupts in outrage over luxury
music festivals, or Kim K's birthday party, or Jameela Jameel's privileged pores,
no one ever uses the word envy.
It's like we're averting our eyes, avoiding confrontation with this dark aspect of our
own psychology.
So in this video, I want to take a long hard look at envy.
What is it, where does it come from, and seriously, what is Jameela Jameel's skincare routine?
Drop it in the comments, bestie.
Okay, so what is envy?
Pain at the good fortune of others is not a bad start, but there's more to it than that.
Envy is a syndrome, a complex of poisonous thoughts and feelings about people who have
what we want, but cannot get.
It's not simply wanting what another person has, that's greed, which is a much more
wholesome sin.
Because simply wanting what someone has can inspire us, it can fuel our own ambition,
it can even motivate us to improve ourselves.
And sometimes people call that envy, but it's not really envy, it's emulation or admiration.
At worst, it's what the Bible calls coveting.
It covets.
Envy is something darker, it's not just wanting what someone has, it's begrudging them what
they have.
You might even hate the person you envy, and want them to lose what they have, to be humiliated
and destroyed, even if their downfall doesn't benefit you in any way.
Like Satan, who was willing to lose heaven just to spite God, according to the poet John Milfton.
It's gonna be 90 minutes of Milf jokes, kids, so strap in.
So envy is malicious, it's a force of destruction.
For an example of the distinction between envy and emulation, think about incels, involuntary
celibates, these men who can't get girlfriends and are bitter about it online.
It was incels who contributed to our culture the concept of chads, that is beautiful, wealthy,
masculine men.
For incels, taking the red pill means buying into an ideology which says that women only
want to date chads, or else they want to marry beta cucks just to take their beta bucks.
Gas keep, gate boss, girl light.
So if you're an incel, you can either go to the gym and try to become a chad, that's emulation,
the aspiration to attain what another person has, or, and this is the more popular option,
you can take the black pill.
Which means believing that chadhood is genetically determined at birth, there is no hope, no
woman will ever want you, and therefore happiness is impossible, you may as well lie down and rot.
This mindset of resentment has inspired so many mass murders, there's an entire wikipedia
timeline dedicated to tracking them.
And the essential motivation for this violence is envy.
The incel's failed ambition and sense of incurable predestined inferiority turns venomous.
The logic behind the violence is, if I can't get a girlfriend, if I can't get what I want,
then no one can.
In the words of a murderer,
The day of retribution is my attempt to destroy everything I cannot have.
But most incels aren't murderers.
Most of the time, envy is most harmful to the person who envies.
The philosopher Max Scheler called it a self-poisoning of the mind.
There's a Christian saying that envy is the only sin that gives no pleasure.
Because the other sins are fun, right?
Greed, gluttony, lust?
That's what I call a good time.
But envy is misery.
Though I wouldn't go so far as to say it gives no pleasure.
Fire Festival is an art installation where mediocre people realize what their lives would
be like without rich parents.
Yes.
Rich refugee crisis.
We're living in a moment of growing inequality and resentment.
Look around you.
We've got the guillotine memes.
We've got edgy teens tweeting eat the rich.
And none of this is new.
The slogan eat the rich actually originates with the philosopher of the French Revolution,
Jaja Gabor, who supposedly said,
When the people have no more to eat, they will eat the rich.
And fair enough, it's a good source of protein.
But take it from me kids,
cannibalism is one of those tricky things.
It's hard to do just once.
You develop a taste for it.
It's like they say at NA meetings,
once you've lured, you just want more.
Also, who counts as the rich?
Am I the rich?
I certainly hope so, because I want you to eat.
EAT.
Stop it.
See, this is why I quit academia.
If I was a professor, I'd have to behave myself.
And I don't want to behave myself.
I want to be bad.
Do you want to be bad with me?
Let's be bad.
So, you might think that envy is simply the product of inequality,
and that societies that have more inequality have more envy.
I used to assume that too.
But the more I think about it, the more I realize,
that might not be true.
Envy is a basic part of human nature.
It exists in all societies and all economic systems,
and it begins any time two or more people start comparing themselves.
Part Two.
The Desire for Mommy's Milk.
According to Sigmund Freud, or as I call him, Daddy,
Daddy!
The first stage of human development is the oral stage,
in which the primary concern is oral gratification,
which is of course provided by mommy milkies.
Am I doing too much?
I'll tone it down just a little bit.
So look, I get that a lot of people are skeptical about Freud,
and it's true, he was a bit of a crackpot coke fiend
who had some zany ideas.
Like penis envy.
Maybe there's transgender men who experience that,
but I don't think it's a basic fact of the female condition.
As for castration anxiety, is that a dare?
Because I take that personally.
I'm giving it very serious consideration, doctor.
But I feel like even when Freud is wrong,
he's often at least onto something.
Like with the Oedipus Complex,
it's not that you literally desire your mother, right?
That would be weird.
It's more that you desire an archetype.
Mother, right?
Mommy.
You guys get it.
Gen Z TikTok lesbians get it.
They're the ones who got me started on this milk shit.
I'm a reverse Socrates.
I've been corrupted by the young.
My innocent and delicate nature has been defiled.
So Freud says that in the first two years of life,
libido is primarily focused on mommy's milk.
And it's also in this stage that envy first emerges.
So I was the oldest child in my family,
and I was less than two years old when my brother was born.
So I don't remember this because I was one year old,
but my family tells me that when my brother was born,
I was just insanely jealous.
Oh, and I guess now's a good time
to discuss the difference between jealousy and envy.
Scholars agree that there is a difference,
and usually they describe the difference
in one of two ways.
The first is that jealousy is defensive.
It's a kind of protectiveness over what is rightfully yours.
Whereas envy is offensive.
It's resentment over what someone else has that you lack.
And the second difference is that envy
is between two people, the envier and the envied,
whereas jealousy typically involves three people.
As in romantic jealousy, where you have the subject,
the romantic object, and then the rival.
And the subject is jealous of the rival
because they're protective of their relationship
with the romantic object.
And that's also the dynamic of sibling rivalry,
just substituting the romantic object for mommy.
Of course in ordinary English,
people are always gonna say jealousy
when they really mean envy,
probably because jealousy has less negative connotations.
And I think it's pointless to try to fight that,
like I wouldn't go around correcting people,
but just keep in mind that there is a difference.
So sibling rivalry, is that envy or jealousy?
Well I think it's both,
because initially you're defensive
of your privileged only child relationship
with your parents.
But a new baby often gets more attention,
at least in your paranoid toddler brain,
and you might be envious of that.
And in romantic jealousy, you may also envy the rival
if she has qualities that you wish you had.
You know, young kids are little egotists
who are very sensitive to when another child
might be getting preferential treatment.
One of the favorite phrases of tiny babies
is it's not fair.
It's not fair.
Tell me about it, Pampino.
And I've got bad news.
Life is not getting any more fair than this.
According to the Bible,
one of the first events in human history
is the story of Cain y Abel, los dos hermanos.
I don't know why I said it in Spanish.
I guess I just thought it would sound cool.
Was I wrong?
Cain.
It just sounds so much better than Cain.
Cain and Abel.
God tells Cain and Abel each to make a sacrifice,
and then God prefers Abel's.
You know, because God loves meat.
Then, in an act of malicious envy toward Abel,
in spite towards God the Father,
Cain kills his younger brother.
In my earliest memories of my brother,
I already loved him,
and I don't remember the envy.
So I guess I wasn't a Cain.
Cain.
So I must have somehow worked through this
without resorting to murder.
Freud says that the older sibling's envy of the younger
leads to a recognition of impotence.
Because at first,
you selfishly want to be the special most-loved child.
But you see that your parents love your sibling
just as much as you,
and you're powerless to do anything about it.
So your ambition to superiority fails.
And so you have no choice
but to repress your ambition to superiority
as well as your envy.
And the result of that repression
is what we could call herd instinct.
Solidarity.
This feeling of identifying with a group,
the equal siblings.
And as you get older,
the herd instinct evolves into feelings about
justice, duty, community, and equality.
But Freud thought these feelings
retain a vestige of repressed envy.
If I can't be the favorite,
if I can't have special privileges,
then no one can.
And from these observations,
Freud made the generalization,
Social justice means that we deny ourselves
many things so that others
may have to do without them as well.
Okay, so we don't want other people
to have anything we can't have.
So we enviously insist on equality
as a defense against
the greater prosperity of others.
Now, I don't think I completely agree with that.
Like I think Freud is definitely
onto something here.
But don't some of our community feelings
also come from a place of
genuine care for other people?
I cared for someone once.
Rosalind.
Well, we'll come back to that later.
Let's put a pin in me for now.
A pin in it for now.
In Freud, I mean.
Let's put a pin in Freud.
In a 1966 book titled Envy,
A Theory of Social Behavior,
the sociologist Helmut Schuck argued
that rather than being,
that is a very German name.
Helmut Schuck?
It's putting me in a German mood, sweetie.
Hallo meine Lieben.
Heute gibt's ein neues Video.
I just get worse at German every year.
Schuck argued that rather than being
the result of social or economic inequality,
envy is a universal across all human societies,
including very egalitarian ones.
For example, in tribal and village cultures
around the world,
there's often a concept of black magic
or witchcraft,
which are thought to be used by envious people
to bewitch the ones they envy.
You're probably familiar with the concept
of the evil eye,
which originates in ancient Greece
or maybe even earlier than that.
Cultures all over the world today
understand the evil eye as a kind of curse
cast by the malignant gaze of an envious person.
Now you might be thinking that sounds superstitious,
but I actually think the concept of the evil eye
reveals a more sophisticated awareness of envy
and of the social danger that it poses.
You've probably seen these amulets around,
there's an emoji for them now,
which are supposed to protect against the evil eye.
It's called a nazar,
which comes from the Arabic word for sight or surveillance,
similar to the origin of the English word envy,
which is the Latin invidia,
which just means to look at.
So there's an agreement across cultures
that envy is related to sight,
the malevolent gaze,
the evil eye.
And these amulets show that a lot of people
are afraid of being envied
and want to protect themselves.
I was just watching this Turkish YouTube channel
with an episode on the evil eye
and the host explains that for Muslims,
it's customary to say,
or God has willed it when admiring a person or object,
you know, to avoid unintentionally cursing them.
I love that.
It's like no envy,
like no homo, but no envy.
Mashallah.
The top comment on that video says,
See, this is where Kim Kardashian
went wrong with her birthday post.
Clearly, no one in the Kardashian cinematic universe
has ever heard of the evil eye.
Wait, I thought these people were Armenians.
Why haven't they heard of the evil eye?
Oh, okay, nevermind.
Every piece of media they've ever produced
is about flaunting an enviable lifestyle.
This is a particularly American thing.
Most Americans have no concept of the fear of envy.
Like there's advertisements here that literally promise,
if you buy this exclusive luxury vibrator,
you'll be the envy of all your friends.
As if it's a good thing to be envied.
Oh, but it is not.
If people envy you, they gossip about you, right?
They seethe over your successes
and celebrate your misfortunes.
Being envied is basically the opposite of being loved.
So why would anyone want to be envied?
Well, it's a contradiction of human nature.
On the one hand, we need to be loved,
but then there's this other drive in us,
this like Homeric striving for fame and glory and riches,
which is kind of in conflict with our need to be loved.
In a past Gilded Age, there were stories
like Citizen Kane and Sunset Boulevard,
which warned what a sad and lonely thing
success can become.
In ancient democratic Athens,
there was a practice called ostrachismus,
which is the origin of the English word ostracism.
Ostracism was a procedure
where the Athenians would assemble
and each person would write the name
of a person they wanted to ostracize
on a pottery shard called an ostracon.
And whoever got the most votes
would simply be banished from the city for 10 years,
no questions asked.
I love the ancient world.
Things were so direct.
Often this was used to remove someone
who was becoming too prominent or too arrogant
or just annoying.
According to Plutarch,
I'm just going to read this from Wikipedia,
in one anecdote about Aristides,
known as Aristides the Just,
who was ostracized in 482,
an illiterate citizen not recognizing him
came up to ask him to write the name Aristides
on his ostracon.
When Aristides asked why,
the man replied,
it was because he was sick of hearing him
being called the Just.
It's good!
It's so good!
See this is why the idea of cancel culture is absurd.
This has been going on since the dawn of civilization.
People in most cultures,
not all,
but most cultures understand
that being envied is a massive social liability,
so it's best not to draw too much attention to yourself.
According to a Tamil saying,
the tree that bears fruit will be stoned.
This is sometimes called tall poppy syndrome
because the tallest poppies in the garden will be cut.
Shook argues that the fear of envy
is a major inhibiting force in many societies.
In Haiti,
G.E. Simpson found that a peasant
will seek to disguise his true economic position
by purchasing several smaller fields
rather than one larger piece of land.
For the same reason,
he will not wear good clothes.
He does this intentionally
to protect himself against the envious black magic
of his neighbors.
Now this kind of thing is not unheard of in America.
Like I've known people from seriously wealthy families
who move to the city
and they dress like gutter punks,
like they're trying to pass as poor.
But in general,
Americans don't openly acknowledge fear of envy
in the way many other cultures do,
and I don't think that's an accident.
We're a nation of show-offs,
and so the taboo against discussing envy
is related to our whole national ethos
of shoving our wealth in everyone's face.
But though the fear of envy
isn't widely talked about or admitted here,
it's definitely still there,
only repressed,
confined to the realm of dreams and art.
In the movie Black Swan,
Nina is a perfection-obsessed ballerina
who achieves her dream
of getting the lead role in Swan Lake,
after which her life and mind
are totally unraveled by fear of envy.
Black magic,
Black Swan.
At first we see how Nina's success
comes at the very real cost of being envied,
by her ex-ballerina mother,
by the other girls in the company,
and by the former lead ballerina she's replaced.
Did you suck his c***?
Not all of us have to.
I love Winona Ryder so much.
I love Natalie Portman so much.
I love Mila Kunis so much.
I just like women.
Where's my shock wand?
Stop it.
Stop standing.
But reasonable fear of envy becomes paranoia,
as Nina begins hallucinating
Black Swan doppelgangers,
and is seduced by bisexual demon Mila Kunis,
who's trying to steal her role.
You gotta watch out for those bisexual demons.
They'll getcha.
Did you have some sort of
lesbian dream about me?
Stop.
You could argue that Nina is actually suffering
a kind of self-envy,
where she envies the disinhibited,
sexually liberated,
corrupted part of herself
that's capable of adult eroticism,
and also of dancing the Black Swan.
So she imagines that part of herself
as an envious rival who's trying to replace her.
It's like her mind is split between two impulses.
There's her dominant White Swan impulse,
which we could call the Squidward personality,
perfectionistic and orderly,
but reserved,
priggish,
stiff.
And then there's her repressed Black Swan impulse,
which we could call the SpongeBob personality,
intuitive,
chaotic,
ecstatic.
In SpongeBob SquarePants,
the character Squidward is fundamentally a figure of envy,
stemming from failed ambition.
Hello, you've reached the house of unrecognized talent.
Squidward aspires to artistic achievement
but remains a mediocrity,
partly because of his overly dry,
doctrinaire attitude towards art.
SpongeBob is Squidward's social equal.
They're literally neighbors,
and they both work the same fast food service job
for the same exploitative capitalist.
But SpongeBob is a Mozartian intuitive genius
who's able to transform the most mundane activities,
blowing bubbles,
flipping burgers,
into a kind of aesthetic rapture.
Squidward intensely envies SpongeBob's uninhibited joy
and intuitive creativity,
but he can't admit that envy to himself.
So he convinces himself that what he's really feeling
is contempt,
snobbish disdain for SpongeBob's childish behavior.
What the people want is culture,
not dancing bubbles.
Though deep down,
Squidward really wants what SpongeBob has.
It's beautiful.
Uh, I mean, uh.
Which we see when he can't help himself
from blowing bubbles,
or when he trades away all of his possessions
for the chewing gum wrapper that in SpongeBob's hands
was a source of infinite entertainment.
A lot of people my age who watched SpongeBob as a kid
re-watch it now,
and are horrified to discover
that they identify with Squidward,
whereas as children,
they identified with SpongeBob.
Well, you either die as SpongeBob,
or you live long enough to see yourself
become the Squidward.
FUTURE!
And there's a pain in becoming Squidward,
which is usually explained as
the disappointing drudgery of adult life,
or simply loss of childhood.
I would argue that envy of childhood
is the distinctive Squidwardian emotion.
Squidwardian?
Are we saying that word?
Are we really saying that word out loud?
To an audience of millions?
Okay!
It's basically the same dynamic
as Salieri's envy of Mozart in Amadeus.
Oh my god, the evil eye killed Mozart!
You gotta watch out for that one, kids.
If a mysterious stranger shows up
on your doorstep at midnight
asking you to compose a requiem mass for your own father,
just say no.
So in Spongemadeus' Mozart pants,
we have a diligent though stuffy wannabe,
envying the effortless playfulness
of the spontaneous genius.
Squidward's envy of SpongeBob is,
well, it's Apollo's envy of Dionysus.
Look, if we were to view SpongeBob SquarePants
through the philosophy of Friedrich Nietzsche,
stay with me ladies, I have an angle here,
we could say that Squidward represents
what Nietzsche called the Apollonian impulse,
while SpongeBob represents the Dionysian.
Nietzsche thought there were two
conflicting artistic drives in the human personality.
The Apollonian, named after the Greek god Apollo,
is the drive towards self-control, order, logic, morality.
And the Dionysian, named after Dionysus,
is the drive toward intoxication, frenzy, passion, intuition.
Both SpongeBob and Amadeus present these two drives
in conflict, with the Apollonian envying the Dionysian.
Of course, this is a misrepresentation
of how art is actually created,
because Nietzsche's whole point is that
you need a balance of the two drives.
In reality, you cannot have a pure Dionysian artist
like SpongeBob, because creating good art
requires at least some level of discipline in ordering.
See? It is all in the technique.
Otherwise, you're just some drunk idiot with a guitar.
Get off the stage!
So Black Swan is, in a way, actually more realistic.
In order to give the perfect performance,
Mina has to unify her fragmented personality
and dance both swans, resolving the envious rivalry
between her two artistic impulses.
It was perfect.
Another movie about fear of envious ballerina-doppelgangers
Can you guess it?
is Jordan Peele's 2019 horror film Us,
which dramatizes the repressed economic guilt and fear
of the American middle class.
We meet the Wilsons, a moderately affluent family
with a vacation house and a boat,
along with the Tylers, a slightly better-off white family
whom the Wilsons envy.
Saw their new car, right?
You had to do it.
You just had to get that thing to fuck with me too.
One night, the Wilsons' vacation home is invaded
by a family of their own monstrous doppelgangers.
Red, the only doppelganger who can speak,
explains that her family is metaphysically tethered
to the Wilsons, living wretched and destitute versions
of their lives in a liminal backroom's underworld.
It's super fucking liminal.
I'm on Ambien at an AA meeting.
Not again.
Once upon a time, there was a girl,
and the girl had a shadow.
The two were connected, tethered together.
When the girl ate, her food was given to her warm and tasty.
But when the shadow was hungry,
she had to eat rabbit, raw and bloody.
We later find out that all over the US,
O-U-S spells us.
Hey, that's the title of the movie.
Ohhhhh.
The tethered have risen up to kill
their privileged doppelgangers,
and to link arms across the country
in a dark parody of the real world
1986 homelessness fundraiser Hands Across America.
So my reading of Us is that it's an expression
of middle class guilt about privilege,
and fear of envy.
It's not a movie about the working class.
If it was a movie about the working class,
then the working class would be able
to speak human languages,
and would not be scary monsters
who make animal sounds
and stagger around like zombies.
This is a movie about the anxious middle class's
nightmare of the working class.
Us represents in a self-aware way
what other home invasion movies represent unconsciously.
The fear of the envious poor,
of revolution, of slave revolt.
Tell me you did not just reference Home Alone.
But Us diverges from other home invasion movies
by not just being fearful about the underclass,
but also guilty.
The idea of the tethered underclass
represents life as a zero-sum game
where every moment of your happiness
is bought with someone else's suffering.
It's an incredibly guilty fantasy,
an internalization of the black magic logic
of people who blame their own misfortunes
on the people they envy.
As Shook puts it,
my neighbor's harvest
can only have turned out better than mine
because he has somehow succeeded
in reducing mine by black magic.
So the fear of envy and the guilt of success
are repressed in American culture,
but they still find expression in movies.
Jordan Peele is kind of like
the Charles Dickens of the 21st century.
Us actually reminds me of A Christmas Carol,
a story about the guilt of the rich
if ever there was one.
You know, Scrooge is visited by ghosts
who show him how wretched and sad
the lives of his employees are,
and how he'll die alone and hated by everyone,
and his funeral is only attended by businessmen
on the condition that lunch is provided.
Dickens was truly the master
of scaring the rich straight.
So maybe fear of envy
can serve a softly regulatory function
by motivating charity and generosity in the rich.
But in general,
I'm suspicious of envy as a motivation for politics.
Because remember,
the basic logic of envy is,
if I can't have it, then no one can.
Which is a purely negative, destructive style of thinking.
It's taking privileges away,
not for the material benefit of the underprivileged,
but merely for the psychological satisfaction
of the envious person.
And that's even worse when you consider
that envy is subjective.
It doesn't necessarily target
objective power and privilege.
So envy in politics is not by any means
relegated to the left.
Conservative politics is brimming with envy.
Like in this debate about forgiving student loan debt,
you often hear people say,
I had to pay my student loans,
so they should too.
Debt forgiveness is not fear.
The logic here is,
since I didn't get my student debt forgiven,
no one should.
It's intergenerational envy,
which is a pretty common thing.
Usually older generations envying the young.
Kids these days have it so easy.
When I was young, we ate nails for breakfast
and sent text messages on the Pony Express.
The feeling is basically,
it's not fair that kids these days
don't have to suffer like I suffered.
Or think about the concept of a welfare queen,
which openly reeks of envy and white resentment.
Or the way conservatives talk about immigration.
It's all this envious suspicion
about illegal immigrants sneaking in
and getting government handouts
without having to pay taxes.
I had to work hard for my money,
so why should these people get a free ride?
Not that that's what being an illegal immigrant
is actually like,
except in the imagination of people who envy them.
Envy is felt more intensely by prideful people,
so it's especially sharp when it targets people
who are supposed to be beneath you.
The Jewish radical feminist Andrea Dworkin
made what I think is a pretty compelling argument
that both anti-Semitism and misogyny
are partly rooted in envy.
She quotes a bigoted argument
made by the wife-killing protagonist
of Tolstoy's story, The Kreutzer Sonata,
who resents that women and Jews
find a kind of paradoxical power in their own oppression.
Just like the Jews,
as they pay us back for their oppression
by financial domination,
so it is with women.
Ah, you want us to be traitors only?
All right.
As traitors, we will dominate you, say the Jews.
Ah, you want us to be merely objects of sensuality?
All right.
As objects of sensuality, we will enslave you.
Dworkin explains,
This dominance of men by women
is experienced by the men as real,
emotionally real,
sexually real,
psychologically real.
It emerges as the reason for the wrath of the misogynist.
The woman appears to control sex.
The man needs it.
This causes his rage at her perceived power over him.
Women control access to what men want,
which gives women a kind of indirect power
that some men envy.
They envy the sexual power of women.
It doesn't matter to the misogynist that,
especially at the time Tolstoy was writing,
women objectively have less power in society than men.
He envies women because they have what he desires.
Likewise, it didn't matter to Weimar anti-Semites
that Jewish people were a marginalized minority.
Anti-Semitism is often rooted in an envious obsession
with the disproportionate influence
and affluence of Jewish people.
It is not the absolute differences between men
which feed envy,
but subjective perception,
the optics of envy.
Magic mirror on the wall.
Who's the cuntest of them all?
Thou art cunt, my queen.
But hold, a lovely maid I see.
Oh, yes, it's me.
What?
In a way, I'm kind of just in the beginning
of this whole transition.
I'm not sure what to expect.
I'm kind of just in the beginning
of this whole transition.
You know, like a young little girl
going through all these things,
having a sleepover with the girls.
What do we do on a sleepover?
Do we have like pillow fights and all that stuff?
Alas, she is more cunt than thee.
My pussy stunting on the Gram has come to nothing.
The classic 1937 Disney movie
Snow White and the Wicked Milf
is the story of a, quote,
vain and wicked queen
who obsessively envies
the beauty of her own stepdaughter.
Are you sure this one's for children?
Every day the milf queen asks the mirror
who is the fairest one of all,
and the mirror responds
that the queen is the fairest,
till one day it says
the stepdaughter Snow White is the fairest,
which sends the queen into an envious fury,
resulting in a series of bizarre murder attempts.
So first of all, can we talk plot holes, ding?
Are we really supposed to believe
that this is more beautiful than this?
Uh, ding.
Isn't Snow White like 12 years old?
What's going on, Walt?
Why don't you take a seat?
Maybe she's not 12, I don't know.
It's hard to tell
because she's constantly surrounded by manlets,
but she's just so boring,
and the queen is such a baddie.
Step on my throat, mother.
This is a horny video.
Well, yeah, because I quit riding that brown tiger.
I can feel the pulse back in my veins.
So despite the injustice done to its lead milf,
Snow White does illustrate
some interesting things about envy.
Once again, we have black magic and witchcraft
as an expression of envy.
We have the age difference,
intergenerational envy, the envy of youth.
It kind of reminds me of those millennial women
who hit 30 and suddenly feel a need
to rage against Gen Z.
Pretty counterproductive,
since if you're worried about seeming old,
complaining about the youths,
it's probably not helping your case gorge.
You might wonder if there's also jealousy
involved with the evil queen.
Is she worried that the king
is gonna fall in love with his own daughter?
Well, I don't think so,
because we never even see the king.
The queen doesn't mention him.
It's not about the king.
So there's no romantic jealousy involved.
It's just one woman envying another woman
over beauty for its own sake.
We stan a Bechdel test passing
movie about women hating each other.
Gatekeep, gas girl, gate girl, gas keep, light boss.
In fact, in the original Brothers Grimm version,
the queen first tries killing Snow White
with beauty accessories,
poisoning a comb,
and lacing her to death with a corset.
I wish I could die that way.
What's really striking
is the pure kamikaze malignity of it all.
This queen, who we know is obsessed with her look,
is willing to transform herself with witchcraft
into an ugly old hag,
just to give Snow White the poisoned apple.
And the queen disguising herself as an old hag
parallels Satan disguising himself as a serpent.
I mean, you could actually argue
that the queen is simply a persona of Satan,
it's paradise lost all over again,
which also happens to be the title of my memoir.
The queen is incredibly petty,
because even according to the, again,
wrong and tasteless mirror,
she's still the second most beautiful woman in the world.
How could someone so close to the top of the hierarchy
still be consumed by envy?
Well, basically, because that's how envy works.
It's petty, it's subjective,
and it's indifferent to the magnitude of the inequality,
or to the absolute position on the overall hierarchy.
So you can be the second best in the world,
and still be obsessively envious
of the one person who may barely even be above you.
In fact, there's studies showing
that Olympic silver medalists
are actually less satisfied with their prize
than bronze medalists,
probably because the bronze medalist
is just happy to be on the podium at all,
while the silver medalist is so close to first,
they can't help but wonder, what if?
Humans form our sense of identity and self-worth
not by comparing ourselves to any absolute standard,
but by comparing ourselves to each other,
and we're more likely to compare ourselves
to the people who are around us
than we are to people who are far away.
We could call this the proximity effect of envy.
We're more likely to envy people who are close to us,
or similar to us,
especially people we're in competition with.
That's why social media is such a nightmare.
It's an incubator of envy,
because it puts everyone next to everyone else.
So we're all being compared, all in competition,
and it can destroy your self-esteem,
because you're comparing your actual life
to these idealized images.
And it also turns public figures
into lightning rods for envy,
because of the numeric visibility of popularity and success.
It's a perverse consequence of the proximity effect
that envy within an oppressed class
is often more venomous and obsessive
than envy for the oppressor.
So for example, in Snow White and Black Swan,
you have women envying other women,
because women are often in competition with each other.
And I know it's kind of a misogynistic trope.
In media, there's constant portrayals
of vain and envious women.
Jealous bitches fighting over men.
Over youth.
Over beauty.
It's like drag queen femininity.
Death becomes her femininity.
-"En garde, bitch!"
So yeah, it's kind of a misogynistic trope,
but, how do I put this delicately,
sometimes reality is misogynistic.
Like when my eyelash won't stay glued on!
The patriarchy's machinations are clearly to blame.
In her 1976 essay Trashing the Dark Side of Sisterhood,
feminist Jo Freeman wrote about her ostracism
from within the women's movement.
-"I've been watching for years with increasing dismay
as the movement consciously destroys anyone within it
who stands out in any way."
And she quotes a speech by fellow feminist Anselma Delolio.
-"And who do they attack?
Achievement or accomplishment of any kind
would seem to be the worst crime.
Do anything that every other woman secretly
or otherwise feels she could do just as well,
and you're in for it.
You are immediately labeled a thrill-seeking opportunist,
a ruthless mercenary out to make her fame and fortune
over the dead bodies of selfless sisters
who have buried their abilities
and sacrificed their ambitions
for the greater glory of feminism."
Freeman speculates,
-"The primary reason there have been so few great women blank
is not merely that greatness has been undeveloped
or unrecognized,
but that women exhibiting potential for achievement
are punished by both women and men.
The fear of success is quite rational
when one knows that the consequence of achievement
is hostility and not praise."
So at no point in this essay
does Joe Freeman use the word envy.
But as usual, envy is right below the surface,
causing all the trouble.
So Freeman is describing
how people from marginalized groups,
whose ambition raises them above the typical limits
set by marginalization,
are often ostracized from their own communities.
But she has no causal explanation for why this happens.
I have an explanation.
The explanation is envy.
And women are more likely to envy other women.
Trans women are more likely to envy other trans women.
Oh god, am I really gonna go there?
If we did this topic justice,
this video would be nine centuries long.
-"En garde, bitch!"
A lot of people assume that trans women envy cis women,
and there is some truth to that.
There definitely was a time in my life
when I used to envy cis women for being cis women,
but now I kind of just don't even allow myself
to have the thought,
what if I were a cis woman?
So in a way, because becoming a cis woman is impossible,
it's unobtainable,
I actually envy cis women less.
So trans women are more likely to envy other trans women
because of the proximity effect,
and because another trans woman
represents an actual possibility
of what I, a trans woman, could become.
She's a standard to which I could plausibly compare myself.
Here's a post someone made on my own fan subreddit.
Am I the only one who finds it hard
to watch trans creators?
Before I realized I was a trans woman,
I fucking loved people like ContraPoints,
Nyx Fears, and other trans creators.
But ever since I realized I was trans,
I just get this angry, resentful feeling
in the pit of my stomach
whenever I get recommended any of these videos.
I seriously loved ContraPoints,
but whenever I try to watch any of her videos,
I just wanna scream.
I have this feeling toward passing trans people in general.
I feel such hatred for them, and I don't know why.
Am I just a toxic person?
Well, sweetie, you're not a toxic person,
at least not any worse than anyone else,
it's just that human nature is a toxic person.
And that angry, resentful feeling
in the pit of your stomach
that makes you wanna scream
and feel such a hatred has a name,
and the name is Envy.
I actually admire the person who wrote this post,
because they're doing the best
that any of us can do, really,
which is noticing the feeling
without endorsing the feeling.
I wish that more people could feel things
without rushing to a rational defense of the feeling.
And isn't rationality itself
often simply the attempt to make our feelings contagious?
Sometimes people have no self-awareness about it at all.
For example, there's a certain kind of boomer transsexual
who complains that,
when I transitioned,
I had to go through rigorous medical gatekeeping
but kids these days just waltz on in
and walk out with hormones.
It's intergenerational envy, trans edition.
It was hard for me,
so it should be hard for everyone,
like the student debt debate.
If I can't have it, no one can.
And look, I do have sympathy and admiration
for older trans people.
Like, being trans in 2021
is already the maximum level of adversity
that I can handle.
I cannot imagine how hard it was to do this in the 80s.
However, the pain of envy is not a valid argument.
Envy is not sacred rage,
and the malignant demands of envious people
should be ignored.
God, this community.
The constant competition.
The envy, the cringing.
It makes it really hard to get along
with other trans people.
Oh, speaking of which.
Gay tangent, everybody.
Gay tangent.
Envy presents kind of a unique problem
to same-sex attracted people
because of the increased risk
of envying the very people you're attracted to.
I want to f*** the ones I envy.
I envy.
You know, it's the classic
do I want you or do I want to be you problem.
I've heard feminine queer women say
they could never date another femme
because they're worried
they would just end up envying her.
So dating masculine women solves that problem
because having separate roles,
separate aesthetics,
separate categories
helps to avert proximity envy between partners.
Unfortunately, I am not that smart.
Basically, I am attracted to femininity.
But I also want to embody
a kind of feminine archetype myself.
I'm not masculine and I don't want to be.
You know, I used to think
I'd only want to date another trans woman
because of the mutual understanding.
But I've kind of realized that at this point
it may actually be more psychologically healthy
for me to open up to dating cis women.
I used to not want to do that
because I was afraid it would make me feel like a man.
But at this point, honestly, just be a man.
Whatever, it's fine.
As a drag queen once said,
I'm more of a man than you'll ever be
and more of a woman than you'll ever have.
Yes, gawd.
Can we get the tequila out of the frame, please?
I think at a distance,
it's okay to indulge the attraction emulation ambiguity.
But if you want to actually have a relationship with someone,
you have to make up your mind
that you desire this woman
and you do not want to be her.
Because think about it from the other perspective.
What could be less attractive
than someone who literally wants to be you?
Teacher, make her stop copying me.
Like as much as I joke every episode
about how Buffalo Bill is an iconic trans legend,
you don't want to date that bitch.
Imagine trying to date Eve from All About Eve.
Pass.
Hard pass.
So if you're a queer woman or a queer anything, honestly,
and you find yourself envying your partner,
my advice is stop overthinking a good situation.
An enviable woman wanted to be with you.
So sit back, relax, and enjoy the clout.
I get it though, it's complicated.
You know, we're all supposed to proudly affirm
what we truly desire,
but how do you know what you truly desire?
Do I want mommy?
Or do I want to be the mommy?
Yes.
Just yes.
Anyway, let's go back to talking about Sigmund Freud.
The mother half took over completely.
Do I look okay?
Is my hat on straight?
So we keep running into this avoidance of the word envy.
And people especially cannot seem to notice
when they themselves are feeling envious.
Like that person who puzzled over the angry resentful feeling
in the pit of their stomach
without being able to name what they were feeling.
There's two reasons why people are usually in denial
about their own envy.
One is guilt, and the other is shame.
Shame.
Shame because admitting to yourself that you envy someone
implies that you feel inferior to them,
which is shameful.
It wounds the ego.
And guilt because envy is malicious.
If you envy someone, you may feel angry and miserable
about their success and good fortune,
and you may wish to see them ruined or brought down.
That's cruel and antisocial.
It goes against most ideas of morality,
and it's a thought that's usually
not socially acceptable to admit.
So envy is shameful, guilty, and socially unacceptable.
And we deal with that by suppressing it from our awareness.
But it is still there.
And in order to maintain the denial,
we have to convince ourselves that this angry resentful feeling
in the pit of our stomach is actually something else.
Think about how in Spongebob,
Squidward shows contempt for Spongebob's childishness,
for blowing bubbles, for having fun at work,
when in fact, Squidward envies Spongebob's uninhibited joy
and intuitive creativity.
But he can't allow himself to have the thought
that he envies Spongebob,
because that would mean recognizing
the intolerably shameful truth
that he feels inferior to Spongebob.
So what he does instead is convince himself
that what he really is, is a refined sophisticate,
scoffing at this childish fool.
How did I ever get surrounded by such loser neighbors?
We could call this envy-to-contempt sublimation.
Sublimation is a psychoanalytic term,
which means that you transform an ego-wounding feeling
or socially unacceptable longing
into something more ego-flattering or socially acceptable.
So the classic example used by Freud
is the transformation of sexual urges,
of erotic energy, into creative expression.
It's like the founder of the NoFap movement,
Lady Gaga, once said,
I have this weird thing that if I sleep with someone,
they're gonna take my creativity from me through my...
So according to Freud,
the vast majority of erotic longings
can never be fulfilled.
Tell me about a segment...
Ugh, misery.
But there's a positive side to this, supposedly,
which is that you can sublimate your erotic longings
into a more socially acceptable productivity.
So, you know, instead of slicking the bean,
maybe you write novels about thirsty vampires,
or for that matter, philosophical treatises
about the will to power.
Oh, we'll get to you.
Freud thought that civilization itself
is built at the cost of our instincts,
most of which we have to sacrifice
in order to live in a society.
So like erotic impulses,
I think envy can be sublimated,
which is what's happening when it becomes contempt.
Another example is the blog McMansion Hell,
which makes fun of the tasteless architecture
of suburban ostentatious trash.
I would argue that part of the fun of this blog
is the pleasure and relief of looking down at the rich.
Because looking enviously up at the rich
is painful, it makes you feel inferior.
And a way to alleviate that pain
is to sublimate envy and pretend
that you're an aristocratic aesthete
scoffing at the vulgar taste of the era of East.
These flying buttresses are an extremely poor taste.
Another example is shit-talking plastic surgery.
I once heard a trans woman say,
at least I don't look like a botched sex doll.
The subtext is,
there's a certain kind of trans woman influencer
who lives in LA and has a lot of cosmetic surgery
to achieve a doll-like aesthetic.
But it costs a lot of money to look like this.
And a lot of trans women can't afford
surgeries that they want.
And one way to cope with frustrated desire
is to convince yourself that the thing
that's out of reach is not worth having anyway.
See also the discourse on Twitter
about how passing is transphobic.
There's an ancient Greek fable
where a fox wants some grapes,
but he can't reach the vine.
So he walks away bitterly and says,
well the grapes are transphobic anyway.
The cisgender version of this is maybe
the not-like-other-girls meme,
which is classic envy-to-contempt sublimation.
The trope is usually that other girls
are popular and slutty.
They have fake tans and fake nails.
They like partying and makeup
and stupid music for idiots.
But I'm quirky and real.
I listen to Pink Floyd and read books
and eat lots of pizza late at night,
alone and sad.
There's usually a subtext of anxiety
about inferiority,
the other girls being more socially accepted,
feminine, and put together.
A lot of times the other girls
don't even exist, right?
They're a media construct of idealized womanhood.
Like where are these other girls
who've never eaten pizza
and enjoy wearing makeup at 9am on a Saturday morning?
Are they between the sofa cushions?
Did you put them in with the other laundry?
Are the other girls in the room with us right now?
So the feeling of inferiority
toward the other girls
is reframed as a kind of contemptuous
hipster superiority,
which is really just an ego-defensive
persona of resentment.
Like Janice in Mean Girls.
She's not even really a lesbian.
She's Lebanese.
Lebanese.
Regina got confused.
And then she dances with a boy at the end
and is readmitted into girlhood.
Uh, thank you for that Tina Fey,
that's very helpful.
Great.
Another way we can reframe
feelings of envious inferiority
is by transforming them into moral superiority.
Moral superiority often being the refuge
of people with nothing better to feel superior about.
We don't have to feel guilty or ashamed of envy
if we convince ourselves
that what we're actually experiencing
is justified, legitimate hatred.
So for example,
think of the morality around sexuality.
Part 69.
Sluts.
Yeah, what are you gonna do about it?
Cancel me?
En garde!
Bitch!
Why does everyone hate sluts so much?
Sluts never did nothing wrong to nobody.
Open sexual promiscuity is in a way
analogous to opulence.
You're conspicuously enjoying something
that other people want but may not be able to get.
Many cultures have norms about modesty,
for example expecting women
to cover their hair in public.
This is usually explained as
prophylaxis against male lust,
but I wonder if it also serves
to prevent a more generalized envy,
which female beauty has a way of attracting.
Men often slut shame
because they want to control female sexuality.
And by female sexuality,
I do mean male sexuality,
because often what they're really struggling to control
is their own desire.
But slut shaming is also done
pretty viciously by women to each other.
And that's a complicated thing.
It's more than just envy.
Sometimes it comes from a sense
that a woman who's having casual sex with a lot of men
is compromising the collective
sex-withholding power of the group,
almost like she's crossing a picket line.
But there's also sometimes a resentment
that a woman who's showing skin
is using her body to get unearned attention.
And that smells like envy to me.
I don't use my body to get attention,
so no one should.
The repressed feeling is
maybe I'm a little jealous
that she's getting all this attention
by posting thirst traps,
but you don't think that.
You think,
I am above this
because I am chaste.
I have class.
I am a feminist.
I would also suggest accusing her
of pandering to the male gaze.
That's, of course, the feminist way
of calling someone a low-down hobag skank.
So again, we have envy to contempt sublimation,
and often the contempt is moral, virtuous.
The psychological need to convince ourselves
that envy is morality can become so strong
that we actually start inventing things
to be outraged about.
Take, for instance, the tendency to imagine
that the wealthy and powerful
are enjoying wild satanic orgies
and indulging all the forbidden salacious pleasures
that we ourselves are denied.
Like QAnon, these conspiracy theorists
who want us to imagine Hillary Clinton
reclining in a garden of earthly delights,
sampling the pleasures of Ephibes.
Live, laugh, love that for her.
Envy is very imaginative when it comes
to the hedonistic extravagance of the envied.
Let's talk about Marie Antoinette,
the queen of France who was guillotined by the revolution.
If you know one thing about Marie Antoinette,
it's probably that when she heard about a famine
where the people had no bread,
she infamously responded,
let them eat cake.
What an evil bitch.
How could she say that?
Well, she didn't.
She never said it.
It's a lie.
The phrase let them eat cake,
originally let them eat brioche,
first appeared in Rousseau's Confessions,
written in 1765 when Marie Antoinette was nine years old.
Rousseau attributed the line to a great princess.
Probably no one ever said this.
It's kind of like how the most famous photo
of Paris Hilton is the one where she's wearing
a Stop Being Poor t-shirt.
What an evil bitch.
How could she wear that?
Well, she didn't.
It's photoshopped.
The actual shirt said Stop Being Desperate.
Envy likes to fabricate the diabolical crimes
of its enemies.
I assume to compliment the hedonistic extravagance.
I mean, what is a Disney villain
if not an opulent homosexual
seen through the eyes of the envious?
See how I do it?
I'm gonna try lowering the ISO
because it's so f***ing bright in here now.
Okay, well it's a much lower ISO.
What if I get another white over here?
That's what this channel is really about,
one biological female's quest
to create a harmonious color story.
In the years leading up to
and during the French Revolution,
Marie Antoinette was constantly defamed
in these sleazy tabloids called libelles.
It's the same root as the English word libel.
The often pornographic libelles depicted the queen
as a bisexual demon
who was constantly having drunken orgies
and sexually manipulating everyone around her.
All of which is very interesting,
but none of which is true.
The historian Robert Darnton called it
an avalanche of defamation
that has no parallel in the history of vilification.
This woman took the blame,
the moral blame,
for the structural failings of a broken economic system.
And by the time she was brought
before the Revolutionary Tribunal in 1793,
the actual person Marie Antoinette
had long ago been overshadowed
by the libellous caricature of her.
Now there was maybe one good reason
for executing the former queen,
which is that the legitimacy of your new republic
is a little more secure
when you don't have living monarchs hanging around.
Someone better tell the English.
But the problem with that reasoning
is it has nothing to do
with whether or not the queen deserved to die.
And beheading a recently widowed mother of two
in front of a jeering crowd for political expediency
might weigh a little heavy on the conscience.
So the Revolution had to convince themselves
that the queen deserved it,
which was pretty easy after decades of,
again, false and defamatory gossip.
In her biography of Marie Antoinette,
Antonia Fraser describes
how the prison guards separated Marie
from her eight-year-old son,
who they plied with alcohol
and groomed into accusing his own mother
of incestuous abuse.
To justify killing Marie Antoinette,
they had to destroy the idea of this woman as a mother.
So she was convicted of what may as well have been
crimes against ethics in games journalism,
and sent to the guillotine,
where her last words were
sorry to the executioner for stepping on his foot.
A women-stop-apologizing challenge.
This is what a girlboss winning looks like.
So Marie Antoinette literally did nothing wrong.
Hey, how are you?
An innocent milf was killed that day,
and I, for one, won't stand for it.
So look, we have a psychological incentive
to believe that people whom we envy are immoral monsters,
because then we get to label our hatred and violence
toward them justice.
Cruelty generally cannot conceptualize itself as cruelty,
and part of the reason for that
is that calling cruelty what it is
takes the fun out of it.
It reminds me of the second best day
in the history of Twitter,
October 1st, 2020,
the day that Trump got COVID.
And I'm gonna be honest,
I have never felt more schadenfreude in my entire life.
Well, well, well.
If it isn't the leopards-eating-people's-faces party
having their faces eaten by leopards.
It's the last time I eat cake.
Like Dan Savage said,
it felt like Ronald Reagan got AIDS.
The next day, I tweeted,
these last 24 hours have been the first time
I've genuinely enjoyed Twitter in years,
because this website is good for one thing only,
reveling in the cruelest of human impulses.
And someone responded to that saying,
oh my god, could you even be a bigger killjoy?
But why was I being a killjoy?
The tweet was about how much I was enjoying it.
Well, for most people,
I guess not me,
but for normal people,
for other girls,
cruelty is only pleasurable
as long as they can convince themselves
it's something other than cruelty.
Justice served.
So again, reason, rationality,
are often the attempt to publicly communicate,
to evangelize our private feelings.
And morality, ethics, and justice
are often put forward
as the respectable public face
of private envy, vindictiveness, and hatred.
But is this a corruption of morality?
Or have we stumbled onto something darker?
What if morality itself
is simply the expression
of some kind of sadomasochistic urge?
It's too early for this.
I mean, it's literally 7 a.m. where I'm filming.
I don't know how this keeps happening to me.
My head gets cut off one afternoon.
Puts me in a philosophical mood.
Next morning, I've stayed up all night
and I'm still talking about the philosophes.
Meow meow.
Hello again, kittens.
Let's talk about justice, uwu.
I look like a Supreme Court justice.
Sonia?
Soda meow your?
It would actually be fierce if I wasn't, you know,
if I wasn't being Natalie.
Look, I've been seeing a lot of comments lately
along the lines of,
Natalie used to do serious academic arguments.
Now she only cares about makeup.
All right, you little shits.
You want book learning?
I'm gonna learn you so hard.
I'm gonna learn you so hard
you're gonna have a god damn headache in the morning.
Friedrich Nietzsche.
Friedrich Wilhelm Nietzsche.
Do you mind if I call you Fred?
Friedrich was a German philosopher
who had a lot to say about envy and morality.
But before we get into that,
I want to say a little bit about his life,
because it's just very funny.
Nietzsche is famous for his concept of the Ubermensch,
but Friedrich, sweet, beautiful little Friedrich,
he was not what most people think of as an Ubermensch.
Friedrich was a chronically ill, chronically in pain,
nearly blind incel,
who probably slept with a prostitute once
and got syphilis and died.
Life is funny.
Sad, but funny.
In the introduction to Beyond Good and Evil,
the editor says,
though he prided himself on being comfortable with women,
he does not seem to have been very successful
in establishing emotionally satisfying relationships with them,
which is hardly surprising.
Ah!
I love when the introduction to a book
is just a brutal roast of the author.
Who wrote this?
Rolf Peter Horstmann.
You're killing it, Rolf.
You're savage.
I adore.
Friedrich's books sold a dismal number of copies in his lifetime.
What emerges is a picture of a totally isolated,
highly neurotic man who had to try hard
to avoid thinking of himself as a complete failure.
Oh.
He was also doing huge doses of opium, relatable,
and writing himself prescriptions for sleeping pills
using the name Dr. Nietzsche.
Dr. Nietzsche?
Pretty sure I got a Xanax prescription from that guy once.
Behind a Dairy Queen.
Nietzsche was also a failed musician,
and was in love with the composer Richard Wagner's wife.
The virgin Nietzsche contra the Chad Wagner.
You beta cuck.
Why did I do that?
Can we all agree that catgirl Nietzsche
is by far the most cursed thing I've ever done?
I just wanna mom this guy, honestly.
I don't even care that he's a misogynist.
His misogyny is simply too sad to be offended by.
You know, I think it's interesting
that a person this pathetic
can also be a genius whose name will never die.
He's someone who had a lot of reason
to be envious and self-pitying,
but his philosophy couldn't be more against that.
And as a person of pathetic experience myself,
that is unironically kind of inspiring to me.
So let's go in.
In his book on the genealogy of morality,
Frederick wants to explain the origin
of the concepts of good and evil.
Under what conditions did man invent
the value judgments good and evil,
and what value do they themselves have?
Have they to now obstructed or promoted human flourishing?
Hang on, my food's here.
That's right, you're getting a mukbang, sweetie.
Did you think I was gonna sit at this giant table
and not be eating something?
This video's been going on more than an hour,
so I assume you guys are drunk by now,
and we're just kind of hanging out at this point.
You guys can't even see.
Well, here, I've got a bunch of sushi,
and it's my mission to eat all of this
while summarizing the entire life
and work of Friedrich Nietzsche.
Trisha Paytas, Nicocado, consider this a challenge.
So Frederick argues that good and bad,
not good and evil, that's different, we'll get to that,
but good and bad were originally the self-affirming values
of people with power.
So to be good meant to be powerful,
strong, beautiful, healthy,
and to be bad meant to be weak, sick, common, ugly.
I'm gonna eat one like a cat.
And Frederick supports this speculation with etymology.
So in a lot of languages,
the word that means morally good or spiritually noble
originally meant noble in the sense of aristocratic,
the propertied class.
Like in Buddhism, the Arya Satyani,
that's Sanskrit for noble truths.
Arya means noble.
And Arya is used to mean spiritually noble,
but earlier it meant the aristocracy, the rich.
And originally, it was just the name
that a culture in Northern India gave themselves, the Aryans.
I'm really working not to get soy sauce on this lace.
This was later misunderstood by Europeans
who wrongly thought that Aryan was a race.
Oops, goddammit.
Goddammit, kids, can we not?
Frederick traces the origin of the German word gut,
or the English good, to the name of the Goths.
No, not those Goths,
the Scandinavian people who invaded Europe.
Frederick calls them the blonde beasts of prey.
I like to stalk my prey in the small hours of the night.
The German word schlecht, which means bad,
is related to schlicht, which means plain,
simple, originally common, low,
not aristocratic, not noble.
So good and bad were originally the values
of warrior aristocrats,
who were like Homeric heroes celebrating themselves.
And Frederick calls their value system master morality,
this glorification of combat, feasting,
athleticism, sexual conquest, beauty.
These things were called good,
and their opposites, weakness, impotence,
ugliness, were called bad.
The ancient nobles worshiped noble gods
who acted like them and shared their values.
I mean, if I created a personal goddess,
I think we all know what animal that would be,
me and the ancient Egyptians on the same page.
So for example, Roman warriors could worship Mars,
the god of war,
and it was like they were worshiping themselves.
They were dumb jocks worshiping dumb jock gods.
Well, good for them,
but what about the people who got shoved into lockers?
Well, Frederick's example,
and this is gonna create some misunderstandings later,
but his example is the Jews,
who were colonized by the Romans in Judea.
And it's certainly not that the Jews didn't try to revolt.
Oh, they did, multiple times.
But for several centuries,
the Romans were just too powerful.
No one could stop them.
So the question is,
what happens psychologically to people who are oppressed
and who lack the power to overthrow the oppressor?
Well, in that case,
frustrated vindictiveness builds over time
to become this deep bitterness,
which Nietzsche gave the French name
Rsentiment, resentment in English.
Oui, eh, eh, oui, absolument, naturellement.
I don't speak French,
I just enjoy making vaguely French noises.
M'en, pas, quatre, eh, eh oui.
I don't like the English,
but I like the French even less.
Because they're always dressed so well
and they speak a sexier language than me.
Stop it.
This is your final warning, comprendez-vous?
Good wine though, I'll give them that.
So there's a German word, Neid, which means envy.
So why is Frederick using this French term, Rsentiment?
What's going on, Frederick?
Why are you speaking French?
Are you nervous?
Are you trying to impress me?
Nietzsche must have said Rsentiment,
because he thought it was something different than envy.
I think the difference is resentment,
and I'm just gonna use the English word
so I don't sound like an asshole,
resentment is born not just of wanting what someone has,
but of a permanent frustration of the desire for revenge.
It's born of weakness, inability to get revenge.
Now revenge itself implies weakness,
at least a temporary weakness.
We say revenge is best served cold,
but actually, revenge is only served cold.
If it's served hot, if someone slaps you
and you slap them back immediately,
that's retaliation, not revenge.
You brought this on yourself.
Revenge is only a possibility
when you can't retaliate immediately,
so you become vindictive, you start plotting and scheming.
But if you're too weak, too impotent
to have any hope of revenge, then you become resentful.
So Nietzsche's argument is that a person
who's too weak to get material revenge
can instead get psychological revenge
by creating a new morality.
In Frederick's words,
the beginning of the slave's revolt and morality
occurs when resentment itself turns creative
and gives birth to values.
This is a little high concept for a mukbang, isn't it?
What are you doing, Frederick?
So while master morality says that good
is power, riches, health, and strength,
and bad is the opposite,
slave morality, the morality of resentment,
says blessed are the poor, the meek,
the sick, the powerless.
This is the good of slave morality,
and its opposite is not the bad,
but a new concept, the evil.
And what is evil?
Well, everything that master morality says is good.
Power, wealth, conquest, sexual satisfaction.
He's talking about Christianity here,
he's not talking about Judaism.
But Frederick thinks of Christianity
as the spiritual revenge of the Jews against the Romans,
an inversion of the empire's values.
But he also thinks that slave morality
is fundamentally dishonest.
It's like the fox and the grapes.
Not being able to take revenge
is called not wanting to take revenge.
It might even be called forgiveness.
Slave morality says that weakness is righteous.
Submission to people you hate is called obedience.
Having to wait is called patience.
Inability to satisfy sexual desire
is called chastity, purity, and so on.
And while master morality is born of saying yes to yourself
as a powerful, noble beast of prey,
slave morality is born of saying no to the master
and everything he has that you can't.
I like to have my belly rubbed.
Scratch my back above my tail, please.
I'm gonna put the rest of the fish away
because it's getting warm and I'm full.
This has not been a successful mukbang.
It turns out that it's actually very difficult
to do a mukbang while talking.
I should've thought this through a little harder, hmm.
So slave morality is born of a repressed desire for revenge,
but that desire for revenge never completely disappears.
It's there, for example,
in the Christian idea of the last judgment.
No need to take revenge against the wicked, my sheep.
God will do that for us.
And in the meantime, being weak is good, actually.
I find this book thrilling to read, honestly,
and I'm not easily thrilled,
especially not by philosophers.
I think this book in particular gets me
because, especially if you were raised Christian,
this is so the opposite of everything
you were ever taught to believe
that it almost feels, like, dirty.
Should I be reading this?
Is this allowed?
Because even if you're not religious,
most of us still agree with a lot of Christian morality.
Like, yeah, Jesus was a good guy.
Blessed are the meek, sure.
But then Frederick comes along and he's like,
mm, morality is just a cope for frustrated vindictiveness.
And you're like, I need to lie down.
Where's my smelling salts?
But wait, there's more.
This gets even darker.
Nietzsche thinks that over the last two millennia
of European history, slave morality has triumphed.
St. Paul made Christianity marketable,
the Emperor Constantine converted,
and by the Middle Ages,
even kings and aristocrats were kneeling down
not to powerful warrior gods made in their own image,
but to a god that was weak,
suffering, victimized, oppressed.
So by the 19th century,
slave morality had become the only morality.
And it's not just Christianity, either.
The secular version of these values
became socialism, anarchism.
About free thinkers and atheists,
Nietzsche has this to say.
We loathe the church, not its poison.
Apart from the church, we too love the poison.
Okay, the poison.
What is the poison?
Well, Frederick thinks that resentment poisons the mind,
and turns humans against our own natural instincts.
Not just against aggression,
but against sexuality,
against ambition,
against power,
against life itself.
And there's two possible outcomes of this.
One is that resentment becomes a political movement,
the conspiracy of those who suffer,
the tyranny of the herd,
the revolution that eats itself.
Only we are good and just, is what they say.
As though health, success, strength, pride,
and the feeling of power were in themselves depravities
for which penance, bitter penance,
will one day be exacted.
Among them, we find plenty of vengeance seekers
disguised as judges,
with the word justice continually in their mouth
like poisonous spittle.
So you get the mentality of a hyper-moralistic resentment mob,
which I'm sure we're all familiar with.
The other outcome is that this moralism turns inward,
and attacks the individual conscience,
producing asceticism, self-denial, guilt.
Because slave morality condemns
not only the external beasts of prey who are oppressing us,
but also the beast of prey within,
our own animal instincts,
what Christianity calls sin.
So Frederick thinks that modern humans have become sick.
We hate ourselves, we hate our own nature,
we hate life itself.
I mean, is he wrong?
You see a girl boss winning,
I only see the will to power.
Frederick thinks of modern men as once-proud wildcats
who've become domesticated house pets,
at the cost of everything great in the human spirit.
That's very valid, Frederick.
That's super hecking valid.
So look, I've been pretty positive about Nietzsche so far,
but I do have a couple critiques I want to say.
One is that Frederick associating slave morality
with the Jews is very irresponsible.
Even though he didn't intend to be antisemitic,
and even though he was outspoken against antisemitism
in his own time,
when you keep referring to the Christian values
you're critiquing as Jewish hatred and Jewish revenge,
some people might get the wrong idea.
And some people did, Frederick.
Like your dumbass sister, Elizabeth Nietzsche,
who became a literal alternative ethno-identitarian.
God damn it, Liz.
Kind of goth goals, though.
Yes, that kind of goth.
You're right this time.
My other critique is that it doesn't seem to have occurred
to Frederick that genuinely caring about other people
is an option.
Like not because caring about other people
is repressing your true selfish nature,
but just because caring about other people
is part of your nature.
And isn't it?
Isn't caring about other people also in our nature?
I do think most of what Nietzsche says about resentment
accurately describes a very real thing.
But it's not the only thing.
There is genuine care and love in this world,
I've been told.
I've heard rumors.
And I'm even gonna go so far as to say
hashtag not all Christians.
Christ, I'm defending the Christians.
What is this channel coming to?
There are Christians, maybe not most,
but still some, for whom love and forgiveness
are genuine experiences,
and not just some kind of twisted,
impotent, passive-aggressive vengeance.
Where I agree with Nietzsche, and with Freud,
is I do think a lot of the emotional foundation
of justice and morality is retribution,
envy, or some combination of the two.
But maybe it doesn't have to be that way.
There's a famous Martin Luther King quote
responding to Nietzsche.
What is needed is a realization
that power without love is reckless and abusive,
and that love without power is sentimental and anemic.
Power at its best is love
implementing the demands of justice,
and justice at its best is love correcting everything
that stands against love.
So Reverend King concedes to Nietzsche
that to simply call power evil is a sickness, anemic.
But there still needs to be some kind of emotional
or spiritual force that keeps humanity
from tearing itself apart.
And maybe something like this Christian idea
of love for humanity is the missing piece.
Because without something like that,
I just see retribution and envy snowballing
into human self-destruction.
And I hate that for us.
It's not very sliving of us.
Do you guys know about sliving?
Do you even subscribe to Paris Hilton's YouTube channel?
She doesn't have as many subscribers as I do,
but you know, I try to support smaller creators.
Sliving is basically slaying and living your best life
into one word.
It's the new that's hot.
Maybe I'll do a video about love
when I'm in a better mood.
So for now, well, let's put it this way.
God is dead, and we have killed him, yeah?
Sliving!
Okay, I'm moisturized.
I'm primed.
I've proven my academic credentials.
Now it's time to do my makeup.
That's right, children.
I'm going full Bailey Sarian.
I'm going full suspish.
So I guess I should say something
about the political implications of all this,
since I guess this channel is about politics.
Sometimes I have to read my own Wikipedia article
to remember what I'm doing with my life.
So this morality of resentment,
of impotence, and permanently frustrated revenge
judges that power is evil.
I don't use foundation.
I just use concealer.
I know that's like not how you're supposed to do makeup,
but I don't need to be good at makeup, okay?
I have a million subscribers on YouTube.
I don't need to be good.
There was a New York Times article
about young women's attitudes toward political ambition,
and one of the women who was interviewed said,
as a white woman, I know I have unearned privilege.
So am I really the best person to be in leadership?
Uh, yes.
Yes, you are.
Because we need leaders like you
who are capable of questioning
the legitimacy of their own authority.
Otherwise, we're just gonna be stuck
with another blonde beast of prey.
And of course it's good to be aware of your privilege,
especially as a leader,
but let's not be so self-effacing
that we efface ourselves off the face of the earth.
This is the self-sabotage of resentment values.
If you think power is evil,
then you've given up on the ambition to acquire any power,
which virtually guarantees your political irrelevance,
since, like MLK said,
you have to at least have some power
to implement the demands of justice.
Remember what incels call taking the black pill,
this conviction that the reason you don't have a girlfriend
is just that you're genetically undesirable.
There's nothing you can do to change it,
and I guess women are just too shallow
to be attracted to all the amazing hatred and spite
that festers in your heart.
For a lot of black-pilled incels,
it seems like there's only one thing left in life
that they enjoy,
which is simply the pleasure of complaining,
of moaning in pain.
It reminds me of a comment from Dostoevsky's
second most horrible protagonist.
The moan is a protest against the meaninglessness of pain,
and part of the satisfaction of moaning
is inflicting your pain on other people.
This kind of malignant moaning,
it's kind of the opposite of music,
because a lot of music, like blues,
is benevolent moaning that transforms pain into pleasure.
I mean, that's what blues is all about.
My woman don't love me no more,
but I know her sister will.
You know, optimism.
I think a lot of incel discourse
is really just malignant moaning, right?
It's not an attempt to diagnose or solve any problem.
It's just a contagious expression of misery,
a moan of pain that masquerades as a political agenda.
Sexual Marxism, they call it.
The redistribution of sex.
State-mandated GFs.
That's very valid.
Of course, they don't actually expect any of this to happen.
That's not the point.
So incels are kind of a universal punching bag online.
It's very easy to point and laugh at them,
but what's harder is to look in the mirror
and notice how these exact same tendencies
are rampant in our own communities.
So the incel black pill is just one instance
of what I call an ideology of resentment,
a discourse that outwardly appears
like moral or political critique,
but which on examination is mainly just a resentful moan.
The goal of resentment politics
is not to improve conditions.
In fact, the resentful person is full of contempt
for any morally compromised sellouts
who are attempting to enact plausible reforms.
They don't want victory.
They don't want power.
They want to endlessly critique power.
Because for them, critique is an important
psychological defense against feeling impotent.
Schaler described it this way.
It is peculiar to resentment criticism
that it does not seriously desire
that its demands be fulfilled.
It does not want to cure the evil.
The evil is merely a pretext for the criticism.
What am I going to do with my eyes?
I think a pink kind of look.
We've been doing a lot of pink looks.
I just, I love that hay fever look.
As a general rule,
the more radical a political community claims to be,
the more likely it is to be a community of resentment.
Self-styled radicals will tell you
superficial surface reforms do not interest us.
The problem must be critiqued at its root.
And then the root turns out to be this universal,
all-encompassing evil, right?
Society itself.
The system.
The machine.
A resentment ideologue always imagines himself
to be engaged in a kind of satanic revolt
against an omnipotent, omnipresent enemy.
Okay, I just need to do makeup for a second.
It's harder than it looks to be a makeup vlogger.
It's hard to talk while doing this.
And nothing short of total revolution
counts as any sort of victory whatsoever.
We have to dismantle the entire system.
Burn it all down.
I guess it's pedestrian to point out
that this is the revolutionary utopian equivalent
of Christians awaiting the last judgment.
Our kingdom is coming, comrades.
Often the appeal of utopian ideology
is similar to religion.
It's not about healthcare, higher wages,
relief from police violence.
Those are actual goals that could be demanded,
worked for, and achieved.
Utopian ideology instead promises relief
from some general malaise, alienation.
And so ironically, it can have the same opiate effect
that Marx ascribes to religion.
But release from the general anguish of human existence
is not a political goal.
There's been many revolutions in the last few centuries,
and so far, zero utopias.
Resentment, envy, and hunger, for that matter,
are not satiated by the downfall of the old regime.
When the people have no bread, they eat the rich.
And when the rich are gone, they eat each other.
And because of the proximity effect,
envy may actually increase after the revolution.
You may actually be more envious of a favored comrade,
a successful citoyen, oui, a kulak,
than you ever were of the aristocrats.
So envy turns paranoid and imaginative
in revolutionary moments.
It gets sublimated into morality,
and the accusations start flying.
That citizen is conspiring against the revolution.
That peasant is hoarding grain.
So the guillotine starts slicing thousands of heads off,
the gulags fill up.
For an authoritarian, strongman takes over
just to announce another revolution two decades later.
The things people will do to stay relevant, honestly.
And for what?
What long-term egalitarian utopia results?
Socialism with Chinese characteristics?
So look, I do understand that sometimes
you just have to do a revolution.
And if I'd been there in 1789,
I'm sure I'd be storming the Bastille myself.
But I just wish we could stop being so doe-eyed about it.
Revolution is a bloody nightmare
that happens because society is collapsing
and people are desperate.
At worst, revolution is nothing more
than a violent day of retribution.
And at best, it lays the groundwork
for future incremental progress.
But it will never usher in utopia,
nor is it the antidote to a vague sense of unease,
which, I'm sorry to report,
is simply the resting state of an unsedated human mind.
Now I'm not saying, as some conservatives do,
that all leftist or all egalitarian politics
is born of envy.
No.
This is a specific subtype.
There are plenty of reasons,
other than envy or fear of envy,
to oppose an economic distribution
where some people have billions of dollars
while other people are dying
because they can't afford insulin.
Objectively, that is not an efficient use of resources
to promote human well-being.
And personally, I just don't want to live in a country
where people are dying because they can't afford medicine.
And I'm willing to pay however many taxes it takes
for that not to happen.
So while I'm putting down strawman versions of my argument,
I'm also not saying,
oh, let's just stop being envious.
No.
That's impossible.
I think envy is like libido.
It's a basic force of human nature
that's more or less unstoppable.
But with the right leadership,
I think that envy can potentially be sublimated
or redirected into something more constructive.
Because raw envy is a very bad basis
for egalitarian politics.
It often targets the wrong people,
like millionaires instead of billionaires,
and eventually it turns the revolution against itself
and you get the circular firing squad.
The self-cannibalism.
The problem I see on the left today
is that without any genuine political outlet,
resentment mostly manifests as morality.
Morality itself being a way to vent
envious aggression and vindictiveness.
On the left, we claim to be so impersonal, right?
We're all about structural analysis,
the material conditions,
systems of power,
intersectional identity hierarchies.
But if you look at what people
actually spend their time doing here,
it's all this obsessive moral policing.
I wonder if because leftists can't seem to win
on any major political stage,
we feel disempowered.
And so this moral fanaticism
is a psychological substitute.
Like with Marie Antoinette,
it's easier to blame people than systems.
Also, structural analysis is very boring,
and destroying people with gossip
is extremely entertaining.
This obsessive moral policing
also gets turned inward
and becomes leftist guilt.
You know, this useless internalized scolding.
I think I'm done with my makeup.
What do we think?
Leave a comment.
I'm always hesitant to do anything about skincare
since last time I did skincare,
I was critiqued by Hyram.
So I am going to spray my face a couple times
with this Tatcha skin mist,
if that's okay with Hyram.
It feels good to finally address this feud.
Clear the air.
I look a lot better with makeup.
I don't want to say that I don't have natural beauty,
it's just that it's very much enhanced
by painting a different face on top of my face.
But hey, at least this way I've kind of like,
I've kind of earned it, you know,
because it's my skill.
So there's a podcast called Guilty Feminist
that's been running for years,
and I haven't listened in a while,
but in the early episodes,
they'd bring on these women
who would confess their feminist sins.
You know,
hi, my name is Amber,
I'm a feminist,
but I enjoy being choked in bed.
It's hard being a woman.
Not only are you being choked,
you also feel guilty about it.
The same moral hand-wringing
happens with body positivity.
When you make loving your body
into a moral imperative,
not only are you still going to hate your body,
but now you're also going to feel guilty
about hating your body
because it makes you a bad feminist.
So there was one problem,
and now there's two problems.
Thanks, morality.
That's very helpful.
Now I want to take a moment to acknowledge
that a lot of conservatives have made some version
of the argument I'm making in this video.
For example,
Jordan Peterson and Camille Paglia
have argued that academic postmodernists
are motivated by resentment.
The argument is that
deconstructionist literary theory
is a kind of envious vengeance
against the beauty and virtuosity
of canonical great art.
And yeah, there's probably some truth to that.
A lot of academics are failed artists,
but I was even more manqu than that.
I've noticed that working class,
non-academic socialists
do tend to be more productive
and more self-advancing,
involved in unionizing or organizing.
Whereas, it's usually people who went to college.
I went to college!
Presumably because they had
middle-class ambitions at some point,
but whose middle-class ambitions have failed,
who become the great critiquers of capital.
I mean, I can tell you from experience
that when I was eating Chef Boyardee
over my master's degree,
that's when I was most likely to say things like,
according to Antonio Gramsci,
in the logic of late-stage capitalism,
the culturally hegemonic neoliberal ideology
manufactures the consent of the civil term.
Uh, so point taken.
But some conservatives take this argument way too far,
and try to argue that the entire left
is nothing but a coalition of resentment.
Like, there's a video on YouTube
of the philosophy professor Stephen Hicks
doing a version of the post-modernism
is resentment argument,
and in the comments section,
there's a bunch of people saying,
this describes Black Lives Matter,
Antifa, and the Democrats.
Does it, though?
I mean, any political movement
is gonna have people in it
who suffer from resentment poisoning.
But Black Lives Matter, at its core,
is about the right not to be murdered by police.
The slogan, Black Lives Matter,
is an affirmation of the value of black life.
So that seems like something even Nietzsche would approve of.
Huey Newton, the co-founder of the Black Panther Party,
was inspired by Nietzsche
to create the slogan All Power to the People.
When we coined the expression All Power to the People,
we had in mind emphasizing the word power,
for we recognize that the will to power
is the basic drive of man,
but it is incorrect to seek power over people.
We have been subjugated to the dehumanizing power
of exploitation and racism for hundreds of years,
and the black community has its will to power also.
What we seek, however, is not power over people,
but the power of control of our own destiny.
That, to me, is a role model
for how to do identity politics
without centering resentment.
It's instead an affirmation of self-determination
and self-respect.
Like Nietzsche would say, it's saying yes to yourself.
Whereas if your whole political project
is defined in the negative,
then you're allowing yourself
to be defined by your enemies.
I find feminism is prone to this,
where even, and in fact especially,
the most radical feminists
cannot seem to escape this resentful consciousness
of being the second sex
and defining themselves against men.
Earlier I mentioned Andrea Dworkin in a positive way.
She's the most radical of radical feminists,
and my first impulse is actually to defend her
because she's very widely hated,
and most of the people who hate her hate a caricature.
Like in that Stephen Hicks video,
Hicks summarizes Dworkin as
calling all heterosexual males rapists.
Literally in the preface to her most famous book,
Dworkin says,
If one's sexual experience has always,
and without exception, been based on dominance,
how could one understand that this book
does not say that all men are rapists
or that all intercourse is rape?
Listen, Hicks, I get that you're a full professor
and I'm just a makeup vlogger,
but my gut feeling on this one is,
before criticizing a book,
maybe read the book.
Just a thought.
Get it together, prof.
You're being owned online by a makeup vlogger.
I mean, there's no shame in that.
It happens to me all the time.
That being said,
I do think that Hicks is coincidentally correct
that Dworkin is a theorist of resentment.
What Dworkin does say in this book
is arguably even more bleak
than what is falsely attributed to her.
The book is called Intercourse.
She wrote a book called Intercourse.
Imagine writing a book called Intercourse.
I can actually easily imagine that.
Never mind.
So this is an argument about the meaning of sex.
Penetration, to be specific.
Dworkin argues that penetration expresses domination,
invasion, occupation, possession, contempt, degradation.
So it's against the Freudian
male castration anxiety interpretation,
where it's a fear of being devoured by the woman.
Imagine being afraid of that.
I'm gonna get a facelift someday
and I'm gonna look like this.
I'm perfect.
I certainly don't agree with everything she says,
but isn't Dworkin closer to the truth here?
Closer than Freud, anyway.
Think about what men typically say to women during the act.
Do they say,
Hell, I'm being devoured.
Never heard that one.
Have you?
No, usually it's more along the lines of,
You like that, don't you?
You little.
Et cetera.
And of course, you can eroticize being subjugated and degraded and enjoy it.
And I think Dworkin would argue that most women do eroticize subjugation
because they're taught to.
But enjoying it, she'd have to say,
doesn't change the meaning of what's happening.
So I think Dworkin says some things that are very true
and some things that are off the fucking rails.
Where she loses me is where she starts getting blackpilled.
And this book, this is the feminist blackpill.
It is 250 pages of hopeless misery and rage.
She says,
Male-dominant gender hierarchy seems immune to reform.
This may be because intercourse itself is immune to reform.
Uh, okay.
So women will never be free until men stop putting the P in the V.
We can dream, Andrea.
We can dream.
Like most ideology of resentment,
this book is totally dismissive of any plausible reforms
that might actually improve the situation of women.
Instead, preferring to wallow in the endless violence,
filth, and abjection of it all.
I also think it's symptomatic that Dworkin identifies as a lesbian,
but in that second wave political way.
Quoting from the foreword,
To Dworkin, it was a badge of rebellion against the patriarchy.
In 30 plus years of knowing her,
I've never heard of a single romance with a woman, not one.
This is not surprising to me from the author of a 250 page book about sex
that not once pauses to even imagine the possibility of intimacy between women.
Because it's not a lesbianism that's about saying yes to women,
it's a lesbianism that's about saying no to men.
You know, people think that lesbians are the biggest man-haters,
but I don't think that's true.
I think lesbians just don't think about men that much.
The only men I think about are Fred Nietzsche and, uh, Oedipus the King.
It's straight women who are usually the real man-haters,
because they're stuck with this,
and love is closer to hatred than neutrality.
So what does Andrea Dworkin actually want?
What would she say yes to if she said yes to anything?
Sometimes women have trouble saying what they want,
because no one ever told them they could.
Romance.
That's what Joan Didion said is the real desire of the women's movement.
Joan Didion, of course, being not like other girls.
Dworkin offers occasional glimpses of a positive desire.
Despite all efforts to socialize women to want intercourse,
women still want a more diffuse and tender sensuality
that involves the whole body in a polymorphous tenderness.
That does sound nice.
I'm so lonely.
I think it's a bit bold to speak for all women, though.
Like, there are definitely women out there who, uh,
they don't make love, Anastasia.
They f*** hard.
I'm really sleepy, and this bed right behind me just looks so nice.
I can't in here right now.
What if I just go to sleep, and then wake up,
and then just record the rest of the video when I wake up.
I don't want to do it now.
I'll get Pikachu, that'll make this easier.
Isn't it better for me to have a friend?
Pikachu is the most adorable Pokemon.
Why?
Because he's the yellowest.
Name one thing more yellow than Pikachu.
You can't name anything.
You can't think of anything.
So if diffuse and tender sensuality is what you want,
then just say that.
Is that what you want, Pikachu?
I bet it is.
And Dworkin did get married.
To a gay man.
So I guess she found what she wanted.
Lucky.
Envying Andrea Dworkin.
Is that really what we've sunk to around here?
You know, I've been noticing the poison creeping into my mind lately.
I know this isn't very original, but I had a bad year.
You know, I fell in love with my best friend like a gay idiot,
got my heart comprehensively broken,
and then COVID hit and gave me a year of solitude to
spiral deeper into a hell of my own making.
You know, I stopped saying yes to life,
and I started saying yes to chasing the dragon.
By which I mean playing Spyro the Dragon,
one of the greatest appropriate-for-all-ages video games of all time.
Look at him go!
I'm taking the hair clips out.
I catch myself having bitter spinster thoughts.
It's because I'm trans.
It's because I'm gay.
That's why I'll die alone.
Yeah, that's the reason I'm alone.
Definitely not because I don't leave the house.
See, I am not immune to incel-tier brain poisoning,
and you really can use political theorizing as an excuse not to fix your life.
Society did this to me.
A transphobic society made me hate myself.
Well, yeah, that's true.
But at a certain point, you have to take responsibility for your own mind,
and decide to stop being an accomplice in your own annihilation.
Since we keep referencing Paradise Lost,
the mind is its own place,
and in itself can make a heaven of hell a hell of heaven.
Yes, squad.
So I ask myself, what kind of mind do I want to be?
Do I want to obsess over what I lack,
concede society's judgment of my inferiority,
become a self-hating, self-pitying, envious, resentful little nothing?
Or do I want to get off the goddamn floor,
stop chasing the dragon, and say yes to life?
The answer, of course, is that I long to return to the sweet womb of my dark mother.
But we're not gonna do that,
because there's plenty of time to numb the pain after you die.
The sweet embrace of death is the darkest mother of all.
Also, nothing is less attractive than an envious, resentful, self-pitying person.
It's beyond a personality flaw,
it's a personality deformity that can ruin whatever chance at happiness you have.
So in the short time that you're alive,
you have to discover that which is noble in yourself, and say yes to it.
You know, don't say no to getting older, say yes to being a MILF.
Yes, yes.
What I'm really trying to say here is,
Spongebob Squarepants is the Ubermensch.
Spongebob says yes to life, and so should we.
Yes to ourselves.
Yes to art.
Yes to sensuality.
Yes to the world.
Yes.
Eh, we.
Is this really how we're ending the video?
I guess.
Okay, bye!
Oh, so what if my fantasies make no sense?
You wanna talk about things that don't make sense?
Heterosexuality.
Let's put that under the microscope, hmm?
You want me to believe that a straight woman,
who knows the difference between magenta and mauve,
is gonna date a straight man who thinks it's gay to wash his underwear,
and that's just gonna work out fine.
You think it's safe to raise a child in that environment?
I don't think so.
Not on my watch.
See, I think straight men should date each other.
They can sit on the couch all day playing Xbox and then f*** each other.
And then straight women can pair off,
decoupage some shit,
and eat each other out.
Isn't that better?
Isn't that more rational?
I wish I could wiggle these cat ears.
Like, I wish I had anatomical control over them.
Hello?
Yes, Dr. Spiegel?
Yes, it's me again.
I have a suggestion.
What do we even have here?
We've got tuna, salmon, some squid, mackerel, shrimp,
some, I think it's yellowtail, clam, some rolls.
I've never been as much into rolls.
I'm a cat, you know I like fish.
You start adding too much avocado and rice into things.
It's an affront to my feline nature.
So
Doctor, I think if a breeze comes into the window, I could die.