Aren't you happy Game of Thrones is back?
Yay!
I thought us up a George RR Martini.
It involves fire and- No.
Fire.
No.
According to my Game of Thrones house things, I should be Tyrell.
This is- Oh god, I can smell it from here.
This is sriracha, because all my house quizzes tell me I'm a Targaryen, so cheers!
Just wait until I make a, you know, fire gun.
Oh, I will hate that.
You know how I hate tasty things.
So before we talk about Cinder, let's talk about some of the ideas people threw at us
regarding Arisen, and the dystopia discussion that we had last week.
While we were kind of poo-pooing dystopia as an idea for the sequel, Emily Hopkins suggested
that it would be like New Moon meets dystopia, Riley leaves her and it's like the end of
the world, and then it is literally the end of the world, but she's too depressed to even
care or notice.
Hey, that would definitely- And then like, you know, because our idea was instead of
like in New Moon where it's like November, it was just going to be ellipses for like
45 minutes, and then at the end of it there's like a totalitarian government.
We were fitted for our uniforms today, but I don't care.
Guest said, remember when a matriarchal society in a sci-fi post-apocalyptic setting was written
as if it was mind-blowing and terrifying?
Would Sarah Ellenson accidentally write something like that?
I think she would.
I think she would, yeah.
In fact, I think that's how we bring Scarlett back into this.
Yeah, she's like the leader of the matriarchy.
And all the women are scorned.
Everyone's scorned.
It's like they scorned us so we will destroy them.
So they just have their meetings.
They never talk about their scorn, and they were like, we will have revenge.
Oh, one of my favorite was- I didn't write this one down.
Whoever said this.
I think we finally had a winner in the race to complete Arisen.
Oh yeah.
And that was simply another.
We need it.
I like this title, another.
I was like, another.
So I feel like, you know, we want to take it in a funnier direction and more, yeah.
And so I think, rather than Arisen, which I think a YA book would actually be called,
I like another.
Yeah.
Lauren Kate suggests that book two, there tends to be a big undercurrent in YA these
days, to borrow the idea from the Lego movie of this special.
I think we could play that up.
Although that was definitely there in the first one.
I haven't seen the Lego movie yet.
Don't talk to me.
Lauren Kate's also said that, you know, even the worst of YA dystopias are at least, you
know, a little bit of a metaphor, which, you know, Divergent isn't really.
And they might be paper thin and obvious, but, you know, it's there.
And Sarah doesn't exactly get layers.
So if you're going to do dystopia, whatever would normally be presented as a metaphor
needs to be, like, 100% on the nose.
I wonder what that could be, though.
So they take their guns away or something.
No, like there's a health care system called Shmo-shmama-shmare.
And they're like, no, but I want to visit my doctor.
They raise the minimum wage.
No!
And the moochers, like, crawl out.
They're like the Morlocks.
Review in time.
We decided next week we're going to go with Miss Peregrine's Home for Peculiar Children
based on popularity of suggestion.
Before we start talking about Cinder, so we're going to do this one in two weeks.
So we have two weeks to read it.
Another library copy.
Thank you, Queens Library.
You are awesome.
We picked this one because we presumed it wasn't focused on romance.
We could be wrong.
Yeah.
For the next one, I say give us something adult, reasonably popular,
within the last five years, little or no romance.
So we can focus less on romance, even though that is relevant to our Cthulhu love.
We still have to read that Ypres love.
Yeah, at some point we've got to read Ypres love.
Or just keep pushing up.
Yeah, it was like next year.
Cinder, speaking of romance, the Cyborg Cinderella retelling for our modern age by Marissa Meyer.
We read that, and it did indeed have a cyborg foot.
Yes.
Nella, what did you think of Cinder?
Reading Cinder, I was struck by how well the plot moved along.
It definitely kept up its pace and definitely got straight to the cliffhanger ending.
It was a snappy one.
It's a series.
But yeah, it was very snappy.
I did really like the main character.
You know, with Cinderella stories, yes, we want to see her go to the ball.
We want to see her be triumphant.
This definitely took that and didn't want to do that.
I mean, it hit the ball thing.
It hit some of the things you consider vital to a Cinderella story.
It hit the class thing.
But those were just the background noise of what this book is actually about,
which is...
Revolution.
Imagine that.
And, you know, a tyrant.
Yeah.
Invasion.
The tyrant is basically a completely unironic version of Scarlet.
I know.
She has auburn hair and everything.
She's like walking all sexy.
Like the evil queen.
Well, it's funny because she shows up and everyone's like,
Oh, the evil queen is here.
I know.
That's the thing.
It's like not even at some point is someone like,
Oh, she's not that bad.
No, everyone's like,
Well, the evil queen's in town.
She sure is evil.
She mind controlling, baby killing.
Yep.
Kills babies.
Evil queen.
Boy, she's evil.
Doesn't like mirrors.
Sure is hot.
Oh, boy, she hot.
That's the worst thing about the evil queen.
She might look pretty, but the truth is she ugly.
Oh, she ugly.
She ugly.
That's the worst thing a woman can be.
She shows up and she's all like,
That's what she's hiding under the veil she always wears.
Her mustache.
That she's true.
That's half the book read like,
And everyone's like,
God, she's evil.
But talking about evil characters, there's another character.
There's a doctor character who shows up and you think,
Oh, now Cinder's going to get it.
Like, this guy is no good.
He seems to have an obsession with young girls.
Literally.
Literally a thing about young girls.
And it's super creepy.
Well, he's kind of set up like this Dr. Mingel,
like doing literal, literal Auschwitz experiments on cyborgs.
But no, then he turns out to be an ally.
And we never go back to examine,
so 27 cyborgs have died by your hand.
He's a Dr. Fungal.
It is just completely accepted in this universe
that cyborgs are second class citizens.
And it is never explained.
They're just like, they're people.
They're humans that have like, you know, artificial hearts
or, you know, bionic arms or whatever.
Or there's the one guy that gets listed as a cyborg
who's just missing a foot.
Yeah.
He's got like a peg leg that happens to have like a little robot.
I want to know what happened in this world
to turn people so against prosthetics.
Yeah.
I mean, if you get a titanium hip replacement,
does that make you count as a cyborg now?
Yeah, this world is incredibly...
Was there the cyborg wars?
Yeah, was that World War IV that they mentioned?
This world is incredibly ableist.
I mean, is it like Star Trek where like,
oh no, not eugenics, the eugenics war.
But they never mention it.
Okay, granted, this is book one of three,
so maybe it gets mentioned.
But as it is, it's never even alluded to
why cyborgs are so shat upon.
They're like, basically, literally slaves.
Like, can be owned and sold for no reason
other than they have prosthetic foot.
Which of course is our Cinderella thing.
Her foot comes off.
Which I thought was clever.
I feel like, it depends on what you like.
It felt on the younger end of YA to me.
Because it was A, really short.
Compared to something like
Daughter of Smoke and Bone series,
or even Twilight, or The Fifth Wave.
It was really short and super predictable.
Like, the twist at the end is like,
it was so obvious, it's like, it can't be that.
It's gonna be a bait and switch.
It has to be a bait and switch.
No, I knew it was gonna be that.
No, it wasn't.
The characters are not super deep,
but it was like, all concept.
But the concept I thought worked.
But it was fun.
Yeah, it was fun.
It was a fun concept.
And I would definitely wanna read the next three books.
Yeah, no, I'm on board.
I'm like, I wanna see what happens to Cinder.
Yeah.
I wanna find out about the lunar...
So there's a nation on the moon
that's been there for hundreds of years
and supposedly they're really wealthy
and self-sustainable on the moon.
I really wanna know how that happened.
I hope they go into that.
I do.
Because I'm kinda like,
Mars has the ice cap?
Yeah.
The moon's got a whole lot of nothing.
So anyway, Marissa Meyer,
someone in the comments pointed out
that she was apparently a former fan fiction author.
Which is apparently for like,
Sailor Moon, which I think
really makes a lot of sense
considering the four books.
It's like, Sailor Cinder.
Sailor Scarlet.
Sailor Winter.
I mean, this isn't like Fifty Shades of Grey
where it's just like, I'm taking my, you know...
No, this is an example of someone
who wrote fan fiction who did a good job with it.
Well, I mean, I think it's like
she took the things she liked about the fandom
that she was in and reapplied it
to a completely different thing.
Which I can totally dig.
I really, I can't express how little
I cared about the romance and also didn't buy it.
Well, also, I just really felt like
they both just needed a puppy.
There are so many larger things at stake
and she keeps going,
he's not gonna like me.
And I get that that's the thing
that teenagers will relate to,
does he like me?
Yeah.
But in this case, I didn't buy it
because the stakes were so high.
It's like, get your shit together.
Yeah.
Come on, focus.
I realize you're 16,
but you're framed as smarter than that.
Yeah.
Someone in the comments asked
if there is a Tiger's Curse comparison
because this does take place in New Beijing,
which is like a thousand-ish years
in the future or something.
No.
Because Tiger's Curse at least tries
to incorporate the culture.
This one does not at all.
Someone alluded to,
someone's wearing a kimono
or maybe there's a Buddha in the corner
or something,
but it really has fuck all to do with China.
Yeah.
And it's very much about a,
all the continents have pretty much
been divvied up into commonwealths.
Europe is Europe.
Africa is United Africa or something.
South America has apparently been
bombed into obliteration.
Yeah.
Because they're never,
Australia is still its own thing.
Hey, well.
But it was a part of an interesting point.
I wanted to bring this one up.
This is called The Summer Prince,
which is a considerably less well-known YA book.
This one is on the much, much more adult,
like older YA.
It's a lot more heady.
It's a lot more conceptual.
It's a lot more sci-fi.
This one takes place in a science fiction future Brazil.
But I wanted to bring this one up
because it definitely brings in the culture
and applies it to this potential future.
It is very grounded in the culture of Brazil.
And honestly, I feel like,
this is YA technically,
but I feel like it would appeal more to adults
than teenagers because it is not very,
does he like me?
It's very the opposite of that.
Well, at least Cinder.
I mean, because it's implied like,
she's from Europe.
Yeah, Cinder's kind of implied white.
Yeah.
It's kind of a shame.
She never explicitly said white,
but she's like,
are you from Europe?
Like, who?
All right, so that's Cinder.
Great if you like concept and fast, snappy reads.
Yeah.
And just, you know, a fun and easy thing.
I mean, we're coming into summer,
so definitely I'd say it's a beach book.
Yeah, this is a beach book.
Definitely.
Kill it two, three hours.
Two weeks from now, this one,
made into a movie by Tim Burton.
Really?
I don't know how I feel about that.
Well, I won't know how I feel about that
until I read it.
Well, I guess I have to drink this, don't I?
Yep.
Look, well,
you can take a, like, shot.
I'm just gonna smell.
I do not like sriracha.
You don't like sriracha?
I must be the only asshole in this entire
fucking city that doesn't like sriracha.
Sriracha's, like,
life.
Fire and blood.
Yep, that's, um,
it's a cocktail.
It's good.
Honest.
I just, I don't like spicy.
Mmm-mmm!
Lindsay.
Well, Nella doesn't get to do her rose thing next week,
so, give us something.
You mixologists in there,
and then we'll do it next,
in two weeks from now.
Even if it has something peculiar about it.
Something, something peculiar.
Give us something peculiar.
We'll tie it into this.
Oh right, Goodreads.
Be our friend on Goodreads.
Yeah.
Shayapocalypse?
Uh, yeah.
Goodreads.com slash shayapocalypse.
Be our friend.
You can comment.
We can talk.
I log in sometimes,
and it logs me out of my Facebook.
Pain in the ass.
It is.
It totally is.
While we will read this in two weeks,
we will be back next week
to talk explicitly about another slash Arisen.
Because we really need to start writing that.
Yeah.
Here, you can have this one.
Oh.
Bye.