In and out. In and out. Staying alive is about doing things. This very second, your cells are
combusting glucose molecules with oxygen to make energy available, which keeps you alive for another
precious moment. To get the oxygen to your cells, you're breathing. Breathing is an answer to a very
hard problem. How do you get the resources that your cells need to survive from the outside to
the inside of your cells? Every living thing has to solve this problem, and the solution is
surprisingly different depending on one of the most important regulators of life, size. As we've
discussed in other videos, at different scales, the physical laws of the universe have different
consequences for its inhabitants. Simple things like temperature, microgravity, or surface tension
might not matter to you or be a deadly danger, depending on how big you are. Living things need
a lot of different materials to keep themselves going, and they somehow need to transport them
from the outside to the inside. This was a huge problem for the first things on the verge of being
alive, because doing anything in our universe requires energy, and the first living beings on
Earth did not have the abundance of tools and techniques available that life has today after
billions of years of evolution. So at the very beginning, life needed to find a way to get good
stuff inside and bad stuff outside of itself without using energy. Luckily, the very first
forms of life were very, very small. And because they were so small, they were able to use a free
form of transport that was based on a physical law called diffusion. Diffusion is the rule of
the universe that molecules, especially in liquids or gases, are constantly moving around in all
directions. And because they move around and bump into each other and other molecules, they tend to
spread. For example, if you drop a sugar cube into water, then there is a lot of sugar in one place,
and in another place, there's none. As sugar molecules dissolve in the water, they will start
randomly bumping against the water molecules and other sugar molecules. Slowly, all the sugar
molecules will spread out and form multiple phases of different concentrations. These random movements
continue endlessly until at some point, the sugar will be spread evenly in the water. The great thing
about diffusion is that life can use it for free. It doesn't require energy. And life loves free
things. So all life on Earth relies on diffusion. Let's look at the smallest living being on Earth,
a bacterium, specifically its surfaces. Cell membranes allow for diffusion of certain molecules.
This specific bacterium consumes oxygen to live while carbon dioxide is produced inside as a waste
product. So inside the bacterium, there isn't a lot of oxygen, but a lot of carbon dioxide. Because
of diffusion, these molecules will eventually spread evenly, so the carbon dioxide diffuses
out while oxygen is constantly replenished from the outside. But this kind of breathing only works
for the very small world, for bacteria, amoeba or your cells, and a few very small animals. Insects,
for example, have a fine network of trachea, tunnels with a pressure gradient where air very
slowly can diffuse in and exchange gases with the insect cells. But even insects seem to be able to
contract their trachea, and at least some even have specialized breathing organs like spiracles
and air sacs. At certain scales, diffusion is just too slow to keep cells alive. The fundamental
problem is that the exchange with the environment can only happen at the surface, and diffusion of
materials can only sustain a certain amount of inside. Tiny living things have only a little bit
of inside or volume, and a lot of outside or surface area. But what if we wanted to create
a bacteria the size of a blue whale and had a very convenient enlargement machine? We would sadly be
messed up by the square cube law. In a nutshell, it means that if you make something 10 times
larger, its outside or surface would grow by 100, but its insides or volume grows by 1000 times.
If we compare the bacterium Pseudomonas aeruginosa with a blue whale, we see that the bacterium has
10 million times more surface in relation to its volume than the whale. The bacterium has a lot of
outsides, while the whale has a lot of insides. If we make a bacterium the size of a whale,
our giant bacteria now has too much insides, and most of its inside is now very far from its
surface. The oxygen our bacterium needs would never reach the inside before it would run out
of oxygen. Our giant bacterium would just die. Still, being bigger has many upsides. From making
it harder to be eaten, to making it easier to eat others. But the size of cells is limited by the
distance oxygen and nutrients can effectively diffuse to provide the inside with enough
resources. So life avoided this problem by forming multicellular structures. Beings composed of many
cells instead of one, because diffusion works better if you have many small units instead of
one much bigger one. Over time, the cell buddies began to share work and specialize. Some cells
concentrated on sensing the environment, others on digestion, others on movement. But that still
wasn't enough. The problem of diffusion and surface and energy production remained, limiting
the size these first multicellular forms of life could attain. So in order to become even bigger,
life solved the diffusion problem by having holes and caves and tunnels and by folding in on itself,
so diffusion could happen easily in each one of the cells. Take yourself. What you consider your
outside, your skin, has a surface area of about two square meters. But your lungs have a surface
area of about 70 square meters. They aren't like balloons. They're more like sponges filled with
many tightly packed tiny balloons surrounded by blood vessels. When you breathe in, all these tiny
balloons fill up with fresh air. Blood filled up with CO2 is pumped around the balloons. And then,
the magic of diffusion happens. The oxygen diffuses into the blood where it's picked up by red blood
cells. And the CO2 diffuses out of the blood and into your lungs where it can be breathed out again.
Your blood then carries oxygen rich blood into the furthest corners of your body and picks up
the CO2 waste. Diffusion in the body is effective at about one millimeter. So every cell in your
body is at most one millimeter away from a blood vessel. So medium sized animals like you need a
lot of blood vessels to reach every cell in the body. Your body has around 100,000 kilometers of
capillaries alone, the tiniest of your blood vessels with a surface area of around 1000 square
meters. This is true for all parts of you that want to exchange something with the outside world.
Your body needs surfaces to take in nutrients from your food. So your gut has the surface area of half
a badminton court, roughly 40 square meters. The larger you are, the more hidden surfaces you need.
Take a tree. Its way to stay alive is to create sugar out of thin air and sunlight. So it needs
as much surface area as possible. An orange tree with 2000 leaves has a leaf surface area of 200
square meters. But the surface inside the leaves where diffusion actually occurs is 6000 square
meters. The same with roots where water diffuses from the soil into countless tiny hairs that
maximize the surface area. The roots of one square meter of grass add up to around 350 square meters
of surface. If we look at the breathtaking diversity of life on this planet, it seems like
everything is pretty different. And it is. But some basic principles are the same for everybody
and have not changed significantly for billions of years. If we look at the very, very small or the
very, very big waste goes out and fresh fuel comes in. Big animals just need a lot of complex
plumbing to make it possible. Fresh fuel is something we can all use from time to time,
especially for our creativity. All it really takes is to try something new. And we have the
perfect opportunity to get you started. We partnered with Skillshare, an online learning
community that offers courses on almost any creative skill, such as design, illustration,
animation, photography, and cooking. They have 1000s of courses starting from every level. So
wherever you are right now, there'll be something for you. Maybe you want to look behind the scenes
of our animations. For example, we've made a couple of Skillshare classes that teach you how
we animated scenes from our videos with video lessons, classes, and hands on projects. Or if
you'd rather look into illustration first, we recommend Adobe Illustrator, level up your colors
by Hayden Obey. But what you pick first doesn't really matter that much. The important part is to
get started, have some fun and get new inspiration. Unlimited access to all classes is only $10 a
month with an annual premium membership. And the first 1000 kurzgesagt viewers to click the link
in the description, get a special treat, you'll get a free trial of Skillshare premium. If you
want to break out of your rut by exploring a new skill and support kurzgesagt, give it a try.
And we have something else to make your learning experience truly perfect. Our new Ocean Explorer
notebook. It has beautiful sparkly four lettering and four illustrated infographic pages inside,
taking you on a journey under the sea. The perfect companion for all your note taking needs.
Designed and produced with love by the kurzgesagt merch burbs. Thank you for watching.
Transcribed by https://otter.ai