Okay, so today we are drinking around the world at Epcot.
Because Epcot has roughly 12 countries.
It's like 11.
11.
The challenge is, there's 11 countries and you have to drink a thing from each of them.
My budget is $100. Can it be done?
Is it good?
You think you're an adult with a job, and a dog, and planning a wedding,
and then the next thing you know you aren't dressed up like Quasimodo.
Because you're like, hey, wouldn't it be fun to get drunk?
It's getting late.
So what have we got?
I got a jalapeno margarita.
I got some root beer with sugar on it.
I got the beet margarita.
Some kind of huevo thing.
I'm Penny Frenzel.
And this is your guide to drinking at the cheapest Disney World.
Okay, so Nella and Michael finally showed up.
They will get their drink and we can finally move on to the rest of the world.
Alright.
I got the minty pineapple margarita.
And I got the male shrimp margarita.
And it is good. It's very pineapple-y.
Woo!
Not very minty.
Aquavit here in Norway.
Black licorice flavored liquor that tastes like it's been sitting in a sink.
Normally I'd be here for this, but I'm totally not here for this.
When you make an alcohol entirely based on licorice?
Like, I just...
I'll do it. I'll soldier through.
Okay, so I got this Dragon Pearl.
Which, I don't know if you get what's in it.
But there's at least beer and honey and tapioca.
Which I think is a very Chinese flavor combination.
So I'm gonna see what this is all about.
Oh no.
Oh man, that's weird.
It's a texture thing.
Look at that, look at that.
See that? Tapioca, alcohol, tapioca, alcohol, tapioca.
I'm gonna...
Yeah, it's Capri Sun.
It's Capri Sun with alcohol.
Am I wrong?
No, my god. It tastes like fifth grade.
Wow.
Wow, it is Capri Sun.
It even has the same kick.
I feel like this is how you get kids drinking at an early age.
You just slip this in.
Yeah, and then...
Versus the Capri Sun plum wine.
Next thing you know, they're on gin.
How do you feel right now?
This is me.
Hit me.
Hi!
I've got some serious bloating issues.
Oh, me too.
You've got the hydrocephalus.
No, I've just been traveling and I've got a slight constipation.
I got the Francis Conner German beer, which was only $6.50.
So, a deal.
And it's quite delightful, too.
The Erdinger.
It's this very nice malty German beer.
No one hops, high in body, dark, and filling.
If I may directly refer to it, it's a very important duck.
I said it's an important duck.
Very important duck.
For $9, the wine cellar in the Germany Pavilion is the best value.
You can get a glass of wine for $6.
Okay, let's look at this.
We got it from Norma.
It's very good.
That's a nice one.
Post.
We need to get post.
Yeah.
So, I have gotten the All Bubbles All the Time,
which is a three variety flight of sparkling white wine.
In the words of Betty Murphy, to paraphrase,
my girl likes to party all the time.
My girl likes to All Bubbles All the Time.
I only feel a little sick.
I like that these are sweet.
They will make me feel less pukey than I already do.
What would you consider your drunkenness level?
I'm a very pleasant 5.
So, I feel like if 1 is nothing and 10 is blacking out,
I'd say I'm at about 6.
I'm at about 5.
I'm 6, pushing 7.
Here's where we're at.
The New York primary just happened and no one's brought up politics,
so I think we're doing pretty well.
Yes, exactly.
I think America might be the worst one.
There is acapella California dreaming.
Welcome to the Great American Experience.
We're in America, which is totally different from the place where we normally are.
I was going to be brave and get a Jack Daniels cherry slushy,
but I wussied out and got a California thing.
I'm going to be brave.
Mmm, that tastes like happy hour white.
I got a wonderful maple bacon stout.
Oh, you got the maple bacon stout.
It's for science.
It's half for science and it's half for me.
They're two things I really love.
I got the three daughters Ron Fender red ale.
I love a red ale.
It's a little weak, but still really smooth and lovely.
Although, it also got me to level 33 and untapped for Land of the Free.
I love my American Pie.
I did the American Pie.
I just paid $8 for a glass of Sutter Home.
$8 for a glass of Sutter Home.
God damn it.
I did it.
I took it like a shot.
I am well past the forgetting things phase.
I am aware, but I'm a traditionalist, so I have some hot sake right here.
I got a Tokyo Sazen.
It's like a screwdriver but with sake, I think.
It's very astringent.
There's a lot of vinegarness to it.
I have to finish this apparently.
It's great. I love it.
Kawaii moto pro.
I need to capture this thing that I'm feeling,
which is that simply I would be enjoying the shit out of this
if it was the first thing I had.
Because it is like fundamentally delicious,
but right now it feels like a chore.
I am not going to puke.
Oh God, it's raining and we have like, I don't know,
between 5 and 20 left.
Morocco, Canada, France, question mark.
We got this. We got this.
I'm not going to puke.
Okay, we are in Morocco.
You know, that land of traditional,
alcoholic spirits.
And I've lost everyone else.
At least the ones that are not holding the camera.
And what have we got?
This is the coffee plus.
I'm trying to catch a little bit.
That tastes like a thing that should not be mixed with liquor.
So there was rain and the outdoor pavilion
for the special thing going on in Epcot was closed.
So I got a normal wine at Morocco,
but it's open again because the rain has passed.
And they have a sparkling white wine
with pomegranate liqueur on top and I want it.
And I am doing it.
Two drinks, one country.
Right now I have a red wine sangria,
which is a red wine,
typically a full-bodied, kind of chewy kind of wine,
which has been marinated in fruit or vice versa.
I've got mine.
Oh, goodness.
We did it.
We did two drinks, one country.
But it's a really delightful, dry,
with a hint of pomegranate and sweetness,
but still really drinkable, really delightful.
I'm enjoying it.
This belongs in a brunch.
Dutch angle.
It wants to be brunch.
I had a sip and it was so much better
than the mistake I made in the form of coffee.
I mean, the thing is,
if you spend money on a drink in Epcot,
I feel like you're not really disappointed.
You're a monster.
Wait, say, I'm a monster.
I'm a monster, you know.
You are deformed.
And you are ugly.
I learned that you can trust in this whole Epcot.
You're my only friend.
I am your one defender.
Rum marie slushie.
Oh, God, it tastes like a dreamsicle.
Singing the song of angry men.
It is the music of a people
who will not be slaves again.
Somewhere beyond the man.
The 737 is the USS Kentucky.
So, if anyone watches this
and is currently serving on
or has served on
the USS Kentucky,
f*** you.
Beyond the barricade
is there a world you long to see?
You know,
but f*** you.
Well, where were you?
I was on the USS Kentucky.
Oh, okay, so that makes it okay.
The joy and the fright
that we give
is the right to be free.
God, this is awful.
Bad life decision.
I'm not angry,
but I'm quasi-nervous.
My sandwiches are awful.
I have not gone beyond
the tower.
Is this what alcohol tastes like?
Yeah, I was like, I brought you grapes
and you were like, oh.
I've been locked in a place for 20 years.
Wow, you found a way to make ice crystals?
That's amazing.
This is the worst thing in Epcot.
I've become deaf.
So now I have this from Florida
and this from France.
Two F's.
This would have failed me in school.
My parents would have been very disappointed.
They're very disappointed now.
Singing the song of angry men.
I just want to say
that thank you for this moment.
It is the music of the people
who will not be slaves again.
To consume all of this alcohol.
Thank you, Disney.
When the beating of your heart.
I've lost everyone else.
This is the thing that happens to me.
I do know that I sneeze after
X amount of alcohol.
Usually X amount is pretty low.
But right now my number...
30.
Only one country left.
Some of us.
I'm gonna have to sneeze our way to the finish line.
Hey, 10pm.
I found him.
And I got my something something ale.
Waddington.
It's garbage.
I mean, it's great.
I love it.
What is it?
God save the queen.
Honestly?
If you want me to be honest, I don't know.
It's probably the eating bad habits of some people.
God save the queen.
And I think the queen needs saving.
So here we are in Canada.
Three days later.
Because we didn't finish filming our thing.
But we did finish it.
And we finished with crown royal maple flavor.
It was just a shot.
Do you remember it?
I do.
I remember a maple essence hitting my palate.
Mixed well with the despair.
So what did we learn about the Epcot Challenge?
Eat.
If you must do it.
Remember to eat.
I saw it's almost 2 o'clock.
It's 2 o'clock right now and I saw some people just starting it.
Did you scream at them?
No, you need to eat.
You will forget to eat because you won't be hungry because you're drinking constantly.
And then by the time you get to Canada.
You'll be crying and not remembering anything.
No one cried.
That's the miracle.
We had 4 participants and no tears.
No tears.
There was some pouting.
There was a minor argument over a stupid thing.
No one cries.
No friendships were lost or broken.
No one vomited on the premises.
No one vomited on premises.
We waited until we got back to the resort.
Kept that all in.
Yeah, kept that in.
That's fairly successful.
Yeah.
That's pretty successful.
I did the Epcot Challenge once by myself and I didn't vote.
Okay, so the importance of electrolytes.
So I came prepared with potassium tablets and coconut water.
Which I forced down her throat.
Like a goose being fed for pate.
At the end of the night she was like forcing it.
Yeah, and you were like kind of gibberishing like some reason why I shouldn't.
Like, no I don't want it.
I was like, yes you do.
And no hangover the next day.
I felt great.
Yeah, that is the magic.
Like, if you don't want a hangover, because we're like either pushing 30 or in our 30s.
If you don't want a hangover, coconut water and potassium tablets.
Like, we have had no hangovers this whole trip, which is a minor miracle.
I know.
I mean, you don't want to waste your time at Disney World being hungover.
No.
So that's the thing I must impress the most.
Start early, eat, and remember coconut water.
And hydrate.
Very important.
So I guess we'll see you next week?
Cheers.