Hey YouTube, have you ever wondered why we only upload one video each month?
Well, the answer is really easy, time and money.
It's fun of course, but to make animation videos like this, a ridiculous amount of time is necessary,
writing the script, storyboard, designing all the stuff, recording the narration, animation, sound design, and composing original music.
We would love to make more videos, but it's just impossible right now without a time machine.
We all have real jobs and do Kurzgesagt late nights and on the weekends, because it's our passion.
But we'd prefer doing it while the sun is shining and make more videos for you guys.
But now, you can help us make more science and educational content.
There's this great new thing called Patreon.
Patreon is a crowdfunding platform like Kickstarter, but it works on a monthly basis with smaller amounts.
If you want, you can support us with a small sum each month, and we'll spend less time working elsewhere and make more videos.
Depending on the amount, you'll get cool rewards like graphics for your smartphone or computer,
our music, links in the video description, or I'll record your voicemail message.
This is the mailbox of a man called Jimmy. Something like that.
Even the smallest amounts help, and we really appreciate it.
Our videos will stay free on YouTube forever, so if you don't want to fund us, nothing will change for you.
If we get enough money through Patreon, we can invest more time in Kurzgesagt and make more than one video every four weeks in the future.
Thank you all for your attention. Lots of love for all the feels. Kurzgesagt.
kurzgesagt.com