Oh dear, just when you thought the Iraq problem was solved because you haven't heard about it for a while,
everything's back to murderous chaos and terror. What happened?
In 2003, the US invaded Iraq because of its alleged connections to terrorism and weapons
of mass destruction. At the time, Saddam Hussein, a brutal dictator, ruled the country.
He was part of the Sunni minority and suppressed the Shia majority.
Iraq was conquered fairly quickly, but the US had no plan for the country.
The until-then suppressed Shia majority took over and began oppressing the Sunnis
because suppressing other faiths has proven to be such a good idea.
Unsurprisingly, a Sunni rebel uprising began and terrorist groups like al-Qaeda trickled into Iraq
and local forces, often former Sunni military, began fighting the US troops and the newly formed
Iraqi state, peaking in a bloody civil war in 2006. Since then, people in Iraq have basically
been segregated by religion. So, in a tragic irony of history, the US invasion led to the
formation of the very terrorists the US wanted to eliminate in the first place because Iraq was now
the perfect training ground for terrorism. To understand this complicated conflict better,
we need to understand the relationship between the two main branches of the Muslim faith,
Shia and Sunni Islam. Sunnis make up about 80% of the Muslim world and Shia about 20%.
And the hardliners on both sides don't like each other very much.
Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two most powerful players in the game of faiths.
They both have no separation of state and religion, domestic problems,
and a lot of oil money. And they support groups that fight the other religious orientation.
And one of those terror organizations supported by Saudi Arabia was the Islamic State in Iraq,
or ISI for short. In 2010, the Arab Spring happened and changed the whole situation in
the Middle East. In Syria, dictator Bashar al-Assad didn't think much of resigning
and started a gruesome civil war against his own people. The longer the war went on,
the more foreign groups joined the fight, most of them for religious reasons and with the goal
of building an Islamic state in the region. And one of them was the infamous ISI, which now became
the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, or ISIS. They had fought in Iraq for years and had thousands
of well-trained and fanatic soldiers. They already quasi-controlled parts of Northern Iraq and were
very determined to build their religious state. And they changed the game in Syria like no one
expected. ISIS was so unbelievably violent and radical that soon it was at war with almost every
other faction of the Syrian rebel armies. They attacked and killed members of other Muslim
terrorist groups in the territories they controlled. They built an Islamic state with
rules so strict that even the hardliners of Al-Qaeda and Saudi Arabia were shocked
and withdrew their support. ISIS has been accused of responsibility for multiple massacres against
civilians, countless suicide bombings, the hostage taking of women and children, the execution of
their prisoners and beheadings. All kinds of medieval horrors we would rather not have to
illustrate. And this lovely gathering of human beings recently decided it was time to take more
territory in Iraq. Since the US left Iraq, the Shia Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki has monopolized
power and discriminated against Sunnis wherever possible. The government of Iraq is widely regarded
as being corrupt, incapable, and it's certainly hated by a large part of its citizens. The Iraqi
army, consisting of about 300,000 soldiers, was created using 25 billion US dollars in tax money,
but it's not loyal to its government and has been withdrawing or completely disbanding,
giving up city after city. Because ISIS has announced that everyone who opposes them will
be killed, they have proven they mean business. By June 2014, they'd conquered a big chunk of Iraq,
including Mosul, Iraq's second largest city. They'd stolen hundreds of millions from captured banks,
making them the richest terror organization on earth. And they are constantly working on
establishing a super medieval religious state. Iran and the US are even considering working
together to fight them. That's how gruesome the situation is. Events in Iraq show again that
exploiting the people you've defeated in a war, denying them power, a living and a stake in the
rebuilding of the country, is just sowing the seeds of the next bout of violence.
Somehow, we have to break this circle.