I have a couple of important announcements to make and then a bit of
feedback.
First, could the person who's running the Pottola 54 Facebook page
please get in touch with me? You wrote me a while back but unfortunately I had a
hard disk crash last October
and lost your details. For those who have written to the site
I can't access it so I'm afraid I can't respond. Second, good news for all those
who've been asking for higher quality videos of the Made Easy series
which you'll find in a playlist on this channel. Well the good news is I've now
uploaded DVD quality videos of the series
onto a new YouTube channel specifically for downloading
called Made Easy Series. You'll find the URL in this video description
and on my channel. This is the revised version of the series
without the religious content and with mistakes corrected so I'm pleased to say
it's already being used in a number of schools and universities.