now this is the story of the old west and it's a story of a man named
Sylvester and he was a dangerous gunslinger yes this is the pothole of
54 channel just bear with me they were in this bar playing cards and somebody
was cheating and next thing you know they go for their guns the guns are
jerked white gun smoke filled the room Sylvester got hit took a bullet tried to
shoot at him again but he got away he slipped out into the desert he collapsed
his face first into the ground and he's a goner and he starts drying and frying
and mummifying and ends up here at a Hall of Curiosities in Seattle where
visitors gawk at Sylvester's desert dried mummy and take pictures of the
blood-spattered bullet hole that killed him at least that's what Arizona's state
historian Marshall Trimble would have us believe but what does science tell us
well an autopsy of the body revealed it hadn't been mummified by the dry desert
heat at all because it was dripping wet with embalming fluid and scientists who
undertook the autopsy on behalf of the History Channel found that the fluid was
loaded with arsenic a common embalmers chemical used in the late 19th century
and they found the injection points in his legs where the fluid was pumped into
the veins and when they checked the hole in his stomach it wasn't consistent with
a bullet but a drill and the so-called blood spatter around it wasn't blood but
red paint and the autopsy revealed that Sylvester didn't die in a gunfight he
died of tuberculosis so what does Arizona's state historian have to say
now that a scientific analysis has shown that everything he believed was a crock
Sylvester can be anybody we want him to be and I want him to be a gunslinger
that's right he still wants to believe it to some people it doesn't matter what
the evidence is or what the science shows for the truly deluded if we want
the gunslinger story to be true then it's true well it's true for me you see
I believe you mean true for you is different from true for anybody else
it's a mindset a human failing that I've been trying to fathom for years of
course we all know that this kind of delusion is meat and potatoes for
creationists because the eye is so complex here's one asking Richard
Dawkins how evolution could make something as complex as an eye a
question Dawkins was able to answer quite easily you can make a slowly
climbing ramp of improvement from just the very rudiments of vision just say
being able to tell the difference between light and shade nothing more
than that right up to the perfection of a human eye or the eye of a hall I mean
there are flatworms that have just a cup for an eye note no lens not even a pinhole
there are animals like nautilus which is a sort of coiled up squid kind of thing
did you find that convincing I said about the eye well not really now you
might think this guy went on to say he didn't understand the explanation or he
found a flaw in the explanation or he questioned the evidence that supported
it but no none of these so what was the reason he didn't accept it let me tell
you what what happened in my brain at that particular moment in time was that
I was thinking of the book of Genesis and where God says that he made
everything according to its kind okay you're probably not all that surprised
after all he's a creationist but this video isn't about why religious people
delude themselves into disbelieving observable evidence and thinking that
science is all a conspiracy it's about why we still have that affliction even
in a post religious world in Western countries where religion is in decline
people aren't necessarily falling in line with science and rational thinking
instead they're turning to wacky ideas they hear from the internet and
believing as Bill O'Reilly would put it that even though science tells us it's
wrong it's true for them it's as if the need to believe is so ingrained in us
that having dispensed with gods and goddesses we now have to substitute new
beliefs that continue to contradict scientific evidence I don't think
there's a better example of this than the weird and wacky responses I got to
my video expanding earth my ass the video debunked the hilariously stupid
claim of comic book artist Neil Adams that the earth is growing and has
doubled in size over the last 60 million years it's a shame that this video takes
yes I must admit the video did take on a rather mocking tone after all I thought
no one still believes in a flat earth an expanding earth a hollow earth or an
earth made out of sponge cake these are ideas expounded by lone nutcases who
used to sit next to you in a pub and bother you with their conspiracy
theories but I hadn't counted on the power of the internet to bring all these
lone nutcases and their myriad conspiracy theories together into one
virtual room just like Sylvester the gunslinger the physics of the earth can
be whatever they want it to be I watched this video expecting an intelligent
counter-argument but got a video making fun of people oh you mean the
intelligent counter-argument that we can measure the earth's size and its mass
and neither is growing an observation is not disproved by the inability of the
observer to account for it no an observation is disproved right from the
start when there's no observation look if I stick a rock on some bathroom
scales and measure its dimensions and its weight and leave it overnight and it
hasn't grown in size then I'm not making an observation that it's got bigger is
it just me I explained all this in the video I don't know how much clearer it
can be scientists know the earth isn't growing because just like this rock they
can measure the distance of various points of the earth's surface from
satellites and what they found is exactly what was predicted by plate
tectonics uplift in mountain ranges where plates are colliding and
depression at subduction zones where plates are being pushed down and no net
growth they've measured how much the earth as a whole expands and contracts
every year and found the answer was naught point one millimeters in both
directions with no net expansion and we can measure the Earth's mass too
despite the fact that the earth is neither getting bigger or heavier like
Sylvester the gunslinger the earth is growing if they want it to be growing so
all they need to do is explain why one guy thinks helium is being produced in
the center of the earth and it's blowing up like a balloon another there's a star
inside the earth or the increased mass comes from trapped neutrinos ejected by
the Sun electron valence shells are expanding the Earth's the Sun frozen
gases are erupting through weak points the core is bubbly it's expanding
because it's getting hotter recycled materials and volcanoes are making it
bigger says one guy you're closed-minded and sad no that's not my description of
him that's his description of me can you come up with any of your own theories
no because you don't need my theory to explain something that we know is not
happening several people were convinced that sunlight falling on the earth turns
into matter plant life doesn't add mass also then I must take some biology
classes yes please take some biology classes and if you can't afford them
then take just one biology class and make it on the subject of where plants
get their carbon nitrogen potassium phosphorus and hydrogen from even if
they made sense which they don't we don't need any of these wacky stupid
dreamed up ideas to explain something that's not happening look can we just go
back to the rock see the rock now it's sitting in the garden doing nothing so
what's causing it to get bigger maybe little rock elves no don't try to
explain it it's a stupid question because it's not getting bigger okay
look here's the White House why is it painted red aliens may have needed the
government in secret no I don't need an explanation of why it's painted red
because it's not being painted red don't you get it now please stop because I'm
getting a headache I'm gonna lie down you are astoundingly ignorant let you in
as the earth is growing and growing it is shut up I don't care I assure you the
planet is gaining mass has been getting gas and will continue to do so as long
as it exists will you shut up on a clear night take some time and spend it
gazing at the beautiful night sky and I promise you you shall bear witness to
the miracle of meteors as they crash into the eye to start all over again
behold the truth is but a blink away pothola I am shocked you cannot know
this well you do now oh for sake do some maths all the dust and meteorites
falling from space every year amount to barely 40,000 tons about the size of the
Jefferson Memorial even if it's been a hundred times that amount every year for
the last 60 million years that's still around a trillionth the size of the
earth and it doesn't even come close to doubling its size so why are so many
people having so much trouble accepting basic science the author of the growing
earth video Neil Adams says he questioned science when he learned about
the creation of matter at the start of the Big Bang and it sounded to him like
magic that's why I always advise people to do this multiple choice if something
in science doesn't make sense to them you have to conclude that either
research scientists are all incompetent or they're all in on a conspiracy or
they know something you don't so find out what it is sadly Neil went for
option two and then made up his own science which he calls new science
whenever he was told it conflicted with some fundamental laws of physics he
decided these laws must be wrong yes you can do that when you make up your own
science trouble is it's very easy to prove or disprove a law of physics
because unlike a theory a law is basically a mathematical equation to
disprove it all you have to do is input the figures and show that the equation
doesn't balance so in the comments forum I established upfront which laws
Neil accepts and which he rejects and he told me he doesn't accept this Newton's
law of universal gravitation but for a very interesting reason because the moon
is receding from the earth and Newton says it shouldn't well Newton may say it
shouldn't but Newton's law says it should this was a problem for Newton
because he believed that a god-given universe ought to be perfect and have
perfect orbits his law showed that orbits would be influenced by the
gravitational attraction of other objects so Newton reasoned that God
would make constant adjustments to keep all the orbits stable the way to
disprove Newton's law isn't to invoke Newton's belief in divine intervention
but to input the figures and show the equation doesn't balance so I asked Neil
to show his calculations if the equation doesn't balance then Neil can
definitively prove his new science is right in response to my request here are
his calculations well what were you expecting did you really think he was
going to present the world with a calculation showing that one of the most
famous and fundamental laws of physics is wrong of course not instead when I
asked him to produce his calculations I was met with evasion delay waffle
diversion and of course personal attacks but at the end of it Neil had to admit
he didn't know the figures he hadn't worked it out and what's all this math
got to do with it anyway his ideas he said adjust concepts you don't need math
to work all this out just instinct in fact the law fits perfectly with the
recession of the moon and it's not that hard to see why as the earth rotates the
gravitational attraction of the moon causes a tidal bulge which rotates
ahead of the moon's orbit the effect is to slow the earth down over time and
effectively transfer this energy to the moon taking it into a higher orbit the
law tells us that the force of gravitational attraction is the
universal constant times the mass of the earth times the mass of the moon divided
by the distance between them squared and from Newton's second law we know that
force equals mass times acceleration and centripetal acceleration is the
velocity of the orbiting body squared divided by the radius this may look hard
but it's a simple question of substituting letters in the equation
which we all learn to do in elementary school a is v squared over R so let's do
that substitution and since this force is the same as this force the other two
sides of the equation must also be equal and since some of the values on both
sides of the equation are equal they cancel each other out and so we're left
with an equation that tells us the velocity of the moon squared equals the
gravitational constant times the mass of the earth divided by the distance
between them in other words the law tells us that as the moon moves into a
higher orbit and R increases then the velocity V has to decrease in order for
the equation to balance and that's exactly what we find the law balances
perfectly according to everyone who's worked it out it doesn't balance
according to Neil Adams who hasn't worked it out Neil if you still want to
insist that the law doesn't work in the case of the earth moon orbit then all
you have to do is input your figures and show that you're right why won't he do
it well no prizes for guessing and while he's at it show us how the supposed
increased mass and radius of this growing earth would affect the earth's
rotational velocity which is the other point I raise Neil told me he accepted
the law of conservation of angular momentum but after offering up a variety
of spurious excuses he finally admitted he didn't know whether an increasing
mass and radius would speed up the earth's rotation slow it down or keep it
the same now this is very basic physics on any rotating body either extra mass
or an increasing radius or a combination of both would slow down the
rotational speed and because it's a law of physics once again it's governed by a
mathematical equation so increasing the mass and radius of the earth would make
an earth day longer so here's a tip if you're going to invent a new science and
claim to have all the answers then at least try to familiarize yourself with
the physical laws you claim to accept or reject ok I do sympathize with Neil if
you don't understand scientific explanations for natural phenomena then
of course they must seem like magic in the past people attributed these natural
phenomena to God's goddesses and spirits in this post religious age if they don't
accept the scientific explanations they seek answers in conspiracies
what the heck is in our oxygen supply that create a rainbow effect in a
sprinkler one of the most common things I read on my channel are posts from
people who say they like my videos debunking religious belief but don't
agree with my debunking of whatever it is they believe but the point I'm making
is that if you're going to reject or cherry-pick science to support your
beliefs then it doesn't matter whether those beliefs are religious ideological
humanitarian or anything else you're changing reality to fit your conclusions
that's the exact opposite of science the answer to things we don't understand
isn't to assume that scientists must be conspiring against us but to accept that
we don't understand it take a tip from Clint Eastwood got to know his
limitations so instead of making assertions like dinosaurs could not have
lived on an earth this size put it in the form of a question what do
researchers say allowed dinosaurs to live on an earth this size find out what
it is the researchers know that you don't instead of claiming that the earth
is cooling because ice sheets have increased 60% one year put this in the
form of a question why do researchers still insist that ice sheets are
shrinking in other words instead of assuming a conspiracy find out what it
is they know that you don't sometimes they do ask questions but end up
completely ignoring the answer for example a lot of people asked how the
oldest oceanic crust is much younger than the oldest continental crust this
is something I explained in the video the answer is that oceanic plates are
continuously being created and subducted while continental plates aren't and once
you've asked the question and seen the answer that researchers have laid out in
research journals and textbooks and been shown the measurements and the evidence
don't hide behind scientific conspiracy crap simply because you don't want to
change your beliefs I don't care if you're an atheist an agnostic or the
sugarplum fairy that's no different to religious belief some people wonder why
I bother trying to correct all these idiotic fantasies does it matter yes
science is the foundation of our modern technological society and you should be
worried that an increasing number of people are not only dropping out of
science subjects in school they're turning to whacked-out nonsense based on
the idea that science is all a conspiracy as more people distrust
science they're failing to vaccinate their children we're seeing a
re-emergence of diseases that science had eradicated if governments based
their decisions on superstitions and beliefs rather than on hard science then
we're going to suffer the consequences you know Johannes Kepler spent five
years going through thousands of pieces of observational data to work out how
the planets orbit the Sun he would have given his right arm to have known the
answer we have the luxury of being able to learn about planetary orbits at the
click of a button and we're too lazy or stupid or too uninquiring to do it
instead we'd rather make something up now I've been a bit harsh in this video
so if I've embarrassed anyone or made them look stupid good you should feel
embarrassed you deserve to be laughed at because your brand of stupidity is
dangerous and don't bother telling me how arrogant I am for calling all these
conspiracy theorists stupid because I'm always happy to admit that I'm stupid
too this is one of the few things Neil Adams got right nothing wrong with being
too stupid to understand the kind of science that PhD physicists understand
that's the case not just for me but for ninety nine point nine percent of the
population the difference is I accept that I'm too stupid to understand it so
when something in science doesn't make sense to me I don't assume it's because
scientists are incompetent or devious I either try to find out what it is I
don't understand or if I'm too stupid to wrap my head around it which is often
the case then I follow the Clint Eastwood philosophy and accept my
limitations I don't go bounding off to create my own version of science light
which is science based on belief without the need for any complicated
mathematical equations
he can go for a whole year he can go for a whole year on one grain of rice Neil
Adams has done more to bring the fact of Earth's expansion to millions of people
than anyone oh god another armchair scientist still posting in support of
this crap we have no place in official accepted science thankfully that gives
us the freedom to state our beliefs and theories we're not paid to tow I think
he means tow the line by any university or government agency well if scientific
discoveries at universities and scientific institutions are all
conspiracy-led crap then why bother with it to away with science class in school
and science degrees and scientific research let's all sit in armchairs and
make up theories and put our beliefs into chat rooms and videos and the
belief or theory with the most number of likes gets to be true long live free
thinkers oh is that what you are presumably free from the constraint of
having to make your conclusion fit observations or use math or have your
work fact-checked yeah sounds groovy the problem is while you attack those who
did stay awake in science class and did take the time to study and get degrees
and spend years doing painstaking research for a pittance you have the
gall to use the technology they've created to do it with when you use a
computer to write your comments and blogs you're using a machine that
depends on Ohm's law and Kirchhoff's law when you phone your friends to tell them
Newton's law of universal gravitation is wrong you're using satellite technology
that depends on Newton's law of gravitation to get that message through
when you start your stupid car to attend your stupid meeting with other stupid
new-age flat hollow growing sponge cake earth delusionist nut jobs your starter
motor depends on Faraday's law and the oil it runs on was found using Snell's
law and the engine depends on the laws of thermodynamics so the next time a
stupid thought bubble enters your head and you feel like telling the rest of
the world about it just stop and do what I do if my stupid thought is at odds
with known and accepted science and physical laws then I have only three
options and you know what they are either scientists are all incompetent or
they're all in on a conspiracy or they know something I don't and I need to
find out what that is hint try option three first