Thanks for your last response Tony. We're really making progress in our list of disputed issues bringing us down to just one
Tony has now dropped his claim that methane is not a significant greenhouse gas
After I gave facts and figures showing that it is and called on him to cite a single study that shows otherwise
And he's dropped his claim that I blew over Al Gore's assertion about co2 correlation after I showed that I had criticized it
In addition, he couldn't cite a single study by any of the many scientists. He claimed poked holes in a paper by Shakoon et al
So the one issue he's still trying to defend is his claim that positive feedback can't contribute to
Deglaciation and his belief that this would have led to runaway warming and boiling oceans
Before I respond to that because it won't take long. Let me start with something a little more harmonious
I'm delighted that Tony now agrees with the accepted definition of an argument from authority
As I explained in my last video
It doesn't refer to peer-reviewed studies because these are the building blocks of science an argument from authority
Also known as an appeal to authority is claiming that just because a scientist or some other authority gives an opinion
It must therefore be true
Tony now agrees the process of simply quoting expert opinion is an appeal to authority
And I'm sure Tony would also agree that if quoting the opinion of an authority is bad
Then quoting the opinion of someone who isn't an authority like me or Tony is even worse
I've been saying the same thing in my videos for the last 12 years. Here are some clips
Quoting what experts say in television interviews or blogs or even congressional inquiries is called an argument from authority
What matters is not what these contrarians assert in blogs and TV interviews
What matters is the evidence they publish in scientific papers supporting those assertions
Simply listing names and appealing to authority let alone a phony authority is not how science is done
This is why I never report something as science on the basis that a scientist says it is
But people who watch Tony Heller's last video will sway blind that I must do because Tony said I did
Journalists like pothole are left to make appeals to authority pothole are frequently points on his videos that
Professional scientists said this or professional scientists said that I don't use the phrase professional scientists said
Firstly because not all professional scientists are researchers and what matters is research because that's how science is done
Secondly because it doesn't matter what scientists say as Tony and I both agree
What matters is what's been published in peer-reviewed studies?
So I always quote these studies anytime you hear the words researchers say or the authors say in my videos
It's always referring to what they say in a peer-reviewed study
Tony doesn't show any video clips to support his claim
Of course, but because we both have time to fact-check in this debate and cite our sources. I can
So here's where I referenced researchers in my last video
The authors measured oxygen isotopes in the air bubbles trapped in the ice the authors say exactly the same thing as the Indiana
University website what may explain it say the authors from this new data
Researchers have calculated that changed they show their figures they cite their sources
But what they found is that even if as they explain in the study
They're measuring finding video evidence like this is why a fact-checking format is crucial in any science debate
And why Tony wants to end it
Every time he makes a claim, however trivial. It's very easy to fact-check and show that he's got it wrong
So to make Tony's claim accurate
He should have said pot Ola frequently points on his videos that peer-reviewed studies said this or peer-reviewed studies said that
And that would be correct because that is exactly how science is done
And that brings us to Tony's last remaining issue
He's already said in two previous videos that because the role of positive feedback in
Deglaciations doesn't make any sense to him. He doesn't accept it and his third video simply repeats that
So now we're gonna look at the science of feedback and see why that doesn't make any sense
We're all familiar with audio feedback
Tony even gives the same example of audio feedback that I've already
Explained is wrong with a gain of greater than one the sound is coming out of the speaker feeding back into the microphone getting louder
It's going around this loop and gets louder and louder and louder
But as I've explained twice now
The earth has a mechanism for slowing down the rate of warming once the initial forcing stops as it gets warmer
The earth radiates more heat
So the amount of outgoing energy rises until it matches the amount of incoming energy and the temperature
Stabilizes at the equilibrium temperature. There's no such mechanism in Tony's audio feedback example
Which is why you get runaway feedback there, but not in the Earth's energy system
Secondly as Tony himself admits the feedback of the audio system has a gain of greater than one
That's not the case with the earth
This is a crucial difference because as I explained once the initial forcing stops Earth's temperature feedback
Dampens down over time that doesn't happen with audio feedback
Thirdly in the case of glacial cycles changes in the earth's tilt and orbit work against runaway warming as
I explained they eventually send the climate out of an interglacial and back into another glaciation
No, such cycles exist that reverse audio feedback
So now let's discuss the consequences of potholars theory
But as I've repeatedly shown I'm not explaining my theories here
These are measurements and calculations published in peer-reviewed scientific papers
Of course, Tony should know this by now
Because I've said or my theory might so many times that some people want to make it a meme
I've shown these papers and cited them in the video description
Insisting that it's my theory is a great debating tactic
Because of course it means Tony can avoid reading these studies and he doesn't feel he has to rebut them
But after three videos trying to pretend that all I'm doing is cobbling together. My own theory is wearing a little thin
The difference between my explanation and Tony's is that you don't have to take my word for any of this
It's so well understood that it's been established physics for four decades and is laid out very clearly in papers that I've cited
Tony doesn't suggest that I've misrepresented or misunderstood these studies and anyone is free to read them and check
by contrast Tony hasn't provided anything except an appeal to his own authority or in this case a lack of
authority
The argument I hear from a lot of his subscribers is well Tony's got a geology degree
Well, I've got a geology degree too. It doesn't make me an expert on the Earth's energy systems
And even if both of us were experts in this we've already agreed that citing expert opinion is an appeal to authority
This isn't an arts debate where we're debating our personal opinions. This is science
Tony can't just decide that the Earth's feedback system is greater than the forcing because that's his opinion
He has to show where this has been measured and calculated and he needs to cite scientific studies
That support his belief that these feedbacks ought to lead to runaway warming and boiling oceans. I've asked twice now
So I'm hoping third time lucky