Are you worried about video game feminists?
Well now, for the low, low price of $15,000 a month for an undisclosed amount of time,
you, yes you, can be a part of gaming history and make two dudes have more money than before.
Help Jordan Owen and Devo Sarini afford a new camcorder and maybe some fucking makeup.
She's a professional victim, I tell you.
She fled her home and she's a professional.
Those things are technically, it's technically accurate, goddammit.
$15,000.
Why would I waste money on a mere feature-length documentary when I can watch Jordan Owen ranting
on his couch about Anita Sarkeesian for 14 fucking hours for free?
But now we have to go on the run, the feminists drop Davis in the forest and he doesn't want
to get dirt on his turtleneck.
Come on Davis, we have to, no, stop lecturing me about ethics, we have to get out of here
and can you please stop trying to start a forest fire?
$15,000.
I can't wait to be told what to think by this guy, I mean, he has such amazing thoughts
about ethnic minorities.
You should be absolutely furious with the niggers, not the blacks, the fucking niggers.
Whites had been working for the past several hundred years to eliminate slavery throughout
the globe and even when we bought the black slaves, we treated them extremely well.
Oh, of course he has a trilby, of course, why wouldn't he?
I mean, what else would you hang on your novelty toy skull?
$15,000?
But don't worry though, these guys are totally cool with women, hell, women love them, they
get plenty of ass.
At the strip club.
And I'll tell you right now, my favourite dancer at my favourite club is Molly at Tattletales.
Go look her up and you'll find out why.
But enough of that bullshit, all this talking about murdering video game women's making
me Ayn Randi, if you know what I'm fucking saying, that was a pun.
Being befuddled to talk about objectivity, the hottest legs in Atlanta just walked down
the sidewalk outside.
What did the guy they were attached to have to say for himself?
$15,000 a month.
If Atlas shrugs any harder, he'll fall off his dad's fucking couch.
$11 billion Canadian US dollars.
This should be the kind of thing that people are mobilising over.
We should be out in the streets, en masse, destroying video game feminism.
Yeah, you're really fucking out there right now.
Is that Corinthian leather or did you make it out of all those fucking belts?
What?
Why are there belts in the corner?
$15,000.
David Serrini has a fucking blog.
Oh, sweet.
He's a master of text, not just audio and visuals.
A better class of people hiked up those mountains.
Politics just melt away, leaving a bunch of fat, pasty white guys.
The colour just melted right off all my black friends that I totally have.
Actually, they didn't want to go hiking with me for some reason.
On paper, I have nothing against white nationalism.
I am a huge white nationalist on paper.
This guy knows exactly what women are like.
Women in our culture have become the most decadent sluts since the fall of Rome.
Going out for gang bangs every weekend and despising the men that would actually treat
them with love, dignity and respect.
$15,000.
But enough about women, let's do some Bible study.
So, a series of videos on theology.
I don't think these are going to be the most popular videos I ever record.
Not the plastic fucking niggers.
So it starts out, Eve allows herself to be tricked by the serpent.
Any of you men out there with experience with women, know that women are so prone to this.
They want to be seen.
The Bible, the number one authoritative source on women.
Oh my god.
Holy shit.
It just keeps...
Holy fucking...
$15,000.
Don't get him started on Karl Marx, a guy who's worked, he's totally red.
You see it with the Marxists.
The Marxists say the capitalist class stole all the money.
So we're going to go burn down their houses and rape their children and torture them and
hang them and take their property, then we'll have a socialist utopia.
He knows, he knows, he knows.
$15,000.
My opinion is so expensive that wearing normal clothes wouldn't do it justice.
If you give me $15,000, I'll be able to make a suit out of money and that will justify
my opinion.
Okay, fuck it.
I'll watch one more of these and then I'm just going to forget these guys.
Hold on a second.
Is he playing the Sims while he..
Holy f...
What.
What the fuck.
What?!
What?
How many of those do you...
He moves it between shots.
He just keeps...
Oh my fu...
I'm crying.
I'm dying.
Holy fuck.
What the fuck?
What?
I'm dying.
I feel like I should say something at least semi-serious in this if people are going to
end up watching this.
In one of his videos, David Sorini openly admits that whenever he says anything that
sounds even vaguely progressive, he gets a bunch of shit off of white nationalists.
Like, they see him saying something that's not pro-white people, and they get pissy with
him.
Obviously, this is a terrible thing, and the people who do that are the worst kind of scum,
but the real question is why so many white nationalists watch his videos in the first
place?
Like, have you considered that maybe you're attracting the wrong audience when you talk
about how bad black people are, or women in general?
Come on now.
I actually, like, watched through some of that stuff, so I could make some kind of long-winded
fucking 40-minute rebuttal, but all I could f- it- all you can do is laugh.
You don't- you don't need to bother, like, it's-
I can't- I can't believe there's fucking skulls all over the place.
I hope it's not real.
Oh my god, is it real?